-DOCSTART- -X- O
Gitanggong -X- _ O
karon -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
Carbon -X- _ B-LOC
Police -X- _ I-LOC
Station -X- _ I-LOC
ang -X- _ O
langyaw -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
si -X- _ O
Ken -X- _ B-PER
. -X- _ O

Dihang -X- _ O
wa -X- _ O
nakahatag -X- _ O
og -X- _ O
igong -X- _ O
rason -X- _ O
nganong -X- _ O
kuyog -X- _ O
niya -X- _ O
ang -X- _ O
mga -X- _ O
bata -X- _ O
, -X- _ O
gi-turnover -X- _ O
si -X- _ O
Ken -X- _ B-PER
ngadto -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
kapulisan -X- _ O
. -X- _ O

Hugot -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
gipanghimakak -X- _ O
ni -X- _ O
Ken -X- _ B-PER
nga -X- _ O
duna -X- _ O
siyay -X- _ O
dautang -X- _ O
tuyo -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
mga -X- _ O
bata -X- _ O
. -X- _ O

Matod -X- _ O
niya -X- _ O
, -X- _ O
lima -X- _ O
ka -X- _ O
tuig -X- _ O
na -X- _ O
siya -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
nagbalik-balik -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
Sugbo -X- _ B-LOC
aron -X- _ O
pagtabang -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
pamilya -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
maong -X- _ O
mga -X- _ O
bata -X- _ O
. -X- _ O

Nakurat -X- _ O
na -X- _ O
lang -X- _ O
siya -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
gi-hold -X- _ O
sila -X- _ O
diha -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
terminal -X- _ O
. -X- _ O

Giklaro -X- _ O
sab -X- _ O
niya -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
upat -X- _ O
lang -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
iyang -X- _ O
kuyog -X- _ O
ang -X- _ O
menor -X- _ O
de -X- _ O
edad -X- _ O
samtang -X- _ O
ang -X- _ O
duha -X- _ O
nag-edad -X- _ O
na -X- _ O
og -X- _ O
19 -X- _ O
ug -X- _ O
18 -X- _ O
anyos -X- _ O
. -X- _ O

Nagsugod -X- _ O
ang -X- _ O
panaghigala­ay -X- _ O
nila -X- _ O
ni -X- _ O
Ken -X- _ B-PER
sa -X- _ O
pamilya -X- _ O
dihang -X- _ O
nakaila -X- _ O
niya -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
internet -X- _ O
ang -X- _ O
inahan -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
mga -X- _ O
bata -X- _ O
lima -X- _ O
ka -X- _ O
tuig -X- _ O
na -X- _ O
ang -X- _ O
nakalabay -X- _ O
. -X- _ O

Bisan -X- _ O
og -X- _ O
naminyo -X- _ O
ug -X- _ O
nakaanak -X- _ O
na -X- _ O
kini -X- _ O
, -X- _ O
nagpadayon -X- _ O
ang -X- _ O
ilang -X- _ O
panaghigalaay -X- _ O
. -X- _ O

Gani -X- _ O
lakip -X- _ O
ang -X- _ O
mga -X- _ O
ginikanan -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
ilang -X- _ O
ikakuyog -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
Moalboal -X- _ B-LOC
ug -X- _ O
ila -X- _ O
lang -X- _ O
kining -X- _ O
hapiton -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
Siyudad -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
Naga -X- _ B-LOC
kon -X- _ O
nakadayon -X- _ O
pa -X- _ O
lang -X- _ O
unta -X- _ O
sila -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
pagsakay -X- _ O
og -X- _ O
bus -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
terminal -X- _ O
. -X- _ O

Gihimug-atan -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
langyaw -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
di -X- _ O
lang -X- _ O
ang -X- _ O
maong -X- _ O
pamilya -X- _ O
ang -X- _ O
iyang -X- _ O
natabangan -X- _ O
. -X- _ O

Gani -X- _ O
naka-volunteer -X- _ O
siya -X- _ O
ug -X- _ O
nitabang -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
rehabilitasyon -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
Bogo -X- _ B-LOC
City -X- _ I-LOC
human -X- _ O
ang -X- _ O
bagyong -X- _ O
Yolanda -X- _ B-OTHER
niadtong -X- _ O
2013 -X- _ O
. -X- _ O

Ang -X- _ O
usa -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
mga -X- _ O
dalagita -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
kuyog -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
langyaw -X- _ O
, -X- _ O
nihimakak -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
may -X- _ O
pagpangabuso -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
himuon -X- _ O
ang -X- _ O
langyaw -X- _ O
kanila -X- _ O
bugti -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
iyang -X- _ O
pagtabang -X- _ O
ug -X- _ O
paglibre -X- _ O
kanila -X- _ O
. -X- _ O

Matod -X- _ O
niya -X- _ O
, -X- _ O
matag -X- _ O
anhi -X- _ O
ni -X- _ O
Ken -X- _ B-PER
ubanon -X- _ O
sila -X- _ O
niini -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
pag- -X- _ O
travel -X- _ O
. -X- _ O

Gihikay -X- _ O
na -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
Carbon -X- _ B-ORG
Police -X- _ I-ORG
Station -X- _ I-ORG
ang -X- _ O
mga -X- _ O
dokumento -X- _ O
alang -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
pagpasaka -X- _ O
og -X- _ O
tukmang -X- _ O
kaso -X- _ O
batok -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
langyaw -X- _ O
. -X- _ O

Lakip -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
gisukit-sukit -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
mga -X- _ O
pulis -X- _ O
ang -X- _ O
ginikanan -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
mga -X- _ O
bata -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
kuyog -X- _ O
niini -X- _ O
. -X- _ O

Mokabat -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
15 -X- _ O
ka -X- _ O
mga -X- _ O
tawo -X- _ O
ang -X- _ O
nangaangol -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
pabuto -X- _ O
, -X- _ O
apan -X- _ O
way -X- _ O
naangol -X- _ O
tungod -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
saag -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
mga -X- _ O
bala -X- _ O
sukad -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
gabii -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
Pasko -X- _ B-OTHER
hangtod -X- _ O
kagahapon -X- _ O
, -X- _ O
matod -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
usa -X- _ O
ka -X- _ O
opisyal -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
Department -X- _ B-ORG
of -X- _ I-ORG
Health -X- _ I-ORG
( -X- _ I-ORG
DOH -X- _ I-ORG
) -X- _ I-ORG
7 -X- _ I-ORG
. -X- _ O

Tulo -X- _ O
ka -X- _ O
mga -X- _ O
tawo -X- _ O
ang -X- _ O
nabut­han -X- _ O
og -X- _ O
pabuto -X- _ O
atol -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
pagsaulog -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
Pasko -X- _ 
sa -X- _ O
dakbayan -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
Lapu-Lapu -X- _ B-LOC
samtang -X- _ O
usa -X- _ O
ka -X- _ O
balay -X- _ O
kansang -X- _ O
kisame -X- _ O
nalungag -X- _ O
gumikan -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
stray -X- _ O
bullet -X- _ O
. -X- _ O

Sa -X- _ O
pagka-gabii -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
Disyembre -X- _ O
24 -X- _ O
ug -X- _ O
25 -X- _ O
nadala -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
tambalanan -X- _ O
ang -X- _ O
mga -X- _ O
biktima -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
dihang -X- _ O
ang -X- _ O
8 -X- _ O
anyos -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
si -X- _ O
Inot -X- _ B-PER
naka-angkon -X- _ O
og -X- _ O
paso -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
nawong -X- _ O
ug -X- _ O
gamay -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
gisi -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
iyang -X- _ O
ngabil -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
dihang -X- _ O
nabuthan -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
whistle -X- _ O
bomb -X- _ O
. -X- _ O

Si -X- _ O
Capitan -X- _ O
nabuthan -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
tuo -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
mata -X- _ O
samtang -X- _ O
wa -X- _ O
matino -X- _ O
kon -X- _ O
asa -X- _ O
ang -X- _ O
paso -X- _ O
o -X- _ O
samad -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
naangkon -X- _ O
ni -X- _ O
Agnes -X- _ B-PER
. -X- _ O

Sa -X- _ O
laing -X- _ O
bahin -X- _ O
, -X- _ O
usa -X- _ O
ka -X- _ O
ginang -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
taga-barangay -X- _ B-LOC
Bankal -X- _ I-LOC
ang -X- _ O
mi-post -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
iyang -X- _ O
kasinatian -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
Pasko -X- _ O
diin -X- _ O
nipadayag -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
iyang -X- _ O
kabalaka -X- _ O
human -X- _ O
ang -X- _ O
kisame -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
ilang -X- _ O
balay -X- _ O
nabuslot -X- _ O
gumikan -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
saag -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
bala -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
mitugpa -X- _ O
. -X- _ O

Nanawagan -X- _ O
si -X- _ O
Carreon -X- _ B-PER
sa -X- _ O
kapulisan -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
palapdan -X- _ O
pa -X- _ O
ang -X- _ O
ilang -X- _ O
monitoring -X- _ O
ug -X- _ O
supervision -X- _ O
alang -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
mas -X- _ O
luwas -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
kasaulogan -X- _ O
, -X- _ O
ilabi -X- _ O
na -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
naghinangat -X- _ O
ang -X- _ O
Bag-ong -X- _ O
Tuig -X- _ O
. -X- _ O

Bisan -X- _ O
pa -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
mao -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
mga -X- _ O
hitabo -X- _ O
, -X- _ O
kapulisan -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
Central -X- _ B-LOC
Visayas -X- _ I-LOC
mihulagway -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
malinawon -X- _ O
ug -X- _ O
hapsay -X- _ O
ang -X- _ O
pagsaulog -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
Pasko -X- _ B-OTHER
karong -X- _ O
tuiga -X- _ O
itandi -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
milabayng -X- _ O
tuig -X- _ O
samtang -X- _ O
menos -X- _ O
usab -X- _ O
ang -X- _ O
biktima -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
pabuto -X- _ O
tungod -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
pasidaan -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
kapulisan -X- _ O
. -X- _ O

Ang -X- _ O
traffic -X- _ O
enforcers -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
Talisay -X- _ B-LOC
City -X- _ I-LOC
ug -X- _ O
lungsod -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
Minglanilla -X- _ B-LOC
nanghimakak -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
mga -X- _ O
alegasyon -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
social -X- _ O
media -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
wa -X- _ O
silay -X- _ O
gihimo -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
pagsulbad -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
grabeng -X- _ O
paghuot -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
trapiko -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
Cebu -X- _ B-LOC
South -X- _ I-LOC
Coastal -X- _ I-LOC
Road -X- _ I-LOC
niadtong -X- _ O
Sabado -X- _ O
. -X- _ O

Labing -X- _ O
minos -X- _ O
10 -X- _ O
ka -X- _ O
oras -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
wa -X- _ O
hapit -X- _ O
makairog -X- _ O
ang -X- _ O
trapiko -X- _ O
niadtong -X- _ O
Sabado -X- _ O
, -X- _ O
gikan -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
hapon -X- _ O
, -X- _ O
hangtod -X- _ O
na -X- _ O
nianang -X- _ O
gabii -X- _ O
. -X- _ O

Gibasol -X- _ O
ni -X- _ O
de -X- _ B-PER
la -X- _ I-PER
Peña -X- _ I-PER
ang -X- _ O
upat -X- _ O
ka -X- _ O
mga -X- _ O
aksidente -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
sakyanan -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
gitaho -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
nahitabo -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
samang -X- _ O
oras -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
dapit -X- _ O
ubos -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
jurisdiction -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
Minglanilla -X- _ B-LOC
. -X- _ O

Matod -X- _ O
ni -X- _ O
de -X- _ B-PER
la -X- _ I-PER
Peña -X- _ I-PER
nga -X- _ O
ilang -X- _ O
gitawag -X- _ O
ang -X- _ O
ilang -X- _ O
mga -X- _ O
kauban -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
Minglanilla -X- _ B-LOC
, -X- _ O
apan -X- _ O
way -X- _ O
bisan -X- _ O
usa -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
nanubag -X- _ O
. -X- _ O

Tungod -X- _ O
niini -X- _ O
, -X- _ O
nanawag -X- _ O
sila -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
Minglanilla -X- _ B-ORG
Police -X- _ I-ORG
Station -X- _ I-ORG
aron -X- _ O
magpatabang -X- _ O
. -X- _ O

Samtang -X- _ O
di -X- _ O
tinuod -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
way -X- _ O
traffic -X- _ O
enforcers -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
lungsod -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
Minglanilla -X- _ B-LOC
niadtong -X- _ O
Sabado -X- _ O
. -X- _ O

Mga -X- _ O
opisyal -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
lungsod -X- _ O
nakadawat -X- _ O
og -X- _ O
mga -X- _ O
pagsaway -X- _ O
, -X- _ O
labina -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
social -X- _ O
media -X- _ O
, -X- _ O
human -X- _ O
natanggong -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
karsada -X- _ O
. -X- _ O

Ang -X- _ O
kahuot -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
trapiko -X- _ O
naggikan -X- _ O
pa -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
dakbayan -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
Talisay -X- _ B-LOC
lahos -X- _ O
na -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
lungsod -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
Minglanilla -X- _ B-LOC
. -X- _ O

Si -X- _ O
municipal -X- _ O
administrator -X- _ O
Concordio -X- _ B-PER
Mejias -X- _ I-PER
niingon -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
siya -X- _ O
mismo -X- _ O
natanggong -X- _ O
usab -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
trapiko -X- _ O
niadtong -X- _ O
higayona -X- _ O
og -X- _ O
duha -X- _ O
usab -X- _ O
ka -X- _ O
oras -X- _ O
nianang -X- _ O
gabii -X- _ O
. -X- _ O

Matod -X- _ O
niya -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
dili -X- _ O
lang -X- _ O
ang -X- _ O
lungsod -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
Minglanilla -X- _ B-LOC
ang -X- _ O
grabeng -X- _ O
trapik -X- _ O
, -X- _ O
apil -X- _ O
na -X- _ O
usab -X- _ O
ang -X- _ O
Cebu -X- _ B-LOC
city -X- _ I-LOC
, -X- _ O
Talisay -X- _ B-LOC
, -X- _ O
Naga -X- _ B-LOC
, -X- _ O
San -X- _ B-LOC
Fernando -X- _ I-LOC
hangtod -X- _ O
na -X- _ O
siyudad -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
Carcar -X- _ B-LOC
. -X- _ O

Iya -X- _ O
usab -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
gihimakak -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
nag-party -X- _ O
ang -X- _ O
mga -X- _ O
traffic -X- _ O
enforcers -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
maong -X- _ O
adlaw -X- _ O
, -X- _ O
hinungdan -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
walay -X- _ O
makita -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
enforcers -X- _ O
. -X- _ O

Nagkanayon -X- _ O
si -X- _ O
Mejias -X- _ B-PER
nga -X- _ O
igo -X- _ O
lang -X- _ O
silang -X- _ O
naniudto -X- _ O
ug -X- _ O
human -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
paniudto -X- _ O
, -X- _ O
mibalik -X- _ O
ra -X- _ O
usab -X- _ O
sila -X- _ O
dayon -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
ilang -X- _ O
puwesto -X- _ O
. -X- _ O

Usa -X- _ O
ka -X- _ O
taxi -X- _ O
driver -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
nahinabi -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
Superbalita -X- _ B-ORG
Cebu -X- _ I-ORG
nibutyag -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
mga -X- _ O
alas -X- _ O
3 -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
hapon -X- _ O
siyang -X- _ O
nihatod -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
iyang -X- _ O
pasahero -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
dakbayan -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
Naga -X- _ B-LOC
gikan -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
Tabunok -X- _ B-LOC
, -X- _ I-LOC
Talisay -X- _ I-LOC
City -X- _ I-LOC
. -X- _ O

Niabot -X- _ O
sila -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
Naga -X- _ B-LOC
mga -X- _ O
alas -X- _ O
8 -X- _ O
na -X- _ O
hapit -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
gabii -X- _ O
tungod -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
kahuot -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
trapiko -X- _ O
. -X- _ O

Niabot -X- _ O
siya -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
Cebu -X- _ B-LOC
City -X- _ I-LOC
mga -X- _ O
alas -X- _ O
11 -X- _ O
na -X- _ O
pasado -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
gabii -X- _ O
. -X- _ O

Alkanse -X- _ O
tong -X- _ O
biyahia -X- _ O
kay -X- _ O
P700 -X- _ O
kapin -X- _ O
rang -X- _ O
patak -X- _ O
. -X- _ O

Tungod -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
gilantawan -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
tingsakay -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
paghinangat -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
Bag-ong -X- _ O
Tuig -X- _ O
, -X- _ O
ang -X- _ O
mga -X- _ O
tinugyanan -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
Cebu -X- _ B-ORG
South -X- _ I-ORG
Bus -X- _ I-ORG
Terminal -X- _ I-ORG
nanawagan -X- _ O
ug -X- _ O
nihangyo -X- _ O
karon -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
mga -X- _ O
police -X- _ O
station -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
matag -X- _ O
lungsod -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
mag-deploy -X- _ O
og -X- _ O
personnel -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
makatabang -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
pagdumala -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
trapiko -X- _ O
. -X- _ O

Usa -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
nakitang -X- _ O
hinungdan -X- _ O
nganong -X- _ O
mangatanggong -X- _ O
ang -X- _ O
mga -X- _ O
pasahero -X- _ O
diha -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
terminal -X- _ O
mao -X- _ O
ang -X- _ O
kalangay -X- _ O
usab -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
pagbalik -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
mga -X- _ O
bus -X- _ O
tungod -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
grabeng -X- _ O
traffic -X- _ O
. -X- _ O

Gikan -X- _ O
Disyembre -X- _ O
22 -X- _ O
hangtud -X- _ O
Disyembre -X- _ O
25 -X- _ O
, -X- _ O
anaa -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
kapin -X- _ O
131,000 -X- _ O
ka -X- _ O
mga -X- _ O
pasahero -X- _ O
ang -X- _ O
gibana-banang -X- _ O
nidagsa -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
CSBT -X- _ B-LOC
. -X- _ O

Kini -X- _ O
base -X- _ O
usab -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
natala -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
mga -X- _ O
bus -X- _ O
trips -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
niabot -X- _ O
og -X- _ O
592 -X- _ O
niadtong -X- _ O
Biyernes -X- _ O
, -X- _ O
579 -X- _ O
niadtong -X- _ O
Sabado -X- _ O
, -X- _ O
655 -X- _ O
niadtong -X- _ O
Domingo -X- _ O
ug -X- _ O
556 -X- _ O
niadtong -X- _ O
Lunes -X- _ O
, -X- _ O
adlaw -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
Pasko -X- _ O
. -X- _ O

Apan -X- _ O
matod -X- _ O
ni -X- _ O
CBST -X- _ B-ORG
Operations -X- _ O
Manager -X- _ O
Joey -X- _ B-PER
Herrera -X- _ I-PER
, -X- _ O
anaa -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
700 -X- _ O
ang -X- _ O
average -X- _ O
bus -X- _ O
trips -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
ilang -X- _ O
matala -X- _ O
panahon -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
tingsakay -X- _ O
. -X- _ O

Ang -X- _ O
pag-menus -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
bus -X- _ O
trip -X- _ O
atol -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
tingsakay -X- _ O
pagsugat -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
Pasko -X- _ O
gitumbok -X- _ O
ni -X- _ O
Herrera -X- _ B-PER
nga -X- _ O
tungod -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
kalangay -X- _ O
pagbalik -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
mga -X- _ O
bus -X- _ O
gikan -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
ilang -X- _ O
biyahe -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
habagatang -X- _ O
Sugbo -X- _ B-LOC
. -X- _ O

Sigun -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
CSBT -X- _ B-ORG
management -X- _ O
, -X- _ O
ang -X- _ O
grabeng -X- _ O
traffic -X- _ O
maoy -X- _ O
hinungdan -X- _ O
nganong -X- _ O
dugay -X- _ O
makabalik -X- _ O
ang -X- _ O
mga -X- _ O
bus -X- _ O
ug -X- _ O
maoy -X- _ O
nakaingon -X- _ O
nganong -X- _ O
daghan -X- _ O
ang -X- _ O
mangatanggong -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
pasahero -X- _ O
diha -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
terminal -X- _ O
. -X- _ O

Niadtong -X- _ O
Sabado -X- _ O
, -X- _ O
ang -X- _ O
security -X- _ O
manager -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
terminal -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
si -X- _ O
Joy -X- _ B-PER
Tumulak -X- _ I-PER
, -X- _ O
personal -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
nihangyo -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
Police -X- _ O
Regional -X- _ O
Office -X- _ O
7 -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
mag-deploy -X- _ O
og -X- _ O
mga -X- _ O
pulis -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
makatabang -X- _ O
pagbantay -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
trapiko -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
mga -X- _ O
lungsod -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
southern -X- _ O
Cebu -X- _ B-LOC
, -X- _ O
butang -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
gipatalinghugan -X- _ O
dayon -X- _ O
ni -X- _ O
Chief -X- _ O
Supt. -X- _ O
Mario -X- _ B-PER
Espino -X- _ I-PER
. -X- _ O

Ang -X- _ O
lungsod -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
Minglanilla -X- _ B-LOC
maoy -X- _ O
gitumbok -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
terminal -X- _ O
ug -X- _ O
bisan -X- _ O
gani -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
mga -X- _ O
pasahero -X- _ O
, -X- _ O
diin -X- _ O
nasinati -X- _ O
ang -X- _ O
grabeng -X- _ O
kahuot -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
trapiko -X- _ O
. -X- _ O

Giingong -X- _ O
way -X- _ O
nakita -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
mga -X- _ O
traffic -X- _ O
enforcer -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
maong -X- _ O
lungsod -X- _ O
niadtong -X- _ O
Sabado -X- _ O
tungod -X- _ O
kay -X- _ O
nagpahigayon -X- _ O
sila -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
ilang -X- _ O
Christmas -X- _ O
party -X- _ O
, -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
gihimakak -X- _ O
usab -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
opisyal -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
mao -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
lungsod -X- _ O
. -X- _ O

Daghang -X- _ O
mga -X- _ O
netizen -X- _ O
ang -X- _ O
nakasaway -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
mga -X- _ O
traffic -X- _ O
enforcer -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
Minglanilla -X- _ B-LOC
kay -X- _ O
wa -X- _ O
nila -X- _ O
makit-i -X- _ O
dihang -X- _ O
naghuot -X- _ O
ug -X- _ O
wa -X- _ O
na -X- _ O
hapit -X- _ O
makairog -X- _ O
ang -X- _ O
taas -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
trapiko -X- _ O
padung -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
habagatan -X- _ O
ug -X- _ O
dakbayan -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
Sugbo -X- _ B-LOC
. -X- _ O

Patay -X- _ O
ang -X- _ O
usa -X- _ O
ka -X- _ O
security -X- _ O
guard -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
hubog -X- _ O
nagmaniho -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
iyang -X- _ O
motorsiklo -X- _ O
ug -X- _ O
nakabangga -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
gikasugat -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
laing -X- _ O
motorsiklo -X- _ O
atol -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
Pasko -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
national -X- _ O
highway -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
Barangay -X- _ B-LOC
Fuente -X- _ I-LOC
, -X- _ O
lungsod -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
Carmen -X- _ B-LOC
. -X- _ O

Si -X- _ O
Ian -X- _ B-PER
Vincent -X- _ I-PER
Perales -X- _ I-PER
, -X- _ O
29 -X- _ O
minyo -X- _ O
taga -X- _ O
Barangay -X- _ B-LOC
Poblacion -X- _ I-LOC
Carmen -X- _ I-LOC
, -X- _ O
DOA -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
tambalanan -X- _ O
samtang -X- _ O
grabe -X- _ O
ang -X- _ O
kahimtang -X- _ O
ni -X- _ O
Flaviano -X- _ B-PER
Ornopia -X- _ I-PER
, -X- _ O
31 -X- _ O
, -X- _ O
usa -X- _ O
ka -X- _ O
security -X- _ O
guard -X- _ O
taga -X- _ O
Barangay -X- _ B-LOC
Cogon -X- _ I-LOC
, -X- _ O
lungsud -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
Tabogon -X- _ B-LOC
. -X- _ O

Si -X- _ O
Chief -X- _ O
Insp -X- _ O
Christian -X- _ B-PER
Torres -X- _ I-PER
, -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
nahinabi -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
Superba­lita -X- _ B-ORG
nagkanayon -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
mga -X- _ O
alas -X- _ O
8:10 -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
gabii -X- _ O
Disyembre -X- _ O
25 -X- _ O
, -X- _ O
giingong -X- _ O
hubog -X- _ O
ang -X- _ O
guwardiya -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
si -X- _ O
Ornopia -X- _ B-PER
nga -X- _ O
nagmaniho -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
iyang -X- _ O
motorsiklo -X- _ O
. -X- _ O

Ang -X- _ O
guwardiya -X- _ O
padulong -X- _ O
moduty -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
Liloan -X- _ B-LOC
, -X- _ O
gikasugat -X- _ O
niini -X- _ O
ang -X- _ O
gisakyan -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
biktima -X- _ O
. -X- _ O

Ang -X- _ O
guwardiya -X- _ O
tungod -X- _ O
kay -X- _ O
hubog -X- _ O
kusog -X- _ O
nakapadagan -X- _ O
wala -X- _ O
na -X- _ O
mosubay -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
lane -X- _ O
gidaro -X- _ O
ang -X- _ O
gisakyang -X- _ O
motorsiklong -X- _ O
gisakyan -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
biktima -X- _ O
. -X- _ O

Gidali -X- _ O
sila -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
pagdala -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
tambalanan -X- _ O
pero -X- _ O
dead-on-arrival -X- _ O
ang -X- _ O
biktima -X- _ O
. -X- _ O

Mga -X- _ O
nabiktima -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
sunog -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
Barangay -X- _ B-LOC
Lawaan-3 -X- _ I-LOC
, -X- _ O
dakbayan -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
Talisay -X- _ B-LOC
makadawat -X- _ O
og -X- _ O
financial -X- _ O
assistance -X- _ O
og -X- _ O
tag -X- _ O
P10 -X- _ O
mil -X- _ O
alang -X- _ O
niadtong -X- _ O
maoy -X- _ O
tag-iya -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
balay -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
hingpit -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
naugdaw -X- _ O
. -X- _ O

Kahinomduman -X- _ O
pipila -X- _ O
ka -X- _ O
oras -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
wala -X- _ O
pa -X- _ O
ang -X- _ O
pagsaulog -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
Pasko -X- _ O
usa -X- _ O
ka -X- _ O
dakong -X- _ O
sunog -X- _ O
ang -X- _ O
miulbo -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
sityo -X- _ O
Caduldulan -X- _ B-LOC
, -X- _ I-LOC
Barangay -X- _ I-LOC
Lawaan-3 -X- _ I-LOC
, -X- _ O
alas -X- _ O
6:40 -X- _ O
nadawat -X- _ O
ang -X- _ O
alarma -X- _ O
samtang -X- _ O
alas -X- _ O
8:30 -X- _ O
hingpit -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
napawong -X- _ O
ang -X- _ O
kayo -X- _ O
. -X- _ O

Ang -X- _ O
giingong -X- _ O
paggamit -X- _ O
og -X- _ O
butane -X- _ O
maoy -X- _ O
gitumbok -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
hinungdan -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
sunog -X- _ O
apan -X- _ O
ang -X- _ O
kabomebrohan -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
Tlaisay -X- _ B-LOC
padayon -X- _ O
pa -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
ilang -X- _ O
gihimong -X- _ O
inbestigasyon -X- _ O
. -X- _ O

Gibana-bana -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
mokabat -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
400 -X- _ O
mil -X- _ O
pesos -X- _ O
ang -X- _ O
gibilin -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
danyos -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
sunog -X- _ O
. -X- _ O

Si -X- _ O
Felipa -X- _ B-PER
Solana -X- _ I-PER
ang -X- _ O
pangulo -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
City -X- _ B-ORG
Social -X- _ I-ORG
Welfare -X- _ I-ORG
and -X- _ I-ORG
Services -X- _ I-ORG
miingon -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
base -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
labing -X- _ O
uwahi -X- _ O
nilang -X- _ O
record -X- _ O
adunay -X- _ O
96 -X- _ O
ka -X- _ O
pamilya -X- _ O
kon -X- _ O
384 -X- _ O
ka -X- _ O
mga -X- _ O
individual -X- _ O
. -X- _ O

Samtang -X- _ O
, -X- _ O
80 -X- _ O
ang -X- _ O
maoy -X- _ O
tag-iya -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
mga -X- _ O
balay -X- _ O
15 -X- _ O
ang -X- _ O
nag-abang -X- _ O
ug -X- _ O
adunay -X- _ O
87 -X- _ O
ang -X- _ O
hingpitng -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
nangaugdaw -X- _ O
ug -X- _ O
9 -X- _ O
ka -X- _ O
mga -X- _ O
balay -X- _ O
ang -X- _ O
naapektohan -X- _ O
lang -X- _ O
og -X- _ O
gamay -X- _ O
. -X- _ O

Matod -X- _ O
ni -X- _ O
Solana -X- _ B-PER
nga -X- _ O
ang -X- _ O
kagamhanan -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
Talisay -X- _ B-LOC
mohatag -X- _ O
og -X- _ O
tag -X- _ O
P10 -X- _ O
mil -X- _ O
alang -X- _ O
niadtong -X- _ O
mga -X- _ O
tag-iya -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
balay -X- _ O
, -X- _ O
samtang -X- _ O
kadtong -X- _ O
nag-abang -X- _ O
ug -X- _ O
hingpit -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
naugdaw -X- _ O
ang -X- _ O
ilang -X- _ O
balay -X- _ O
tag -X- _ O
P5 -X- _ O
mil -X- _ O
. -X- _ O

Iya -X- _ O
usab -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
gibutyag -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
ang -X- _ O
luna -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
nasunog -X- _ O
gipanag-iya -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
prebaong -X- _ O
tawo -X- _ O
adunay -X- _ O
pipila -X- _ O
niini -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
nagbayad -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
yuta -X- _ O
apan -X- _ O
uban -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
wala -X- _ O
kadudahan -X- _ O
pa -X- _ O
kon -X- _ O
makabalik -X- _ O
ba -X- _ O
kining -X- _ O
tukod -X- _ O
. -X- _ O

Hinuon -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
pagkakaron -X- _ O
, -X- _ O
ang -X- _ O
mga -X- _ O
nabiktima -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
sunog -X- _ O
kasamtangan -X- _ O
karong -X- _ O
nagbutang -X- _ O
og -X- _ O
tent -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
lugar -X- _ O
samtang -X- _ O
nahatagan -X- _ O
na -X- _ O
kining -X- _ O
pasiunang -X- _ O
tabang -X- _ O
sama -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
mga -X- _ O
pagka-on -X- _ O
. -X- _ O

Si -X- _ O
Mayor -X- _ O
Eduardo -X- _ B-PER
Gullas -X- _ I-PER
ug -X- _ O
Kongresista -X- _ O
Samsam -X- _ B-PER
Gullas -X- _ I-PER
personal -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
mibisita -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
lugar -X- _ O
aron -X- _ O
mohatag -X- _ O
og -X- _ O
tabang -X- _ O
. -X- _ O

Makubra -X- _ O
na -X- _ O
ang -X- _ O
libuan -X- _ O
ka -X- _ O
Cebu -X- _ B-LOC
City -X- _ I-LOC
scholars -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
ilang -X- _ O
transportation -X- _ O
allowance -X- _ O
kin­sa -X- _ O
nagpuyo -X- _ O
gikan -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
mga -X- _ O
bu­k­irang -X- _ O
barangay -X- _ O
ning -X- _ O
dakbayan -X- _ O
. -X- _ O

Si -X- _ O
Mayor -X- _ O
Tomas -X- _ B-PER
Osmeña -X- _ I-PER
, -X- _ O
kinsa -X- _ O
tua -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
Estados -X- _ B-LOC
Unidos -X- _ I-LOC
, -X- _ O
nianunsyo -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
karong -X- _ O
Dis­yembre -X- _ O
28 -X- _ O
, -X- _ O
ilang -X- _ O
makubra -X- _ O
ang -X- _ O
binuwan -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
allowance -X- _ O
gikan -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
city -X- _ O
government -X- _ O
. -X- _ O

Ang -X- _ O
city -X- _ O
scholars -X- _ O
kon -X- _ O
mga -X- _ O
tinun-an -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
ni-graduate -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
public -X- _ O
high -X- _ O
school -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
karon -X- _ O
nag-eskuwela -X- _ O
na -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
lainlaing -X- _ O
unibersidad -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
dakbayan -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
Sugbo -X- _ B-LOC
ug -X- _ O
nagpuyo -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
mountain -X- _ O
barangay -X- _ O
adunay -X- _ O
allowance -X- _ O
gikan -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
siyudad -X- _ O
gawas -X- _ O
. -X- _ O

Ang -X- _ O
mga -X- _ O
city -X- _ O
scholar -X- _ O
giawhag -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
pagpakigtambayayong -X- _ O
ngadto -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
mga -X- _ O
Barangay -X- _ O
Mayor’s -X- _ O
Officer -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
bukirang -X- _ O
barangay -X- _ O
sanglit -X- _ O
sagad -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
ilang -X- _ O
mga -X- _ O
kapitan -X- _ O
dili -X- _ O
kaalyado -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
administrasyon -X- _ O
. -X- _ O

Si -X- _ O
City -X- _ O
Treasurer -X- _ O
Veronica -X- _ B-PER
Morelos -X- _ I-PER
nagkanayon -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
niaging -X- _ O
semana -X- _ O
giatiman -X- _ O
na -X- _ O
nila -X- _ O
ang -X- _ O
payroll -X- _ O
ug -X- _ O
aduna -X- _ O
nay -X- _ O
kwarta -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
gitagana -X- _ O
para -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
pag-apud-apod -X- _ O
niini -X- _ O
ugmang -X- _ O
adlawa -X- _ O
. -X- _ O

Naukay -X- _ O
ang -X- _ O
mga -X- _ O
nag-shopping -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
mall -X- _ O
human -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
kalit -X- _ O
lang -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
nilagobo -X- _ O
ang -X- _ O
ground -X- _ O
floor -X- _ O
ug -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
ilang -X- _ O
pagsusi -X- _ O
, -X- _ O
tawo -X- _ O
kini -X- _ O
. -X- _ O

Dali -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
gitabang -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
security -X- _ O
personnel -X- _ O
ang -X- _ O
biktima -X- _ O
ug -X- _ O
gidala -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
Chong -X- _ B-LOC
Hua -X- _ I-LOC
Hospital -X- _ I-LOC
sa -X- _ O
North -X- _ I-LOC
Reclamation -X- _ I-LOC
Area -X- _ I-LOC
. -X- _ O

Ang -X- _ O
hepe -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
Mabolo -X- _ B-ORG
police -X- _ I-ORG
station -X- _ I-ORG
Chief -X- _ O
Insp. -X- _ O
Clark -X- _ B-PER
Suarez -X- _ I-PER
Arriola -X- _ I-PER
nangunay -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
pagsusi -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
crime -X- _ O
scene -X- _ O
n­itug-an -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
ang -X- _ O
biktima -X- _ O
giila -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
si -X- _ O
Rodrigo -X- _ B-PER
Delos -X- _ I-PER
Santos -X- _ I-PER
Maglasang -X- _ I-PER
, -X- _ O
45 -X- _ O
, -X- _ O
ulitawo -X- _ O
, -X- _ O
engineer -X- _ O
, -X- _ O
taga -X- _ O
Palompon -X- _ B-LOC
, -X- _ I-LOC
Leyte -X- _ I-LOC
, -X- _ O
apan -X- _ O
naa -X- _ O
nag -X- _ O
trabaho -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
Commission -X- _ B-ORG
on -X- _ I-ORG
Elections -X- _ I-ORG
sa -X- _ O
Tuburan -X- _ B-LOC
isip -X- _ O
election -X- _ O
assistant -X- _ O
. -X- _ O

Gidugang -X- _ O
ni -X- _ O
Arriola -X- _ B-PER
nga -X- _ O
nagpadayon -X- _ O
pa -X- _ O
ang -X- _ O
ilang -X- _ O
imbestigasyon -X- _ O
kon -X- _ O
unsay -X- _ O
hinungdan -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
miambak -X- _ O
si -X- _ O
Maglasang -X- _ B-PER
. -X- _ O

Ipahigayon -X- _ O
karong -X- _ O
adlaw -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
Huwebes -X- _ O
ang -X- _ O
public -X- _ O
bidding -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
P150 -X- _ O
milyones -X- _ O
para -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
paghakot -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
libuan -X- _ O
ka -X- _ O
toneladang -X- _ O
basura -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
dakbayan -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
Sugbo -X- _ B-LOC
sa -X- _ O
mosunod -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
unom -X- _ O
ka -X- _ O
buwan -X- _ O
. -X- _ O

Ang -X- _ O
kontrata -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
Jomara -X- _ B-ORG
Konstruckt -X- _ I-ORG
Corporation -X- _ I-ORG
kinsa -X- _ O
maoy -X- _ O
service -X- _ O
provider -X- _ O
gikan -X- _ O
niadtong -X- _ O
buwan -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
Agusto -X- _ O
gikatakdang -X- _ O
mapupos -X- _ O
karong -X- _ O
Disyembre -X- _ O
31 -X- _ O
diin -X- _ O
ang -X- _ O
City -X- _ O
Government -X- _ O
nagbayad -X- _ O
og -X- _ O
tag -X- _ O
P1,296 -X- _ O
matag -X- _ O
1,000 -X- _ O
ka -X- _ O
kilong -X- _ O
basura -X- _ O
. -X- _ O

Atol -X- _ O
unya -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
bidding -X- _ O
proper -X- _ O
, -X- _ O
ang -X- _ O
adunay -X- _ O
labing -X- _ O
ubos -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
bid -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
tulo -X- _ O
ka -X- _ O
service -X- _ O
provider -X- _ O
maoy -X- _ O
madeklara -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
mananaog -X- _ O
ug -X- _ O
hayag -X- _ O
na -X- _ O
ang -X- _ O
kahigayonan -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
sila -X- _ O
ang -X- _ O
makakuha -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
kontrata -X- _ O
sanglit -X- _ O
human -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
bidding -X- _ O
isunod -X- _ O
dayon -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
technical -X- _ O
working -X- _ O
group -X- _ O
ang -X- _ O
post -X- _ O
qualification -X- _ O
. -X- _ O

Sa -X- _ O
niaging -X- _ O
mga -X- _ O
kontrata -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
paghakot -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
basura -X- _ O
, -X- _ O
ang -X- _ O
Jomara -X- _ B-ORG
ug -X- _ O
ang -X- _ O
Pamocor -X- _ B-ORG
nagpulipuli -X- _ O
og -X- _ O
daog -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
bidding -X- _ O
sanglit -X- _ O
sila -X- _ O
ra -X- _ O
ang -X- _ O
klaro -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
service -X- _ O
provider -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
nipalit -X- _ O
og -X- _ O
bid -X- _ O
documents -X- _ O
apan -X- _ O
niining -X- _ O
bahin -X- _ O
tulo -X- _ O
na -X- _ O
sila -X- _ O
ang -X- _ O
magpaubsanay -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
presyo -X- _ O
. -X- _ O

Aron -X- _ O
masiguro -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
mga -X- _ O
pi­niriso -X- _ O
ingon -X- _ O
man -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
publiko -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
wa’y -X- _ O
recycled -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
ma­hitabo -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
mga -X- _ O
nakolekta -X- _ O
nila -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
kontrabando -X- _ O
, -X- _ O
gipakita -X- _ O
ni -X- _ O
Rubio -X- _ B-PER
sa -X- _ O
mga -X- _ O
tigbalita -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
ilahang -X- _ O
gisunog -X- _ O
ingon -X- _ O
man -X- _ O
giguba -X- _ O
ang -X- _ O
mga -X- _ O
nakuha -X- _ O
nila -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
mga -X- _ O
kontrabando -X- _ O
. -X- _ O

Matod -X- _ O
ni -X- _ O
Rubio -X- _ B-PER
nga -X- _ O
80 -X- _ O
porsyento -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
maong -X- _ O
kontabando -X- _ O
gipanglabay -X- _ O
kini -X- _ O
gikan -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
Operation -X- _ O
Second -X- _ O
chance -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
pasilidad -X- _ O
diin -X- _ O
mga -X- _ O
bata -X- _ O
ang -X- _ O
gisugo -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
paglabay -X- _ O
niini -X- _ O
. -X- _ O

Samtang -X- _ O
ang -X- _ O
laing -X- _ O
20 -X- _ O
porsyento -X- _ O
mao -X- _ O
kini -X- _ O
ang -X- _ O
gisuwayan -X- _ O
pagpasulod -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
mga -X- _ O
bisita -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
prisohan -X- _ O
. -X- _ O

Dugang -X- _ O
ni -X- _ O
Rubio -X- _ B-PER
nga -X- _ O
kasagaran -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
mga -X- _ O
kontrabando -X- _ O
mga -X- _ O
sigarilyo -X- _ O
diin -X- _ O
niabot -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
kapin -X- _ O
500 -X- _ O
ka -X- _ O
mga -X- _ O
pakete -X- _ O
, -X- _ O
14 -X- _ O
ka -X- _ O
mga -X- _ O
cell -X- _ O
phones -X- _ O
, -X- _ O
chargers -X- _ O
ug -X- _ O
uban -X- _ O
pa -X- _ O
. -X- _ O

Subay -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
ilang -X- _ O
hugot -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
seguridad -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
maong -X- _ O
prisohan -X- _ O
, -X- _ O
14 -X- _ O
na -X- _ O
usab -X- _ O
ka -X- _ O
mga -X- _ O
bisita -X- _ O
ang -X- _ O
ilan -X- _ O
gi-ban -X- _ O
aron -X- _ O
di -X- _ O
na -X- _ O
ni -X- _ O
makapalusot -X- _ O
ingon -X- _ O
man -X- _ O
makasulod -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
maong -X- _ O
pasilidad -X- _ O
. -X- _ O

Sa -X- _ O
ilang -X- _ O
nakuha -X- _ O
, -X- _ O
way -X- _ O
bisan -X- _ O
usa -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
drugas -X- _ O
niini -X- _ O
. -X- _ O

Karong -X- _ O
adlawa -X- _ O
ang -X- _ O
open -X- _ O
house -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
CCJ -X- _ B-ORG
diin -X- _ O
gilauman -X- _ O
ang -X- _ O
pagdagsa -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
tawo -X- _ O
alang -X- _ O
na -X- _ O
usab -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
paghatag -X- _ O
og -X- _ O
kahigayonan -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
makabisita -X- _ O
ang -X- _ O
ilang -X- _ O
pamilya -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
mga -X- _ O
piniriso -X- _ O
. -X- _ O

Dugang -X- _ O
ni -X- _ O
Rubio -X- _ B-PER
nga -X- _ O
wa -X- _ O
siya’y -X- _ O
tawo -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
gipa-break -X- _ O
o -X- _ O
gipabakasyon -X- _ O
aron -X- _ O
masiguro -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
magpabilin -X- _ O
ang -X- _ O
seguridad -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
maong -X- _ O
pasilidad -X- _ O
. -X- _ O

Human -X- _ O
hingpit -X- _ O
na -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
mahibalik -X- _ O
ang -X- _ O
biyahe -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
bus -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
Cebu -X- _ B-LOC
South -X- _ I-LOC
Bus -X- _ I-LOC
Terminal -X- _ I-LOC
, -X- _ O
possible -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
magnihit -X- _ O
kini -X- _ O
karong -X- _ O
adlawa -X- _ O
hilabi -X- _ O
na -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
ang -X- _ O
mga -X- _ O
driver -X- _ O
moseleb­rar -X- _ O
usab -X- _ O
og -X- _ O
pasko -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
tagsa-tagsa -X- _ O
nila -X- _ O
ka -X- _ O
mga -X- _ O
pamilya -X- _ O
. -X- _ O

Bisan -X- _ O
og -X- _ O
hingpit -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
nahibalik -X- _ O
ang -X- _ O
mga -X- _ O
biyahe -X- _ O
paingon -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
habagatang -X- _ O
Sugbo -X- _ B-LOC
. -X- _ O

Dugang -X- _ O
niya -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
way -X- _ O
pro­blema -X- _ O
ang -X- _ O
biyahe -X- _ O
gikan -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
Sugbo -X- _ B-LOC
paingon -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
Dumaguete -X- _ B-LOC
apan -X- _ O
ang -X- _ O
Dumaguete -X- _ B-LOC
paingon -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
Dapitan -X- _ B-LOC
, -X- _ O
wala -X- _ O
pa -X- _ O
higpit -X- _ O
nahibalik -X- _ O
human -X- _ O
ubos -X- _ O
pa -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
Signal -X- _ O
No. -X- _ O
1 -X- _ O
ang -X- _ O
Zamboanga -X- _ B-LOC
atol -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
pakighinabi -X- _ O
niini -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
tigbalita -X- _ O
kagahapon -X- _ O
. -X- _ O

Hinuon -X- _ O
, -X- _ O
aduna’y -X- _ O
mga -X- _ O
pasa­hero -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
nibiyahe -X- _ O
na -X- _ O
paingon -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
Dumaguete -X- _ B-LOC
aron -X- _ O
didto -X- _ O
nav­lang -X- _ O
maghuwat -X- _ O
paingon -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
Da­pitan -X- _ B-LOC
, -X- _ I-LOC
Zamboanga -X- _ I-LOC
del -X- _ I-LOC
Norte -X- _ I-LOC
. -X- _ O

Lakip -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
nahibalik -X- _ O
na -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
biyahe -X- _ O
ang -X- _ O
paingon -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
Bacolod -X- _ B-LOC
ug -X- _ O
Guihulngan -X- _ B-LOC
, -X- _ I-LOC
Negros -X- _ I-LOC
Oriental -X- _ I-LOC
diin -X- _ O
manukad -X- _ O
kini -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
Tangil -X- _ B-ORG
Wharf -X- _ I-ORG
sa -X- _ O
lungsod -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
Dumanjug -X- _ B-LOC
. -X- _ O

Kagahapon -X- _ O
nidagsa -X- _ O
na -X- _ O
ang -X- _ O
mga -X- _ O
pasahero -X- _ O
ug -X- _ O
nipahimang­no -X- _ O
si -X- _ O
Tumulak -X- _ B-PER
sa -X- _ O
mga -X- _ O
nagpla­no -X- _ O
pa -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
mobiyahe -X- _ O
ka­rong -X- _ O
adlawa -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
dili -X- _ O
magdala -X- _ O
og -X- _ O
daghang -X- _ O
bagahe -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
di -X- _ O
kinahanglanon -X- _ O
. -X- _ O

Hilabina -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
mga -X- _ O
butang -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
di -X- _ O
pwe­­­de -X- _ O
isulod -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
terminal -X- _ O
ug -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
bus -X- _ O
, -X- _ O
naglakip -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
pabuto -X- _ O
, -X- _ O
kemikal -X- _ O
, -X- _ O
hinagiban -X- _ O
, -X- _ O
pintal -X- _ O
ug -X- _ O
uban -X- _ O
pa -X- _ O
. -X- _ O

Ang -X- _ O
puti -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
van -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
duha -X- _ O
pa -X- _ O
lang -X- _ O
ka -X- _ O
buwan -X- _ O
sukad -X- _ O
napa­­lit -X- _ O
, -X- _ O
gipanag-iya -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
usa -X- _ O
ka -X- _ O
Rex -X- _ B-PER
Sal­­gariño -X- _ I-PER
base -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
resibo -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
gi­­pakita -X- _ O
ni -X- _ O
Rosito -X- _ B-PER
Paquiao -X- _ I-PER
, -X- _ O
ang -X- _ O
dray­­­ber -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
van -X- _ O
, -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
giisyuhan -X- _ O
og -X- _ O
Inspection -X- _ O
Report -X- _ O
Summo -X- _ O
( -X- _ O
IRS -X- _ O
) -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
mga -X- _ O
tinugyanan -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
LTFRB -X- _ B-ORG
7 -X- _ I-ORG
. -X- _ O

Matod -X- _ O
ni -X- _ O
Cuizon -X- _ B-PER
, -X- _ O
moabot -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
P200,000 -X- _ O
ang -X- _ O
multa -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
masakpan -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
colorum -X- _ O
van -X- _ O
ug -X- _ O
kini -X- _ O
maadto -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
ilang -X- _ O
buhatan -X- _ O
. -X- _ O

Gisumbalik -X- _ O
og -X- _ O
reklamo -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
singer-negosyante -X- _ O
ug -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
iyang -X- _ O
bana -X- _ O
ang -X- _ O
ilang -X- _ O
kanhi -X- _ O
employer -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
nipasangil -X- _ O
nila -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
nangilad -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
gipalit -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
P2.5 -X- _ O
milyones -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
townhouse -X- _ O
niadtong -X- _ O
2016 -X- _ O
. -X- _ O

Si -X- _ O
Eva -X- _ B-PER
Delos -X- _ I-PER
Santos -X- _ I-PER
ug -X- _ O
ang -X- _ O
iyang -X- _ O
bana -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
si -X- _ O
Ruben -X- _ B-PER
David -X- _ I-PER
, -X- _ O
nipasaka -X- _ O
og -X- _ O
reklamong -X- _ O
libel -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
Cebu -X- _ B-LOC
City -X- _ I-LOC
Prosecutors -X- _ I-LOC
Office -X- _ I-LOC
nga -X- _ O
nag-akusar -X- _ O
ni -X- _ O
Prisca -X- _ B-PER
Niña -X- _ I-PER
Mabatid -X- _ I-PER
, -X- _ O
tag-iya -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
Pinoy -X- _ B-ORG
Care -X- _ I-ORG
Visa -X- _ I-ORG
Center -X- _ I-ORG
, -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
nidaot -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
ilang -X- _ O
reputasyon -X- _ O
pinaagi -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
live -X- _ O
interview -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
Facebook -X- _ B-OTHER
ug -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
napublikar -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
mga -X- _ O
pamantalaan -X- _ O
niadtong -X- _ O
Disyembre -X- _ O
21 -X- _ O
, -X- _ O
2017 -X- _ O
. -X- _ O

Ang -X- _ O
magtiayon -X- _ O
nitumbok -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
nasayod -X- _ O
nang -X- _ O
daan -X- _ O
si -X- _ O
Ma­batid -X- _ B-PER
nga -X- _ O
naka-loan -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
Me­trobank -X- _ B-ORG
ang -X- _ O
townhouse -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
wala -X- _ O
pa -X- _ O
kini -X- _ O
gibaligya -X- _ O
ngadto -X- _ O
niya -X- _ O
ug -X- _ O
niuyon -X- _ O
kini -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
maoy -X- _ O
mopadayon -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
nahabilin -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
balanse -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
mortgage -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
P1.9 -X- _ O
milyones -X- _ O
. -X- _ O

Sila -X- _ O
nidugang -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
bakak -X- _ O
usab -X- _ O
ang -X- _ O
pasangil -X- _ O
ni -X- _ O
Mabatid -X- _ B-PER
nga -X- _ O
gibaligya -X- _ O
ngadto -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
laing -X- _ O
tawo -X- _ O
ang -X- _ O
townhouse -X- _ O
. -X- _ O

Si -X- _ O
Eva -X- _ B-PER
nihilak -X- _ O
samtang -X- _ O
nagbasa -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
ilang -X- _ O
pamahayag -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
gipatawag -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
press -X- _ O
conference -X- _ O
kagahapon -X- _ O
kuyog -X- _ O
ang -X- _ O
ilang -X- _ O
tu­lo -X- _ O
ka -X- _ O
mga -X- _ O
anak -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
sila -X- _ O
si -X- _ O
Moni­que -X- _ B-PER
, -X- _ O
Ana -X- _ B-PER
ug -X- _ O
James -X- _ B-PER
Carlos -X- _ I-PER
ug -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
ilang -X- _ O
duha -X- _ O
ka -X- _ O
mga -X- _ O
lawyer -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
sila -X- _ O
si -X- _ O
Atty. -X- _ O
Daniel -X- _ B-PER
Francis -X- _ I-PER
Arguedo -X- _ I-PER
ug -X- _ O
Atty. -X- _ O
Patrick -X- _ B-PER
Gallito -X- _ I-PER
. -X- _ O

Siya -X- _ O
nipasangil -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
napalit -X- _ O
niya -X- _ O
ang -X- _ O
townhouse -X- _ O
gikan -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
magtiayong -X- _ O
Delos -X- _ B-PER
Santos -X- _ I-PER
ug -X- _ O
nibayad -X- _ O
kini -X- _ O
og -X- _ O
P2.5 -X- _ O
milyones -X- _ O
niadtong -X- _ O
Hunyo -X- _ O
7 -X- _ O
, -X- _ O
2016 -X- _ O
. -X- _ O

Matod -X- _ O
ni -X- _ O
Mabatid -X- _ B-PER
nga -X- _ O
gipalit -X- _ O
niya -X- _ O
ang -X- _ O
townhouse -X- _ O
gikan -X- _ O
kang -X- _ O
Eva -X- _ B-PER
aron -X- _ O
tabangan -X- _ O
kini -X- _ O
tungod -X- _ O
kay -X- _ O
giingong -X- _ O
naglisod -X- _ O
kini -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
panalapi -X- _ O
. -X- _ O

Apan -X- _ O
ang -X- _ O
magtiayon -X- _ O
nisumbalik -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
wala -X- _ O
na -X- _ O
magbayad -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
iyang -X- _ O
binuwan -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
amortization -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
banko -X- _ O
si -X- _ O
Mabatid -X- _ B-PER
sukad -X- _ O
niadtong -X- _ O
Hulyo -X- _ O
ning -X- _ O
tuiga -X- _ O
human -X- _ O
kini -X- _ O
nila -X- _ O
gireklamo -X- _ O
og -X- _ O
illegal -X- _ O
dismissal -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
National -X- _ B-ORG
Labor -X- _ I-ORG
Relations -X- _ I-ORG
Commission -X- _ I-ORG
( -X- _ I-ORG
NLRC -X- _ I-ORG
) -X- _ I-ORG
. -X- _ O

Si -X- _ O
David -X- _ B-PER
kanhi -X- _ O
nagtrabaho -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
Pinoy -X- _ B-ORG
Care -X- _ I-ORG
sud -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
usa -X- _ O
ka -X- _ O
tuig -X- _ O
ug -X- _ O
pito -X- _ O
ka -X- _ O
buwan -X- _ O
isip -X- _ O
speaker -X- _ O
ug -X- _ O
naghupot -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
operations -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
Middle -X- _ B-LOC
East -X- _ I-LOC
samtang -X- _ O
si -X- _ O
Eva -X- _ B-PER
speaker -X- _ O
usab -X- _ O
sud -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
dul-an -X- _ O
usa -X- _ O
ka -X- _ O
tuig -X- _ O
. -X- _ O

Apan -X- _ O
niadtong -X- _ O
Hulyo -X- _ O
4 -X- _ O
, -X- _ O
2017 -X- _ O
, -X- _ O
gi­­taktak -X- _ O
sila -X- _ O
ni -X- _ O
Mabatid -X- _ B-PER
sa -X- _ O
trabaho -X- _ O
. -X- _ O

Sila -X- _ O
nagtuo -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
nanimawos -X- _ O
si -X- _ O
Mabatid -X- _ B-PER
nila -X- _ O
ug -X- _ O
ni-pressure -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
bakwion -X- _ O
ang -X- _ O
labor -X- _ O
case -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
gipasaka -X- _ O
batok -X- _ O
niya -X- _ O
ug -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
kompaniya -X- _ O
niini -X- _ O
. -X- _ O

Apil -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
gikiha -X- _ O
og -X- _ O
libel -X- _ O
ang -X- _ O
mga -X- _ O
editor -X- _ O
ug -X- _ O
tigbalita -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
mga -X- _ O
mantalaan -X- _ O
apan -X- _ O
suma -X- _ O
pa -X- _ O
ni -X- _ O
Arguedo -X- _ B-PER
, -X- _ O
nagplano -X- _ O
sila -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
bakwion -X- _ O
ang -X- _ O
reklamo -X- _ O
batok -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
mga -X- _ O
sakop -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
media -X- _ O
. -X- _ O

Usa -X- _ O
ka -X- _ O
semana -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
wa -X- _ O
pa -X- _ O
mi -X- _ O
nang-martsa -X- _ O
, -X- _ O
namroblema -X- _ O
na -X- _ O
mi -X- _ O
ni -X- _ O
Renz -X- _ B-PER
, -X- _ O
akong -X- _ O
bestfriend -X- _ O
, -X- _ O
unsay -X- _ O
among -X- _ O
sul-ubon -X- _ O
sanglit -X- _ O
gusto -X- _ O
namo -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
di -X- _ O
malimtan -X- _ O
ang -X- _ O
labing -X- _ O
una -X- _ O
namong -X- _ O
Pride -X- _ O
. -X- _ O

Daghan -X- _ O
naming -X- _ O
mga -X- _ O
plano -X- _ O
, -X- _ O
gikan -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
mga -X- _ O
see-through -X- _ O
shorts -X- _ O
, -X- _ O
tank -X- _ O
tops -X- _ O
, -X- _ O
ug -X- _ O
uban -X- _ O
pang -X- _ O
mga -X- _ O
beyga -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
outfit -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
nakit-an -X- _ O
namo -X- _ O
online -X- _ O
apan -X- _ O
way -X- _ O
bisan -X- _ O
usa -X- _ O
ang -X- _ O
napatahi -X- _ O
tungod -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
ka-busy -X- _ O
. -X- _ O

Wa -X- _ O
gyud -X- _ O
mi -X- _ O
alamag -X- _ O
unsay -X- _ O
mahitabo -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
usa -X- _ O
ka -X- _ O
Pride -X- _ O
Parade -X- _ O
, -X- _ O
ang -X- _ O
anaa -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
among -X- _ O
mga -X- _ O
hunahuna -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
daghang -X- _ O
mga -X- _ O
parehas -X- _ O
namo -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
miyembro -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
LBGT -X- _ B-ORG
( -X- _ I-ORG
Lesbians -X- _ I-ORG
, -X- _ I-ORG
Gays -X- _ I-ORG
, -X- _ I-ORG
Bisexuals -X- _ I-ORG
and -X- _ I-ORG
Transgender -X- _ I-ORG
) -X- _ I-ORG
community -X- _ O
ang -X- _ O
mangapil -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
maong -X- _ O
kalihukan -X- _ O
uban -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
mga -X- _ O
daghang -X- _ O
lami -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
you -X- _ O
know -X- _ O
na -X- _ O
. -X- _ O

Sa -X- _ O
amoa’ng -X- _ O
hunahuna -X- _ O
, -X- _ O
su­nod -X- _ O
nalang -X- _ O
mis -X- _ O
panon -X- _ O
kay -X- _ O
di -X- _ O
man -X- _ O
mi -X- _ O
kahibaw -X- _ O
mo-Ininsik -X- _ O
. -X- _ O

Mas -X- _ O
engrande -X- _ O
ang -X- _ O
selebrasyon -X- _ O
ning -X- _ O
tuiga -X- _ O
tungod -X- _ O
kay -X- _ O
gawas -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
ika-15 -X- _ O
ka -X- _ O
tuig -X- _ O
na -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
gihimo -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
Taipei -X- _ B-LOC
ang -X- _ O
parada -X- _ O
, -X- _ O
niadtong -X- _ O
Mayo -X- _ O
24 -X- _ O
, -X- _ O
ang -X- _ O
Council -X- _ B-ORG
of -X- _ I-ORG
Grand -X- _ I-ORG
Justices -X- _ I-ORG
sa -X- _ O
maong -X- _ O
nasud -X- _ O
mi-anunsyo -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
ilang -X- _ O
interpretasyon -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
Civil -X- _ O
Code -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
ilang -X- _ O
konstitusyon -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
di -X- _ O
maki-angayon -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
hikawan -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
katungod -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
pagpakasal -X- _ O
ang -X- _ O
mga -X- _ O
same-sex -X- _ O
couples -X- _ O
, -X- _ O
pasabot -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
uyon -X- _ O
sila -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
same-sex -X- _ O
marriage -X- _ O
ug -X- _ O
niawhag -X- _ O
kini -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
mga -X- _ O
magbabalaod -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
usbon -X- _ O
ang -X- _ O
ilang -X- _ O
Civil -X- _ O
Code -X- _ O
sud -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
duha -X- _ O
ka -X- _ O
tuig -X- _ O
ron -X- _ O
mapatuman -X- _ O
ang -X- _ O
maong -X- _ O
tinguha -X- _ O
. -X- _ O

Sumala -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
Taipei -X- _ B-ORG
Times -X- _ I-ORG
nga -X- _ O
record-breaking -X- _ O
ang -X- _ O
123,000 -X- _ O
ka -X- _ O
partisipante -X- _ O
ningsalmot -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
parade -X- _ O
niadtong -X- _ O
Oktubre -X- _ O
28 -X- _ O
. -X- _ O

Sa -X- _ O
di -X- _ O
pa -X- _ O
nako -X- _ O
isaysay -X- _ O
akong -X- _ O
kasinatian -X- _ O
, -X- _ O
gusto -X- _ O
kong -X- _ O
inyong -X- _ O
masabtan -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
kining -X- _ O
artikulo -X- _ O
, -X- _ O
di -X- _ O
ni -X- _ O
binastos -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
kon -X- _ O
unsay -X- _ O
inyong -X- _ O
mga -X- _ O
tinuhu-an -X- _ O
. -X- _ O

Makapangutana -X- _ O
siguro -X- _ O
mo -X- _ O
kon -X- _ O
unsay -X- _ O
sinugdanan -X- _ O
nganong -X- _ O
halos -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
tanang -X- _ O
mga -X- _ O
dagkong -X- _ O
dakbayan -X- _ O
ug -X- _ O
mga -X- _ O
dapit -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
kalibutan -X- _ O
, -X- _ O
magsaulog -X- _ O
ug -X- _ O
Pride -X- _ O
Parade -X- _ O
matag -X- _ O
tuig -X- _ O
. -X- _ O

Maka-ana -X- _ O
siguro -X- _ O
mo -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
wala -X- _ O
ra -X- _ O
moy -X- _ O
problema -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
presensya -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
mga -X- _ O
mahuyang -X- _ O
ninyo -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
mga -X- _ O
igsuon -X- _ O
, -X- _ O
higala -X- _ O
, -X- _ O
classmate -X- _ O
, -X- _ O
paryente -X- _ O
, -X- _ O
kaila -X- _ O
ug -X- _ O
uban -X- _ O
pa -X- _ O
apan -X- _ O
ang -X- _ O
wa -X- _ O
ninyo -X- _ O
mahibaw-i -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
matag -X- _ O
minuto -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
pagtuyok -X- _ O
ning -X- _ O
kalibutana -X- _ O
, -X- _ O
adunay -X- _ O
usa -X- _ O
ka -X- _ O
miyembro -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
LGBT -X- _ B-ORG
nga -X- _ O
giabuso -X- _ O
, -X- _ O
gipasakitan -X- _ O
ug -X- _ O
gitamaktamakan -X- _ O
ang -X- _ O
tawhanong -X- _ O
katungod -X- _ O
. -X- _ O

Usa -X- _ O
ka -X- _ O
gabii -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
ikaduhang -X- _ O
higayon -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
pagbisita -X- _ O
nako -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
nasud -X- _ O
niadtong -X- _ O
Disyembre -X- _ O
2016 -X- _ O
, -X- _ O
nahimamat -X- _ O
ko -X- _ O
og -X- _ O
grupo -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
mga -X- _ O
batan-on -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
akong -X- _ O
abi -X- _ O
kog -X- _ O
namaligya -X- _ O
ug -X- _ O
pagkaon -X- _ O
gawas -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
night -X- _ O
market -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
Songshan -X- _ B-LOC
District -X- _ I-LOC
. -X- _ O

Naggunit -X- _ O
sila -X- _ O
og -X- _ O
mga -X- _ O
placards -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
inisik -X- _ O
, -X- _ O
naninggit -X- _ O
ug -X- _ O
Ininsik -X- _ O
( -X- _ O
murag -X- _ O
namaligya -X- _ O
ug -X- _ O
sud-an -X- _ O
) -X- _ O
ug -X- _ O
usa -X- _ O
nila -X- _ O
niwara-wara -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
rainbow -X- _ O
flag -X- _ O
, -X- _ O
simbolo -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
LGBT -X- _ O
community -X- _ O
. -X- _ O

Nakuryuso -X- _ O
ko -X- _ O
unsay -X- _ O
ilang -X- _ O
gibuhat -X- _ O
maong -X- _ O
nakig-istor­yahanay -X- _ O
ko -X- _ O
nila -X- _ O
kung -X- _ O
unsay -X- _ O
ilang -X- _ O
giprotestaan -X- _ O
ug -X- _ O
kini -X- _ O
nagkanayon -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
nipadayag -X- _ O
lang -X- _ O
sila -X- _ O
ug -X- _ O
pagsuporta -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
same-sex -X- _ O
marriage -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
ilang -X- _ O
nasud -X- _ O
. -X- _ O

Pipila -X- _ O
ka -X- _ O
minutos -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
pakigplastikan -X- _ O
ug -X- _ O
chika -X- _ O
, -X- _ O
nangutana -X- _ O
kos -X- _ O
akong -X- _ O
katabi -X- _ O
kon -X- _ O
usa -X- _ O
siya -X- _ O
ka -X- _ O
mahuyang -X- _ O
. -X- _ O

Didto -X- _ O
ko -X- _ O
nibilib -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
akong -X- _ O
gika-istorya -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
bisan -X- _ O
di -X- _ O
siya -X- _ O
bayot -X- _ O
apan -X- _ O
nisuporta -X- _ O
siya -X- _ O
tungod -X- _ O
ug -X- _ O
alang -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
iyang -X- _ O
mga -X- _ O
higala -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
miyembro -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
LGBT -X- _ B-ORG
. -X- _ O

Tungod -X- _ O
niadto -X- _ O
, -X- _ O
nakadisider -X- _ O
ko -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
mosalmot -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
Pride -X- _ O
ning -X- _ O
tuiga -X- _ O
. -X- _ O

Daghang -X- _ O
mga -X- _ O
posibleng -X- _ O
mahitabo -X- _ O
ug -X- _ O
masinati -X- _ O
nimu -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
parade -X- _ O
: -X- _ O

Nangasaag -X- _ O
ming -X- _ O
Renz -X- _ B-PER
ug -X- _ O
akong -X- _ O
kauban -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
buhat -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
si -X- _ O
Chona -X- _ B-PER
paingon -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
venue. -X- _ O
Wa -X- _ O
sab -X- _ O
mi -X- _ O
nagkakita -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
akong -X- _ O
Taiwanese -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
higala -X- _ O
kay -X- _ O
nalangay -X- _ O
man -X- _ O
ang -X- _ O
mga -X- _ O
ebay -X- _ O
. -X- _ O

Imagina -X- _ O
, -X- _ O
wa -X- _ O
mi -X- _ O
kahibaw -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
rota -X- _ O
kon -X- _ O
asa -X- _ O
magsugod -X- _ O
ug -X- _ O
asa -X- _ O
mahuman -X- _ O
pero -X- _ O
werpa -X- _ O
gihapon -X- _ O
kon -X- _ O
asa -X- _ O
ang -X- _ O
mga -X- _ O
tawo -X- _ O
, -X- _ O
sunod -X- _ O
lang -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
panon -X- _ O
. -X- _ O

Didto -X- _ O
mi -X- _ O
nakakita -X- _ O
og -X- _ O
mga -X- _ O
lalake -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
nag-cosplay -X- _ O
ug -X- _ O
Smurf -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
dakog -X- _ O
bunal -X- _ O
, -X- _ O
lalake -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
nag-costume -X- _ O
og -X- _ O
anghel -X- _ O
ang -X- _ O
pako -X- _ O
, -X- _ O
korona -X- _ O
ug -X- _ O
iyang -X- _ O
pribadong -X- _ O
parte -X- _ O
igo -X- _ O
lang -X- _ O
gitabunan -X- _ O
ug -X- _ O
gamayng -X- _ O
panapton -X- _ O
, -X- _ O
mga -X- _ O
naggilak -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
mga -X- _ O
gown -X- _ O
, -X- _ O
make -X- _ O
up -X- _ O
, -X- _ O
rainbow -X- _ O
flag -X- _ O
bisa’g-asa -X- _ O
ug -X- _ O
uban -X- _ O
pa. -X- _ O
Wa -X- _ O
kalabaw -X- _ O
among -X- _ O
gisul-ob -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
jockstrap -X- _ O
ni -X- _ O
Renz -X- _ B-PER
. -X- _ O

Pipila -X- _ O
ka -X- _ O
minutos -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
among -X- _ O
pagsige’g -X- _ O
lakaw -X- _ O
, -X- _ O
gipanggutom -X- _ O
mi -X- _ O
. -X- _ O

Nalipong -X- _ O
sab -X- _ O
si -X- _ O
Chona -X- _ B-PER
, -X- _ O
maayo -X- _ O
nalang -X- _ O
nakakita -X- _ O
mi’g -X- _ O
McDonalds -X- _ B-ORG
duol -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
Peace -X- _ B-LOC
Memorial -X- _ I-LOC
Park -X- _ I-LOC
. -X- _ O

Naka-order -X- _ O
nami -X- _ O
ug -X- _ O
pagkaon -X- _ O
apan -X- _ O
wa -X- _ O
mi -X- _ O
lamesa -X- _ O
tungod -X- _ O
kay -X- _ O
puno -X- _ O
kinis -X- _ O
mga -X- _ O
costumer -X- _ O
maong -X- _ O
buwag-buwag -X- _ O
ming -X- _ O
tulo -X- _ O
ug -X- _ O
pangaon -X- _ O
. -X- _ O

Lakip -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
gihatagan -X- _ O
niya -X- _ O
og -X- _ O
importansiya -X- _ O
mao -X- _ O
ang -X- _ O
kabatan-onan -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
malayo -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
sakit -X- _ O
ug -X- _ O
magbiuotan -X- _ O
. -X- _ O

Matod -X- _ O
niya -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
wala -X- _ O
siyay -X- _ O
mahatag -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
gasa -X- _ O
alang -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
tanang -X- _ O
Talisaynon -X- _ O
gawas -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
pag-ampo -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
hatagan -X- _ O
og -X- _ O
kabaskog -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
panglawas -X- _ O
ang -X- _ O
taga -X- _ O
Talisay -X- _ B-LOC
ug -X- _ O
malayo -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
sakit -X- _ O
. -X- _ O

Midugang -X- _ O
siya -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
unta -X- _ O
ang -X- _ O
kabataan -X- _ O
manggiluy-on -X- _ O
ug -X- _ O
dili -X- _ O
probelma -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
ilang -X- _ O
mga -X- _ O
ginikanan -X- _ O
ug -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
katilingban -X- _ O
. -X- _ O

Nagkanayon -X- _ O
si -X- _ O
Gullas -X- _ B-PER
nga -X- _ O
kon -X- _ O
ang -X- _ O
kabataan -X- _ O
adunay -X- _ O
pagtahod -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
ilang -X- _ O
mga -X- _ O
maguwang -X- _ O
, -X- _ O
walay -X- _ O
krimen -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
mahitabo -X- _ O
ug -X- _ O
dili -X- _ O
usab -X- _ O
kini -X- _ O
makahimo -X- _ O
og -X- _ O
salaod -X- _ O
. -X- _ O

Si -X- _ O
Gullas -X- _ B-PER
niingon -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
kinahanglan -X- _ O
usab -X- _ O
ang -X- _ O
taga -X- _ O
Talisay -X- _ B-LOC
motuo -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
pag-ampo -X- _ O
iyang -X- _ O
gihimo -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
sanglitanan -X- _ O
ang -X- _ O
iyang -X- _ O
kaugalingon -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
dihang -X- _ O
nahimo -X- _ O
siyang -X- _ O
gobernador -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
Sugbo -X- _ B-LOC
niadtong -X- _ O
kapin -X- _ O
pa -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
40 -X- _ O
anyos -X- _ O
ang -X- _ O
iyang -X- _ O
pangidaron -X- _ O
na-diagnosed -X- _ O
og -X- _ O
lung -X- _ O
cancer -X- _ O
. -X- _ O

Giingnan -X- _ O
siya -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
iyang -X- _ O
doktor -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
aduna -X- _ O
lang -X- _ O
siyay -X- _ O
tulo -X- _ O
ka -X- _ O
buwan -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
mabuhi -X- _ O
, -X- _ O
apan -X- _ O
tungod -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
hugot -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
pagtuo -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
pag-ampo -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
iyang -X- _ O
pamilya -X- _ O
ug -X- _ O
mga -X- _ O
higala -X- _ O
buhi -X- _ O
pa -X- _ O
siya -X- _ O
hangtod -X- _ O
karon -X- _ O
. -X- _ O

Iyang -X- _ O
gibutyag -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
grabe -X- _ O
ang -X- _ O
iyang -X- _ O
pag-ampo -X- _ O
ngadto -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
Birhen -X- _ B-PER
Maria -X- _ I-PER
patron -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
Talisay -X- _ B-LOC
ug -X- _ O
Sta -X- _ B-PER
Teresa -X- _ I-PER
de -X- _ I-PER
Avila -X- _ I-PER
ug -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
balaang -X- _ O
bata -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
si -X- _ O
Senyor -X- _ B-PER
Sto. -X- _ I-PER
Niño -X- _ I-PER
. -X- _ O

Nidugang -X- _ O
siya -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
mahimo -X- _ O
na -X- _ O
unta -X- _ O
siyang -X- _ O
mohunong -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
pagserbisyo -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
publiko -X- _ O
ug -X- _ O
magpahayay -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
nabiling -X- _ O
panahon -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
iyang -X- _ O
kinabuhi -X- _ O
, -X- _ O
apan -X- _ O
ang -X- _ O
iyang -X- _ O
kaikag -X- _ O
ug -X- _ O
kasasig -X- _ O
nagpadayon -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
pagpangulo -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
katawhan -X- _ O
aron -X- _ O
mapada­yon -X- _ O
ang -X- _ O
iyang -X- _ O
pagserbisyo -X- _ O
ug -X- _ O
debos­yon -X- _ O
. -X- _ O

Kinatibuk-ang -X- _ O
2,809 -X- _ O
ka -X- _ O
mga -X- _ O
pasahero -X- _ O
ang -X- _ O
nalangay -X- _ O
ang -X- _ O
mga -X- _ O
biyahe -X- _ O
gumikan -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
kan­selasyon -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
mga -X- _ O
biyahe -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
kadagatan -X- _ O
. -X- _ O

Ang -X- _ O
ihap -X- _ O
gikan -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
lainlaing -X- _ O
mga -X- _ O
pantalan -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
Sugbo -X- _ B-LOC
sama -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
Hagnaya -X- _ B-LOC
, -X- _ O
San -X- _ I-LOC
Remigio -X- _ I-LOC
; -X- _ O
Polambato -X- _ B-LOC
, -X- _ I-LOC
Bogo -X- _ I-LOC
City -X- _ I-LOC
; -X- _ O
Tabuelan -X- _ B-LOC
; -X- _ O
Bantayan -X- _ B-LOC
; -X- _ O
Danao -X- _ B-LOC
; -X- _ O
Consuelo -X- _ B-LOC
, -X- _ I-LOC
San -X- _ I-LOC
Francisco -X- _ I-LOC
, -X- _ I-LOC
Camotes -X- _ I-LOC
; -X- _ O
siyudad -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
Sugbo -X- _ B-LOC
ug -X- _ O
uban -X- _ O
pa -X- _ O
. -X- _ O

Pasado -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
alas -X- _ O
8 -X- _ O
kagaha­pon -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
buntag -X- _ O
, -X- _ O
nibiyahe -X- _ O
ang -X- _ O
Oceanjet -X- _ B-ORG
gikan -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
Cebu -X- _ B-LOC
padulong -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
Ormoc -X- _ B-LOC
City -X- _ I-LOC
apan -X- _ O
gisugat -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
dagkong -X- _ O
mga -X- _ O
bawod -X- _ O
. -X- _ O

Tungod -X- _ O
niini -X- _ O
, -X- _ O
nibalik -X- _ O
kini -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
dakbayan -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
Sugbo -X- _ B-LOC
. -X- _ O

Matod -X- _ O
ni -X- _ O
Lowangco -X- _ B-PER
nga -X- _ O
siya -X- _ O
ug -X- _ O
kaubanan -X- _ O
nangahadlok -X- _ O
og -X- _ O
maayo -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
biyahe -X- _ O
. -X- _ O

Apan -X- _ O
tungod -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
Bagyong -X- _ B-OTHER
Vinta -X- _ I-OTHER
, -X- _ O
nalangay -X- _ O
ang -X- _ O
iyang -X- _ O
pag-uli -X- _ O
, -X- _ O
apil -X- _ O
na -X- _ O
ang -X- _ O
liboan -X- _ O
ka -X- _ O
mga -X- _ O
pasahero -X- _ O
. -X- _ O

Tungod -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
kadagko -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
mga -X- _ O
bawod -X- _ O
, -X- _ O
gihakop -X- _ O
sila -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
kahadlok -X- _ O
, -X- _ O
apan -X- _ O
nagpalasamat -X- _ O
sila -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
nibalik -X- _ O
ang -X- _ O
Oceanjet -X- _ B-ORG
sa -X- _ O
agi -X- _ O
. -X- _ O

Samtang -X- _ O
30 -X- _ O
ka -X- _ O
flights -X- _ O
ang -X- _ O
gipangkansilar -X- _ O
usab -X- _ O
ang -X- _ O
mga -X- _ O
biyahe -X- _ O
gikan -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
Mactan -X- _ B-LOC
Cebu -X- _ I-LOC
International -X- _ I-LOC
Airport -X- _ I-LOC
. -X- _ O

Kini -X- _ O
subay -X- _ O
usab -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
gikanselar -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
biyahe -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
mga -X- _ O
sakyanan -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
kadagatan -X- _ O
paingon -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
maong -X- _ O
mga -X- _ O
dapit -X- _ O
, -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
habagatang -X- _ O
bahin -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
Sugbo -X- _ B-LOC
. -X- _ O

Sigun -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
CSBT -X- _ B-ORG
, -X- _ O
mas -X- _ O
maayong -X- _ O
magpabilin -X- _ O
sila -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
terminal -X- _ O
inay -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
magtapok -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
pantalan -X- _ O
ug -X- _ O
didto -X- _ O
mangatanggong -X- _ O
. -X- _ O

Sugod -X- _ O
niadtong -X- _ O
Huwebes -X- _ O
, -X- _ O
wa -X- _ O
nay -X- _ O
bus -X- _ O
paingon -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
Dumaguete -X- _ B-LOC
, -X- _ O
Bacolod -X- _ B-LOC
ug -X- _ O
Zamboanga -X- _ B-LOC
City -X- _ I-LOC
nga -X- _ O
gitugotan -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
makabiya -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
CSBT -X- _ B-ORG
. -X- _ O

Ang -X- _ O
maong -X- _ O
mga -X- _ O
bus -X- _ O
ikarga -X- _ O
og -X- _ O
barge -X- _ O
paingon -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
ilang -X- _ O
mga -X- _ O
destinasyon -X- _ O
apan -X- _ O
tungod -X- _ O
kay -X- _ O
kanselado -X- _ O
ang -X- _ O
biyahe -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
mga -X- _ O
sakyanan -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
kadagatan -X- _ O
, -X- _ O
dili -X- _ O
ra -X- _ O
gihapon -X- _ O
sila -X- _ O
makatabok -X- _ O
. -X- _ O

Ang -X- _ O
bagyong -X- _ O
Vinta -X- _ I-OTHER
kay -X- _ O
nagkahinay -X- _ O
nahimo -X- _ O
nang -X- _ O
tro­pical -X- _ O
depression -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
nagdala -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
hangin -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
may -X- _ O
gikusgon -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
60 -X- _ O
ka -X- _ O
kilometros -X- _ O
matag -X- _ O
takna -X- _ O
duol -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
iyang -X- _ O
sentro -X- _ O
ug -X- _ O
pag-unos -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
moabot -X- _ O
ngadto -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
90 -X- _ O
ka -X- _ O
kilometros -X- _ O
matag -X- _ O
oras -X- _ O
samtang -X- _ O
nag-irog -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
direksyon -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
kasadpan -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
gikusgon -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
20 -X- _ O
ka -X- _ O
kilometros -X- _ O
matag -X- _ O
oras -X- _ O
. -X- _ O

Kini -X- _ O
nakatugpa -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
yuta -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
Cateel -X- _ B-LOC
, -X- _ I-LOC
Davao -X- _ I-LOC
Oriental -X- _ I-LOC
ala -X- _ O
1:45 -X- _ O
kagahapon -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
kaadlawon -X- _ O
ug -X- _ O
naa -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
Zamboanga -X- _ B-LOC
Del -X- _ I-LOC
Sur -X- _ I-LOC
sa -X- _ O
pagkutlo -X- _ O
ning -X- _ O
balita -X- _ O
. -X- _ O

Apan -X- _ O
gialerto -X- _ O
nila -X- _ O
ang -X- _ O
mga -X- _ O
local -X- _ O
government -X- _ O
unit -X- _ O
ug -X- _ O
mga -X- _ O
molupyo -X- _ O
labi -X- _ O
na -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
mga -X- _ O
dapit -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
delikado -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
pagdahili -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
yuta -X- _ O
ug -X- _ O
flashfloods -X- _ O
. -X- _ O

Si -X- _ O
Tribunalo -X- _ B-PER
nidasig -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
mga -X- _ O
LGU -X- _ B-ORG
ug -X- _ O
local -X- _ O
DRRMO -X- _ B-ORG
nga -X- _ O
gamiton -X- _ O
ang -X- _ O
mga -X- _ O
mapa -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
giapud-apod -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
nag-ila -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
mga -X- _ O
dapit -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
peligro -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
kalamidad -X- _ O
. -X- _ O

Sa -X- _ O
Liloan -X- _ B-LOC
Port -X- _ I-LOC
sa -X- _ O
lungsod -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
Santander -X- _ B-LOC
, -X- _ O
dunay -X- _ O
gibanabanang -X- _ O
500 -X- _ O
ka -X- _ O
mga -X- _ O
pasahero -X- _ O
ang -X- _ O
nangatanggong -X- _ O
ug -X- _ O
gihatagan -X- _ O
og -X- _ O
food -X- _ O
packs -X- _ O
. -X- _ O

Sa -X- _ O
lungsod -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
Oslob -X- _ B-LOC
, -X- _ O
dunay -X- _ O
46 -X- _ O
ka -X- _ O
lokal -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
mga -X- _ O
turista -X- _ O
, -X- _ O
unom -X- _ O
niini -X- _ O
mga -X- _ O
bata -X- _ O
ug -X- _ O
walo -X- _ O
ka -X- _ O
langyaw -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
mga -X- _ O
turista -X- _ O
, -X- _ O
usa -X- _ O
bata -X- _ O
ang -X- _ O
wa -X- _ O
makatabok -X- _ O
gikan -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
isla -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
Sumilon -X- _ B-LOC
paingon -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
mainland -X- _ O
gumikan -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
bagyo -X- _ O
. -X- _ O

Masinati -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
mga -X- _ O
konsumedor -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
Metropolitan -X- _ B-ORG
Cebu -X- _ I-ORG
Water -X- _ I-ORG
District -X- _ I-ORG
( -X- _ I-ORG
MCWD -X- _ I-ORG
) -X- _ I-ORG
ang -X- _ O
10 -X- _ O
ka -X- _ O
oras -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
way -X- _ O
supply -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
tubig -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
pipila -X- _ O
ka -X- _ O
mga -X- _ O
barangay -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
mga -X- _ O
dakbayan -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
Sugbo -X- _ B-LOC
ug -X- _ O
Talisay -X- _ B-LOC
sugod -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
gabii -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
Disyembre -X- _ O
28 -X- _ O
. -X- _ O

Si -X- _ O
Kara -X- _ B-PER
nipasabot -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
kinahanglan -X- _ O
isibog -X- _ O
nila -X- _ O
ang -X- _ O
dagko -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
mga -X- _ O
tubo -X- _ O
, -X- _ O
putlon -X- _ O
ug -X- _ O
isumpay -X- _ O
og -X- _ O
balik -X- _ O
aron -X- _ O
dili -X- _ O
mahugawan -X- _ O
ang -X- _ O
supply -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
tubig -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
mosubay -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
maong -X- _ O
mga -X- _ O
tubo -X- _ O
. -X- _ O

Siya -X- _ O
nidugang -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
dili -X- _ O
sila -X- _ O
dihadiha -X- _ O
makabalhin -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
mga -X- _ O
tubo -X- _ O
kay -X- _ O
mag-agad -X- _ O
sila -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
contractor -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
DPWH -X- _ B-ORG
kon -X- _ O
mahuman -X- _ O
na -X- _ O
og -X- _ O
kubkob -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
yuta -X- _ O
. -X- _ O

Si -X- _ O
Kara -X- _ B-PER
nangayo -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
pagsabot -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
mga -X- _ O
konsumedor -X- _ O
bahin -X- _ O
niini -X- _ O
. -X- _ O

Bisan -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
mga -X- _ O
pagsulay -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
nasinati -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
nasod -X- _ O
sama -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
kalamidad -X- _ O
ug -X- _ O
kalisod -X- _ O
, -X- _ O
anaa -X- _ O
kanunay -X- _ O
ang -X- _ O
Ginuo -X- _ B-PER
, -X- _ O
pagpahinumdom -X- _ O
ni -X- _ O
Cebu -X- _ B-LOC
Archbishop -X- _ O
Jose -X- _ B-PER
Palma -X- _ I-PER
. -X- _ O

Sa -X- _ O
iyang -X- _ O
mensahe -X- _ O
alang -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
Pasko -X- _ B-OTHER
, -X- _ O
ang -X- _ O
arsobispo -X- _ O
namulong -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
nasuwayan -X- _ O
ang -X- _ O
kahiusahan -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
nasod -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
mga -X- _ O
panghitabo -X- _ O
sama -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
pag-atake -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
mga -X- _ O
ISIS-Maute -X- _ B-ORG
Group -X- _ I-ORG
sa -X- _ O
siyudad -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
Marawi -X- _ B-LOC
nga -X- _ O
nikutlo -X- _ O
og -X- _ O
daghang -X- _ O
kinabuhi -X- _ O
. -X- _ O

Ang -X- _ O
arsobispo -X- _ O
namahayag -X- _ O
ang -X- _ O
Pasko -X- _ B-OTHER
nagpahinumdom -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
dihang -X- _ O
gihimugso -X- _ O
si -X- _ O
Hesukristo -X- _ B-PER
diin -X- _ O
way -X- _ O
pamilya -X- _ O
ang -X- _ O
nidawat -X- _ O
nila -X- _ O
ni -X- _ O
Jose -X- _ B-PER
ug -X- _ O
Maria -X- _ B-PER
aron -X- _ O
didto -X- _ O
manganak -X- _ O
ang -X- _ O
inahan -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
Ginuo -X- _ B-PER
. -X- _ O

Siya -X- _ O
nidasig -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
mga -X- _ O
tawo -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
dawaton -X- _ O
si -X- _ O
Hesus -X- _ B-PER
diha -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
ilang -X- _ O
kasingkasing -X- _ O
, -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
ilang -X- _ O
pamilya -X- _ O
ug -X- _ O
komunidad -X- _ O
. -X- _ O

Suma -X- _ O
pa -X- _ O
niini -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
nasayod -X- _ O
ang -X- _ O
mga -X- _ O
tawo -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
kon -X- _ O
ang -X- _ O
Ginuo -X- _ B-PER
anaa -X- _ O
nila -X- _ O
, -X- _ O
dunay -X- _ O
kausaban -X- _ O
alang -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
kaayo -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
moepekto -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
gugma -X- _ O
, -X- _ O
kaluoy -X- _ O
ug -X- _ O
kapasayloan -X- _ O
. -X- _ O

Si -X- _ O
Palma -X- _ B-PER
nidugang -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
sama -X- _ O
ni -X- _ O
Hesus -X- _ B-PER
nga -X- _ O
gasa -X- _ O
gikan -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
Ginuo -X- _ B-PER
, -X- _ O
unta -X- _ O
ang -X- _ O
mga -X- _ O
tawo -X- _ O
mahimo -X- _ O
usab -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
instrumento -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
paglaom -X- _ O
ug -X- _ O
kamaya -X- _ O
ug -X- _ O
gasa -X- _ O
ngadto -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
uban -X- _ O
. -X- _ O

Si -X- _ O
Ahmed -X- _ B-PER
Cuizon -X- _ I-PER
, -X- _ O
director -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
LTFRB -X- _ B-ORG
7 -X- _ I-ORG
, -X- _ O
nibutyag -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
moabot -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
66 -X- _ O
ka -X- _ O
special -X- _ O
permits -X- _ O
ang -X- _ O
giisyu -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
mga -X- _ O
bus -X- _ O
samtang -X- _ O
24 -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
mga -X- _ O
minibus -X- _ O
. -X- _ O

Ang -X- _ O
special -X- _ O
permits -X- _ O
gikinahanglan -X- _ O
aron -X- _ O
makalabyog -X- _ O
ang -X- _ O
publiko -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
mga -X- _ O
sakyanan -X- _ O
gawas -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
gitugot -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
rota -X- _ O
alang -X- _ O
niini -X- _ O
, -X- _ O
aron -X- _ O
makahakot -X- _ O
og -X- _ O
mga -X- _ O
pasahero -X- _ O
ug -X- _ O
dili -X- _ O
dakpon -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
Land -X- _ B-ORG
Transportation -X- _ I-ORG
Office -X- _ I-ORG
. -X- _ O

Matod -X- _ O
niya -X- _ O
lima -X- _ O
ka -X- _ O
operators -X- _ O
ang -X- _ O
nag-apply -X- _ O
aron -X- _ O
maisyuhan -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
special -X- _ O
permits -X- _ O
. -X- _ O

Kini -X- _ O
naglakip -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
Vallacar -X- _ B-ORG
Transit -X- _ I-ORG
, -X- _ I-ORG
Inc -X- _ I-ORG
, -X- _ O
ang -X- _ O
kompaniya -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
nagpadagan -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
Ceres -X- _ B-ORG
buses -X- _ O
; -X- _ O
Sugbo -X- _ B-ORG
Transit -X- _ I-ORG
Express -X- _ I-ORG
; -X- _ O
Island -X- _ B-ORG
Autobus -X- _ I-ORG
Transit -X- _ I-ORG
Corp. -X- _ I-ORG
; -X- _ O
ug -X- _ O
Metro -X- _ B-ORG
Cebu -X- _ I-ORG
Autobus -X- _ I-ORG
Corp -X- _ I-ORG
. -X- _ I-ORG

Kasagaran -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
mga -X- _ O
special -X- _ O
permit -X- _ O
balido -X- _ O
sud -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
12 -X- _ O
ka -X- _ O
adlaw -X- _ O
kun -X- _ O
sugod -X- _ O
karong -X- _ O
adlawa -X- _ O
hangtod -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
Enero -X- _ O
3 -X- _ O
duna -X- _ O
usab -X- _ O
unom -X- _ O
ka -X- _ O
adlaw -X- _ O
kun -X- _ O
kutob -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
Disyembre -X- _ O
28 -X- _ O
. -X- _ O

Kinatibuk-an -X- _ O
, -X- _ O
55 -X- _ O
ka -X- _ O
special -X- _ O
permits -X- _ O
ang -X- _ O
giisyu -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
LTFRB -X- _ B-ORG
7 -X- _ I-ORG
alang -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
mga -X- _ O
bus -X- _ O
ug -X- _ O
24 -X- _ O
ka -X- _ O
special -X- _ O
permits -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
mga -X- _ O
minibus -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
Vallacar -X- _ B-ORG
, -X- _ O
6 -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
Sugbo -X- _ B-ORG
Transit -X- _ I-ORG
Express -X- _ I-ORG
, -X- _ O
1 -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
Mabel -X- _ B-ORG
Montenegro -X- _ I-ORG
, -X- _ O
1 -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
Island -X- _ B-ORG
Autobus -X- _ I-ORG
ug -X- _ O
4 -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
Metro -X- _ B-ORG
Cebu -X- _ I-ORG
Autobus -X- _ I-ORG
Corp. -X- _ I-ORG
( -X- _ I-ORG
SCG -X- _ I-ORG
) -X- _ I-ORG

Si -X- _ O
Osmeña -X- _ B-PER
namahayag -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
bisan -X- _ O
ang -X- _ O
mga -X- _ O
kabos -X- _ O
kinahanglan -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
mobayad -X- _ O
og -X- _ O
buhis -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
ilang -X- _ O
kinitian -X- _ O
bisan -X- _ O
kon -X- _ O
gamay -X- _ O
ra -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
kantidad -X- _ O
. -X- _ O

Matod -X- _ O
ni -X- _ O
Osmeña -X- _ B-PER
kinsa -X- _ O
nimando -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
tag -X- _ O
P5 -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
bayranan -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
mga -X- _ O
drayber -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
motorsiklo -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
makalapas -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
lagda -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
trapiko -X- _ O
pinaagi -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
adjudication -X- _ O
. -X- _ O

Gihulagway -X- _ O
niya -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
di -X- _ O
maayo -X- _ O
ang -X- _ O
pipila -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
mga -X- _ O
provision -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
nasukip -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
Train -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
mo-epekto -X- _ O
sugod -X- _ O
tuig -X- _ O
2018 -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
iyang -X- _ O
gihulagway -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
makadaot -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
nasod -X- _ O
. -X- _ O

Subay -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
Train -X- _ O
, -X- _ O
gawas -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
way -X- _ O
buhis -X- _ O
ang -X- _ O
nagsweldo -X- _ O
og -X- _ O
P250,000 -X- _ O
matag -X- _ O
tuig -X- _ O
, -X- _ O
mosaka -X- _ O
ang -X- _ O
presyo -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
gasolina -X- _ O
ug -X- _ O
krudo -X- _ O
, -X- _ O
dugang -X- _ O
buhis -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
mga -X- _ O
sakyanan -X- _ O
, -X- _ O
coal -X- _ O
ug -X- _ O
sugar -X- _ O
sweetened -X- _ O
drinks -X- _ O
sama -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
mga -X- _ O
soft -X- _ O
drinks -X- _ O
ug -X- _ O
uban -X- _ O
pa -X- _ O
. -X- _ O

Ang -X- _ O
buhis -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
makolekta -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
Train -X- _ O
maoy -X- _ O
igasto -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
P8 -X- _ O
trilyones -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
proyekto -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
imprastraktura -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
kasamtangang -X- _ O
administrasyon -X- _ O
. -X- _ O

Sugod -X- _ O
tuig -X- _ O
2018 -X- _ O
, -X- _ O
ang -X- _ O
produkto -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
diesel -X- _ O
buhisan -X- _ O
og -X- _ O
P2.50 -X- _ O
matag -X- _ O
litro -X- _ O
hangtod -X- _ O
mosaka -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
P4.50 -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
tuig -X- _ O
2019 -X- _ O
ug -X- _ O
mahimong -X- _ O
P6 -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
tuig -X- _ O
2020 -X- _ O
. -X- _ O

Ang -X- _ O
Liquified -X- _ O
Petroleum -X- _ O
Gas -X- _ O
( -X- _ O
LPG -X- _ O
) -X- _ O
buhisan -X- _ O
og -X- _ O
P1 -X- _ O
matag -X- _ O
kilo -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
tuig -X- _ O
2018 -X- _ O
, -X- _ O
P2 -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
2019 -X- _ O
ug -X- _ O
P3 -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
2020 -X- _ O
. -X- _ O

Ang -X- _ O
gobyerno -X- _ O
mokolekta -X- _ O
og -X- _ O
P7 -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
buhis -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
matag -X- _ O
litro -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
gasolina -X- _ O
, -X- _ O
P9 -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
tuig -X- _ O
2019 -X- _ O
ug -X- _ O
P10 -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
2020. -X- _ O
( -X- _ O
PAC -X- _ O
) -X- _ O

Hatagan -X- _ O
og -X- _ O
prayoridad -X- _ O
ni -X- _ O
Mayor -X- _ O
Tomas -X- _ B-PER
Osmeña -X- _ I-PER
sa -X- _ O
tuig -X- _ O
2018 -X- _ O
ang -X- _ O
pagtukod -X- _ O
og -X- _ O
dormitory -X- _ O
para -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
100 -X- _ O
ka -X- _ O
mga -X- _ O
single -X- _ O
mother -X- _ O
kinsa -X- _ O
nagtrabaho -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
business -X- _ O
process -X- _ O
outsourcing -X- _ O
( -X- _ O
BPO -X- _ O
) -X- _ O
. -X- _ O

Matod -X- _ O
ni -X- _ O
Osmeña -X- _ B-PER
nga -X- _ O
daghan -X- _ O
siya -X- _ O
og -X- _ O
ipatuman -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
proyekto -X- _ O
sunod -X- _ O
tuig -X- _ O
apan -X- _ O
kini -X- _ O
maoy -X- _ O
iyang -X- _ O
gihatagan -X- _ O
og -X- _ O
gibug-aton -X- _ O
sanglit -X- _ O
iyang -X- _ O
naobserbahan -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
way -X- _ O
maayong -X- _ O
kaugmaon -X- _ O
ang -X- _ O
mga -X- _ O
single -X- _ O
mother -X- _ O
. -X- _ O

Gipasabot -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
mayor -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
dakong -X- _ O
hagit -X- _ O
alang -X- _ O
kaniya -X- _ O
sanglit -X- _ O
ang -X- _ O
mga -X- _ O
inahan -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
maoy -X- _ O
nagmatuto -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
ilang -X- _ O
mga -X- _ O
anak -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
way -X- _ O
amahan -X- _ O
di -X- _ O
maglisod -X- _ O
og -X- _ O
trabaho -X- _ O
. -X- _ O

Ang -X- _ O
dormitory -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
tukoron -X- _ O
ni -X- _ O
Osmeña -X- _ B-PER
makaatiman -X- _ O
og -X- _ O
100 -X- _ O
ka -X- _ O
single -X- _ O
mother -X- _ O
diin -X- _ O
tuyo -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
dormitory -X- _ O
mao -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
usahon -X- _ O
ang -X- _ O
mga -X- _ O
bata -X- _ O
, -X- _ O
lainon -X- _ O
ang -X- _ O
lalaki -X- _ O
ug -X- _ O
babaye -X- _ O
apan -X- _ O
usa -X- _ O
ra -X- _ O
ang -X- _ O
ilang -X- _ O
kusina -X- _ O
, -X- _ O
adunay -X- _ O
playground -X- _ O
ug -X- _ O
ubang -X- _ O
pasilidad -X- _ O
. -X- _ O

Kon -X- _ O
makita -X- _ O
niya -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
maayo -X- _ O
ang -X- _ O
lakat -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
programa -X- _ O
, -X- _ O
modugang -X- _ O
og -X- _ O
laing -X- _ O
mga -X- _ O
dormitoryo -X- _ O
si -X- _ O
Osmeña -X- _ B-PER
aron -X- _ O
maserbisyohan -X- _ O
niya -X- _ O
ang -X- _ O
daghang -X- _ O
mga -X- _ O
single -X- _ O
mother -X- _ O
. -X- _ O

Tuyo -X- _ O
ni -X- _ O
Osmeña -X- _ B-PER
nga -X- _ O
samtang -X- _ O
nagtrabaho -X- _ O
ang -X- _ O
ilang -X- _ O
mga -X- _ O
inahan -X- _ O
, -X- _ O
adunay -X- _ O
mag-alima -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
ilang -X- _ O
mga -X- _ O
anak -X- _ O
ug -X- _ O
di -X- _ O
na -X- _ O
sila -X- _ O
angay -X- _ O
mabalaka -X- _ O
. -X- _ O

Ang -X- _ O
biktima -X- _ O
giila -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
si -X- _ O
Mark -X- _ B-PER
Neil -X- _ I-PER
Mondejar -X- _ I-PER
, -X- _ O
25 -X- _ O
anyos -X- _ O
ug -X- _ O
residente -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
Cogon -X- _ B-LOC
, -X- _ I-LOC
A -X- _ I-LOC
Lopez -X- _ I-LOC
St. -X- _ I-LOC
, -X- _ O
dakbayan -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
Sugbo -X- _ B-LOC
. -X- _ O

Si -X- _ O
Mondejar -X- _ B-PER
nagbaklay -X- _ O
daplin -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
dan -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
naasoyng -X- _ O
lugar -X- _ O
kuyog -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
iyang -X- _ O
higala -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
si -X- _ O
Jay -X- _ B-PER
Boy -X- _ I-PER
Quijano -X- _ I-PER
human -X- _ O
kini -X- _ O
sila -X- _ O
makigtagay -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
parehong -X- _ O
dapit -X- _ O
. -X- _ O

Sa -X- _ O
dihang -X- _ O
ang -X- _ O
duha -X- _ O
ka -X- _ O
wala -X- _ O
mailhing -X- _ O
mga -X- _ O
lalaki -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
nagsakay -X- _ O
og -X- _ O
motor -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
giilang -X- _ O
mga -X- _ O
suspek -X- _ O
mitungha -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
atubangan -X- _ O
nila -X- _ O
ni -X- _ O
Mondejar -X- _ B-PER
ug -X- _ O
Quijano -X- _ B-PER
. -X- _ O

Ang -X- _ O
biktima -X- _ O
naigo -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
tuo -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
bahin -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
iyang -X- _ O
bukton -X- _ O
ug -X- _ O
kini -X- _ O
nakaaghat -X- _ O
kaniya -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
pag-ikyas -X- _ O
samtang -X- _ O
ang -X- _ O
mga -X- _ O
suspek -X- _ O
nagdali-dali -X- _ O
og -X- _ O
pag-ikyas -X- _ O
paingon -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
laing -X- _ O
direksyon -X- _ O
. -X- _ O

Giparesentar -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
PRO -X- _ B-ORG
7 -X- _ I-ORG
ang -X- _ O
ilang -X- _ O
pagpangandam -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
siguridad -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
simbahan -X- _ O
sama -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
pag -X- _ O
sira -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
karsada -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
Osmena -X- _ B-LOC
boulevard -X- _ O
gikan -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
tanang -X- _ O
sakyanan -X- _ O
. -X- _ O

Usa -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
ilang -X- _ O
plano -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
didto -X- _ O
ibutang -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
dan -X- _ O
Lapu-lapu -X- _ B-LOC
ang -X- _ O
mga -X- _ O
manindahay -X- _ O
ug -X- _ O
imahen -X- _ O
aron -X- _ O
di -X- _ O
sila -X- _ O
makabalda -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
mga -X- _ O
tawo -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
mosud -X- _ O
ug -X- _ O
mogawas -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
simbahan -X- _ O
. -X- _ O

Aron -X- _ O
mahimong -X- _ O
hapsay -X- _ O
ang -X- _ O
pagsud -X- _ O
ug -X- _ O
paggawas -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
mga -X- _ O
debotong -X- _ O
Katoliko -X- _ O
ang -X- _ O
tanang -X- _ O
entrada -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
simbahan -X- _ O
didto -X- _ O
na -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
luyong -X- _ O
bahin -X- _ O
ug -X- _ O
kilid -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
Basilica -X- _ B-LOC
samtang -X- _ O
ang -X- _ O
gawsanan -X- _ O
mao -X- _ O
ang -X- _ O
mga -X- _ O
pultahan -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
nag -X- _ O
atubang -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
Osmena -X- _ B-LOC
Boulevard -X- _ I-LOC
. -X- _ O

Gipusil -X- _ O
patay -X- _ O
ang -X- _ O
barangay -X- _ O
tanod -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
iyang -X- _ O
gikaduwag -X- _ O
hantak -X- _ O
human -X- _ O
gisungog -X- _ O
dihang -X- _ O
napildi -X- _ O
. -X- _ O

Nahitabo -X- _ O
ang -X- _ O
insidente -X- _ O
niadtong -X- _ O
Huwebes -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
gabii -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
Barangay -X- _ B-LOC
Tapul -X- _ I-LOC
, -X- _ O
dakbayan -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
Talisay -X- _ B-LOC
, -X- _ I-LOC
Sugbo -X- _ I-LOC
. -X- _ O

Samtang -X- _ O
ang -X- _ O
suspek -X- _ O
mao -X- _ O
si -X- _ O
Robert -X- _ B-PER
Castanares -X- _ I-PER
, -X- _ O
26 -X- _ O
, -X- _ O
ug -X- _ O
pulos -X- _ O
taga -X- _ O
didto -X- _ O
ra -X- _ O
usab -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
maong -X- _ O
lugar -X- _ O
. -X- _ O

Apan -X- _ O
paghiabot -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
kapulisan -X- _ O
nagbuy-od -X- _ O
na -X- _ O
ang -X- _ O
biktima -X- _ O
ug -X- _ O
aduna -X- _ O
nay -X- _ O
samad -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
ulo -X- _ O
ug -X- _ O
bukton -X- _ O
. -X- _ O

Matod -X- _ O
pa -X- _ O
nagsugal -X- _ O
ang -X- _ O
duha -X- _ O
og -X- _ O
hantak -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
dihang -X- _ O
napildi -X- _ O
ang -X- _ O
suspek -X- _ O
gisungog -X- _ O
kini -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
biktima -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
miresulta -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
pagpamusil -X- _ O
. -X- _ O

Ang -X- _ O
suspek -X- _ O
daling -X- _ O
misibat -X- _ O
samtang -X- _ O
nakuha -X- _ O
gikan -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
crime -X- _ O
scene -X- _ O
ang -X- _ O
tulo -X- _ O
ka -X- _ O
kabhang -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
giutohang -X- _ O
kalibre -X- _ O
.45 -X- _ O
. -X- _ O

Kagahapon -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
buntag -X- _ O
ang -X- _ O
suspek -X- _ O
bulontaryong -X- _ O
mitahan -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
iyang -X- _ O
kaugalingon -X- _ O
ngadto -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
kapulisan -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
Talisay -X- _ B-LOC
inubanan -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
laing -X- _ O
pulis -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
taga -X- _ O
didto -X- _ O
ra -X- _ O
usab -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
si -X- _ O
P01 -X- _ O
Robert -X- _ B-PER
Sabequil -X- _ I-PER
ug -X- _ O
ni -X- _ O
Konsehal -X- _ O
Marvin -X- _ B-PER
Lapinid -X- _ I-PER
. -X- _ O

Kagahapon -X- _ O
gihimo -X- _ O
ang -X- _ O
paraffin -X- _ O
test -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
suspek -X- _ O
samtang -X- _ O
gipasakaan -X- _ O
na -X- _ O
kini -X- _ O
kaso -X- _ O
. -X- _ O

Ang -X- _ O
Philippine -X- _ B-ORG
Drug -X- _ I-ORG
Enforcement -X- _ I-ORG
Agency -X- _ I-ORG
( -X- _ I-ORG
PDEA -X- _ I-ORG
) -X- _ I-ORG
8 -X- _ I-ORG
uban -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
mga -X- _ O
gwardiya -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
bilanggoan -X- _ O
ang -X- _ O
mihimo -X- _ O
og -X- _ O
inspeksyon -X- _ O
, -X- _ O
alas -X- _ O
9 -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
gabii -X- _ O
. -X- _ O

Giila -X- _ O
ang -X- _ O
lima -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
sila -X- _ O
Mario -X- _ B-PER
Marmita -X- _ I-PER
, -X- _ O
sakop -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
Omega -X- _ B-ORG
Drug -X- _ I-ORG
Group -X- _ I-ORG
; -X- _ O
Noli -X- _ B-PER
Rinos -X- _ I-PER
; -X- _ O
Allan -X- _ B-PER
Sia -X- _ I-PER
; -X- _ O
Elvira -X- _ B-PER
Cuevas -X- _ I-PER
ug -X- _ O
Jonalyn -X- _ B-PER
Culaba -X- _ I-PER
. -X- _ O

Nasakmit -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
PDEA -X- _ B-ORG
ang -X- _ O
usa -X- _ O
ka -X- _ O
inablihan -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
pa­kite -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
dunay -X- _ O
shabu -X- _ O
, -X- _ O
duha -X- _ O
ka -X- _ O
foil -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
dunay -X- _ O
shabu -X- _ O
ug -X- _ O
uban -X- _ O
gamit -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
pagsu­yop -X- _ O
. -X- _ O

Nadugangan -X- _ O
ang -X- _ O
kaso -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
lima -X- _ O
ka -X- _ O
piniriso -X- _ O
. -X- _ O

Giunay -X- _ O
pagdunggab -X- _ O
ang -X- _ O
usa -X- _ O
ka -X- _ O
76 -X- _ O
anyos -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
lolo -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
iyang -X- _ O
kauban -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
tagay -X- _ O
dihang -X- _ O
miinit -X- _ O
ang -X- _ O
panaglalis -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
duha -X- _ O
samtang -X- _ O
nag-inom -X- _ O
didto -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
Brgy. -X- _ B-LOC
San -X- _ I-LOC
Vicente -X- _ I-LOC
, -X- _ O
lungsod -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
Dagohoy -X- _ B-LOC
niadtong -X- _ O
Martes -X- _ O
. -X- _ O

Giila -X- _ O
ang -X- _ O
biktima -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
si -X- _ O
Felix -X- _ B-PER
Soliano -X- _ I-PER
, -X- _ O
mag-uuma -X- _ O
ug -X- _ O
residente -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
Purok -X- _ B-LOC
4 -X- _ I-LOC
, -X- _ I-LOC
Barangay -X- _ I-LOC
San -X- _ I-LOC
Vicente -X- _ I-LOC
, -X- _ I-LOC
lungsod -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
Dagohoy -X- _ B-LOC
. -X- _ O

Sa -X- _ O
pakisusi -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
kapulisan -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
, -X- _ O
nasayran -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
ang -X- _ O
duha -X- _ O
nagtagay -X- _ O
kauban -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
ilang -X- _ O
laing -X- _ O
mga -X- _ O
higala -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
usa -X- _ O
ka -X- _ O
tindahan -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
nahisgutang -X- _ O
barangay -X- _ O
. -X- _ O

Usa -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
lima -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
nasakpan -X- _ O
ang -X- _ O
nakuhaan -X- _ O
og -X- _ O
laing -X- _ O
usa -X- _ O
ka -X- _ O
putos -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
gituhoang -X- _ O
shabu -X- _ O
. -X- _ O

Ang -X- _ O
shabu -X- _ O
dunay -X- _ O
timbang -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
singko -X- _ O
gramos -X- _ O
ug -X- _ O
nagkantidad -X- _ O
og -X- _ O
P25,000 -X- _ O
. -X- _ O

Si -X- _ O
Ramos -X- _ B-PER
nasakpan -X- _ O
ng -X- _ O
daan -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
nagsuyop -X- _ O
uban -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
laing -X- _ O
lima -X- _ O
ka -X- _ O
suspek -X- _ O
. -X- _ O

Samdan -X- _ O
ang -X- _ O
15 -X- _ O
ka -X- _ O
tawo -X- _ O
human -X- _ O
magbangga -X- _ O
ang -X- _ O
usa -X- _ O
ka -X- _ O
bus -X- _ O
ug -X- _ O
10-wheeler -X- _ O
truck -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
highway -X- _ O
sakop -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
Barangay -X- _ B-LOC
Pahug -X- _ I-LOC
ning -X- _ O
lungsod -X- _ O
. -X- _ O

Pag-abot -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
nahitaboan -X- _ O
, -X- _ O
mibalhin -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
pikas -X- _ O
linya -X- _ O
ang -X- _ O
bus -X- _ O
gumikan -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
naguba -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
karsada -X- _ O
nunot -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
bagyong -X- _ O
Urduja -X- _ B-OTHER
. -X- _ O

Nakasugat -X- _ O
niini -X- _ O
ang -X- _ O
trak -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
gimaneho -X- _ O
ni -X- _ O
Ramil -X- _ B-PER
Yepes -X- _ I-PER
nga -X- _ O
dunay -X- _ O
kargang -X- _ O
mga -X- _ O
bato -X- _ O
. -X- _ O

Misuway -X- _ O
pagpreno -X- _ O
si -X- _ O
Yepes -X- _ B-PER
aron -X- _ O
malikayan -X- _ O
ang -X- _ O
panangbangga -X- _ O
apan -X- _ O
wa -X- _ O
kini -X- _ O
makakontrolar -X- _ O
gumikan -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
basa -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
karsada. -X- _ O
Samdan -X- _ O
ang -X- _ O
13 -X- _ O
ka -X- _ O
pasahero -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
bus -X- _ O
ug -X- _ O
drayber -X- _ O
niini -X- _ O
ingon -X- _ O
man -X- _ O
ang -X- _ O
drayber -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
trak -X- _ O
. -X- _ O

Gidala -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
Eastern -X- _ B-LOC
Visayas -X- _ I-LOC
Regional -X- _ I-LOC
Medical -X- _ I-LOC
Center -X- _ I-LOC
( -X- _ I-LOC
EVRMC -X- _ I-LOC
) -X- _ I-LOC
ang -X- _ O
mga -X- _ O
samdan -X- _ O
. -X- _ O

Daghang -X- _ O
mga -X- _ O
biyahe -X- _ O
ang -X- _ O
kanselado -X- _ O
samtang -X- _ O
liboan -X- _ O
na -X- _ O
usab -X- _ O
ka -X- _ O
mga -X- _ O
pasahero -X- _ O
ang -X- _ O
stranded -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
gusto -X- _ O
unta -X- _ O
mouli -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
ilang -X- _ O
probinsiya -X- _ O
karong -X- _ O
Pasko -X- _ O
tungod -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
bagyong -X- _ O
Vinta -X- _ I-OTHER
. -X- _ O

Matod -X- _ O
ni -X- _ O
Commander -X- _ O
Jerome -X- _ B-PER
Cayabyab -X- _ I-PER
sa -X- _ O
Cebu -X- _ B-ORG
Coast -X- _ I-ORG
Guard -X- _ I-ORG
nga -X- _ O
wa -X- _ O
nila -X- _ O
tugoti -X- _ O
ang -X- _ O
mga -X- _ O
sakyanan -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
dagat -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
mobiyahe -X- _ O
tungod -X- _ O
kay -X- _ O
ang -X- _ O
port -X- _ O
of -X- _ O
destinations -X- _ O
niini -X- _ O
gipaubos -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
storm -X- _ O
signal -X- _ O
. -X- _ O

Samtang -X- _ O
niabot -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
1,531 -X- _ O
ka -X- _ O
mga -X- _ O
pasahero -X- _ O
ang -X- _ O
stranded -X- _ O
alang -X- _ O
unta -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
mga -X- _ O
biyahe -X- _ O
paingon -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
Bohol -X- _ B-LOC
, -X- _ O
Leyte -X- _ B-LOC
, -X- _ O
Negros -X- _ B-LOC
Occidental -X- _ I-LOC
/ -X- _ I-LOC
Oriental -X- _ I-LOC
, -X- _ O
Dipolog -X- _ B-LOC
, -X- _ O
Surigao -X- _ B-LOC
, -X- _ O
Cagayan -X- _ B-LOC
, -X- _ O
ug -X- _ O
uban -X- _ O
pa -X- _ O
. -X- _ O

Duna -X- _ O
usay -X- _ O
mga -X- _ O
bus -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
padulong -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
Negros -X- _ B-LOC
Oriental -X- _ I-LOC
, -X- _ O
labina -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
dakbayan -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
Dumaguate -X- _ B-LOC
ug -X- _ O
Mindanao -X- _ B-LOC
, -X- _ O
ang -X- _ O
wa -X- _ O
usab -X- _ O
patabuka -X- _ O
gikan -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
Sugbo -X- _ B-LOC
. -X- _ O

Sa -X- _ O
ilang -X- _ O
forecast -X- _ O
, -X- _ O
gilauman -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
mo-landfall -X- _ O
ang -X- _ O
bagyong -X- _ O
Vinta -X- _ I-OTHER
sa -X- _ O
Caraga -X- _ B-LOC
, -X- _ I-LOC
Davao -X- _ I-LOC
Region -X- _ I-LOC
kagabii -X- _ O
o -X- _ O
karong -X- _ O
buntag -X- _ O
. -X- _ O

Paingon -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
kasadpan -X- _ O
ang -X- _ O
direksyon -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
maong -X- _ O
bagyo -X- _ O
diin -X- _ O
aduna -X- _ O
pag-irog -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
21 -X- _ O
kilometros -X- _ O
matag -X- _ O
takna -X- _ O
ug -X- _ O
nagdala -X- _ O
og -X- _ O
hangin -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
65 -X- _ O
kilometros -X- _ O
matag -X- _ O
takna -X- _ O
ug -X- _ O
unos -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
moabot -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
80 -X- _ O
kilometros -X- _ O
matag -X- _ O
takna -X- _ O
. -X- _ O

Dugang -X- _ O
ni -X- _ O
Canasa -X- _ B-PER
nga -X- _ O
susama -X- _ O
ra -X- _ O
ang -X- _ O
hangin -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
gidala -X- _ O
ni -X- _ O
Vinta -X- _ B-PER
ug -X- _ O
ni -X- _ O
Urduja -X- _ B-PER
, -X- _ O
apan -X- _ O
mas -X- _ O
paspas -X- _ O
ang -X- _ O
irog -X- _ O
ni -X- _ O
Vinta -X- _ B-PER
. -X- _ O

Matod -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
labaw -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
PDRRMO -X- _ B-ORG
Emergency -X- _ I-ORG
Response -X- _ I-ORG
ug -X- _ O
Search -X- _ O
and -X- _ O
Rescue -X- _ O
Division -X- _ O
, -X- _ O
Kathy -X- _ B-PER
dela -X- _ I-PER
Calzada -X- _ I-PER
, -X- _ O
ang -X- _ O
mga -X- _ O
lungsod -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
Malabuyoc -X- _ B-LOC
ug -X- _ O
Boljoon -X- _ B-LOC
, -X- _ O
kinahanglang -X- _ O
magmabinantayon -X- _ O
human -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
duna -X- _ O
nay -X- _ O
kasaysayan -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
landslide -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
mugna -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
uwan -X- _ O
. -X- _ O

Sa -X- _ O
brgy. -X- _ B-LOC
Lower -X- _ I-LOC
Beceril -X- _ I-LOC
sa -X- _ O
lungsod -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
Boljoon -X- _ B-LOC
, -X- _ O
wa -X- _ O
pa -X- _ O
hingpit -X- _ O
nahupay -X- _ O
ang -X- _ O
kabalaka -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
mga -X- _ O
residente -X- _ O
labot -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
posibleng -X- _ O
pagdahili -X- _ O
na -X- _ O
usab -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
yuta -X- _ O
dinhi -X- _ O
. -X- _ O

Gawas -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
mga -X- _ O
landslide -X- _ O
, -X- _ O
biktima -X- _ O
sab -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
mga -X- _ O
pagbaha -X- _ O
ang -X- _ O
daghang -X- _ O
dapit -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
southern -X- _ O
Cebu -X- _ B-LOC
dihang -X- _ O
niigo -X- _ O
ang -X- _ O
mga -X- _ O
bagyong -X- _ O
Queenie -X- _ I-OTHER
, -X- _ O
Ruby -X- _ B-OTHER
ug -X- _ O
Seniang -X- _ B-OTHER
niadtong -X- _ O
2014 -X- _ O
. -X- _ O

Gihimug-atan -X- _ O
ni -X- _ O
dela -X- _ B-PER
Calzada -X- _ I-PER
ang -X- _ O
importansiya -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
panag-ala­yon -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
mga -X- _ O
residente -X- _ O
ngadto -X- _ O
na -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
mga -X- _ O
barangay -X- _ O
o -X- _ O
kaha -X- _ O
municipal -X- _ O
ug -X- _ O
city -X- _ O
DRRM -X- _ B-ORG
aron -X- _ O
way -X- _ O
masinating -X- _ O
kakulian -X- _ O
, -X- _ O
taliwala -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
bagyo -X- _ O
. -X- _ O

Ang -X- _ O
pag-obserbar -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
mga -X- _ O
lagda -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
trapiko -X- _ O
di -X- _ O
lamang -X- _ O
makasiguro -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
hapsay -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
dagan -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
trapiko -X- _ O
, -X- _ O
makaluwas -X- _ O
usab -X- _ O
kini -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
mga -X- _ O
kinabuhi -X- _ O
. -X- _ O

Ang -X- _ O
PNP -X- _ B-ORG
Traffic -X- _ I-ORG
Operation -X- _ I-ORG
Groups -X- _ I-ORG
sa -X- _ O
Cebu -X- _ B-ORG
City -X- _ I-ORG
Traffic -X- _ I-ORG
Office -X- _ I-ORG
( -X- _ I-ORG
CCTO -X- _ I-ORG
) -X- _ I-ORG
nitala -X- _ O
og -X- _ O
mas -X- _ O
daghang -X- _ O
mga -X- _ O
aksidente -X- _ O
karong -X- _ O
tuiga -X- _ O
, -X- _ O
gikan -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
Enero -X- _ O
ngadto -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
Nobiyembre -X- _ O
, -X- _ O
apan -X- _ O
mas -X- _ O
minos -X- _ O
ang -X- _ O
nangamatay -X- _ O
. -X- _ O

Base -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
record -X- _ O
, -X- _ O
dunay -X- _ O
42 -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
nangamatay -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
aksidente -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
kadalanan -X- _ O
karong -X- _ O
tuiga -X- _ O
, -X- _ O
mas -X- _ O
ubos -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
48 -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
2016 -X- _ O
. -X- _ O

Kini -X- _ O
nagpasabot -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
dunay -X- _ O
tulo -X- _ O
ka -X- _ O
mga -X- _ O
tawo -X- _ O
ang -X- _ O
nangamatay -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
aksidente -X- _ O
matag -X- _ O
buwan -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
2017 -X- _ O
, -X- _ O
mas -X- _ O
ubos -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
2016 -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
nag-average -X- _ O
og -X- _ O
upat -X- _ O
. -X- _ O

Apan -X- _ O
mas -X- _ O
daghan -X- _ O
ang -X- _ O
mga -X- _ O
aksidente -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
2017 -X- _ O
, -X- _ O
diin -X- _ O
niabot -X- _ O
og -X- _ O
11,153 -X- _ O
, -X- _ O
mas -X- _ O
taas -X- _ O
itandi -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
10,918 -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
2016 -X- _ O
. -X- _ O

Nagpasabot -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
dinhi -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
dakbayan -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
2017 -X- _ O
, -X- _ O
dunay -X- _ O
labing -X- _ O
minos -X- _ O
33 -X- _ O
ka -X- _ O
mga -X- _ O
aksidente -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
dalan -X- _ O
matag -X- _ O
adlaw -X- _ O
ang -X- _ O
mahitabo -X- _ O
. -X- _ O

Si -X- _ O
Sidney -X- _ B-PER
Racaza -X- _ I-PER
, -X- _ O
control -X- _ O
ope­­ra­tions -X- _ O
officer -X- _ O
, -X- _ O
niingon -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
kadaghanan -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
mga -X- _ O
aksidente -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
trapiko -X- _ O
naglambigit -X- _ O
og -X- _ O
motorsiklo -X- _ O
ug -X- _ O
way -X- _ O
pagtahod -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
balaud -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
trapiko -X- _ O
. -X- _ O

Positibong -X- _ O
gitudlo -X- _ O
ni -X- _ O
Eliza­beth -X- _ B-PER
Ybañez -X- _ I-PER
si -X- _ O
Tumara -X- _ B-PER
nga -X- _ O
maoy -X- _ O
nipusil -X- _ O
patay -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
iyang -X- _ O
bana -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
si -X- _ O
konsehal -X- _ O
Iluminado -X- _ B-PER
Ybañez -X- _ I-PER
niadtong -X- _ O
2013 -X- _ O
sud -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
ilang -X- _ O
balay -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
Barangay -X- _ B-LOC
Maharuhay -X- _ I-LOC
lungsod -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
Medellin -X- _ B-LOC
. -X- _ O

Matod -X- _ O
ni -X- _ O
Elizabeth -X- _ B-PER
nga -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
wa -X- _ O
pa -X- _ O
pusila -X- _ O
ang -X- _ O
iyang -X- _ O
bana -X- _ O
, -X- _ O
gipaarakan -X- _ O
pa -X- _ O
ang -X- _ O
ilang -X- _ O
balay -X- _ O
ni -X- _ O
Tumara -X- _ B-PER
nga -X- _ O
niadtong -X- _ O
mga -X- _ O
tungora -X- _ O
way -X- _ O
tawo -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
naigo -X- _ O
. -X- _ O

Apan -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
Oktubre -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
susamang -X- _ O
tuig -X- _ O
, -X- _ O
dinhi -X- _ O
na -X- _ O
niya -X- _ O
gipatay -X- _ O
ang -X- _ O
konsehal -X- _ O
samtang -X- _ O
dunay -X- _ O
gihimong -X- _ O
pulong-pulong -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
Barangay -X- _ B-LOC
Maharuhay -X- _ I-LOC
. -X- _ O

Sukad -X- _ O
niadto -X- _ O
wa -X- _ O
na -X- _ O
mopakita -X- _ O
si -X- _ O
Tumara -X- _ B-PER
sa -X- _ O
ilang -X- _ O
lugar -X- _ O
ug -X- _ O
nisibat -X- _ O
bisan -X- _ O
pa -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
ilang -X- _ O
paningkamot -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
masikop -X- _ O
. -X- _ O

Nakadawat -X- _ O
og -X- _ O
report -X- _ O
ang -X- _ O
PRO -X- _ B-ORG
7 -X- _ I-ORG
nga -X- _ O
naa -X- _ O
ra -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
sitio -X- _ O
Taganas -X- _ B-LOC
, -X- _ O
Barangay -X- _ B-LOC
San -X- _ I-LOC
Marcos -X- _ I-LOC
, -X- _ O
lungsod -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
Placer -X- _ B-LOC
nagtago -X- _ O
si -X- _ O
Tumara -X- _ B-PER
. -X- _ O

Mopatuman -X- _ O
og -X- _ O
mga -X- _ O
kausaban -X- _ O
ang -X- _ O
Basilica -X- _ B-ORG
Minore -X- _ I-ORG
del -X- _ I-ORG
Sto. -X- _ I-ORG
Niño -X- _ I-ORG
atol -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
ika-453 -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
kapistahan -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
adlaw -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
natawhan -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
Balaang -X- _ O
Bata -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
si -X- _ O
Sr. -X- _ O
Sto. -X- _ B-PER
Niño -X- _ I-PER
. -X- _ O

Magsugod -X- _ O
ang -X- _ O
nobenaryo -X- _ O
karong -X- _ O
Enero -X- _ O
11 -X- _ O
diin -X- _ O
ang -X- _ O
“Walk -X- _ B-OTHER
with -X- _ I-OTHER
Jesus” -X- _ I-OTHER
nga -X- _ O
manukad -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
Fuente -X- _ B-LOC
Osmeña -X- _ I-LOC
magsugod -X- _ O
alas -X- _ O
4 -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
kaadlawon -X- _ O
inay -X- _ O
alas -X- _ O
4:30 -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
kaadlawon -X- _ O
ug -X- _ O
mao -X- _ O
sab -X- _ O
ang -X- _ O
sundon -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
Walk -X- _ B-OTHER
with -X- _ I-OTHER
Mary -X- _ I-OTHER
inig -X- _ O
Enero -X- _ O
19 -X- _ O
alang -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
ika-9 -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
adlaw -X- _ O
. -X- _ O

Si -X- _ O
Fr. -X- _ O
Noel -X- _ B-PER
Cogasa -X- _ I-PER
nagkanayon -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
gikan -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
Enero -X- _ O
12 -X- _ O
hangtod -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
18 -X- _ O
, -X- _ O
adunay -X- _ O
tag -X- _ O
11 -X- _ O
ka -X- _ O
misa -X- _ O
ang -X- _ O
ipahigayon -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
Basilica -X- _ B-LOC
nga -X- _ O
bahinon -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
unom -X- _ O
ka -X- _ O
Bisaya -X- _ O
ug -X- _ O
5 -X- _ O
ka -X- _ O
English -X- _ B-OTHER
nga -X- _ O
misa -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
pagasugdan -X- _ O
alas -X- _ O
4 -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
kadlawon -X- _ O
hangtod -X- _ O
alas -X- _ O
7 -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
gabii -X- _ O
. -X- _ O

Ang -X- _ O
Basilica -X- _ B-LOC
abli -X- _ O
24 -X- _ O
oras -X- _ O
para -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
pag-ampo -X- _ O
apan -X- _ O
adu­nay -X- _ O
pipila -X- _ O
ka -X- _ O
oras -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
sirad-an -X- _ O
kini -X- _ O
para -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
paglimpyo -X- _ O
apan -X- _ O
ang -X- _ O
altar -X- _ O
diin -X- _ O
nahimutang -X- _ O
ang -X- _ O
Balaang -X- _ O
Bata -X- _ O
abli -X- _ O
24 -X- _ O
oras -X- _ O
para -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
mga -X- _ O
tawo -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
gustong -X- _ O
mobisita -X- _ O
ug -X- _ O
mohalok -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
iyang -X- _ O
imahen -X- _ O
. -X- _ O

Gihangyo -X- _ O
ni -X- _ O
Fr. -X- _ O
Aladdin -X- _ B-PER
Luzon -X- _ I-PER
, -X- _ O
director -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
safety -X- _ O
, -X- _ O
security -X- _ O
, -X- _ O
peace -X- _ O
and -X- _ O
order -X- _ O
, -X- _ O
ang -X- _ O
mga -X- _ O
tawo -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
dili -X- _ O
pagdala -X- _ O
og -X- _ O
mga -X- _ O
backpack -X- _ O
aron -X- _ O
dili -X- _ O
malangan -X- _ O
ang -X- _ O
pagsulod -X- _ O
sanglit -X- _ O
estrikto -X- _ O
ang -X- _ O
security -X- _ O
ug -X- _ O
gidili -X- _ O
usab -X- _ O
ang -X- _ O
balloon -X- _ O
. -X- _ O

Adunay -X- _ O
tulo -X- _ O
ka -X- _ O
mga -X- _ O
entrance -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
nahimutang -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
D. -X- _ B-LOC
Jakosalem -X- _ I-LOC
, -X- _ O
Plaza -X- _ B-LOC
Sugbo -X- _ I-LOC
ug -X- _ O
P. -X- _ B-LOC
Burgos -X- _ I-LOC
ug -X- _ O
ang -X- _ O
ubang -X- _ O
mga -X- _ O
pultahan -X- _ O
gitagana -X- _ O
para -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
exits -X- _ O
. -X- _ O

Mobutang -X- _ O
usab -X- _ O
og -X- _ O
labing -X- _ O
minos -X- _ O
pito -X- _ O
ka -X- _ O
LED -X- _ O
screen -X- _ O
ang -X- _ O
Basilica -X- _ B-LOC
palibot -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
simbahan -X- _ O
para -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
mga -X- _ O
tawo -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
dili -X- _ O
na -X- _ O
makasulod -X- _ O
gumikan -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
kadaghan -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
motambong -X- _ O
. -X- _ O

Ang -X- _ O
Walk -X- _ B-OTHER
with -X- _ I-OTHER
Mary -X- _ I-OTHER
gikan -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
Barangay -X- _ B-LOC
Guadalupe -X- _ I-LOC
paingon -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
Fuente -X- _ B-LOC
Osmeña -X- _ I-LOC
dayon -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
paingon -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
Basilica -X- _ B-LOC
, -X- _ O
iparada -X- _ O
ang -X- _ O
mga -X- _ O
imahen -X- _ O
ngadto -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
Saint -X- _ B-LOC
Joseph -X- _ I-LOC
National -X- _ I-LOC
Shrine -X- _ I-LOC
nga -X- _ O
gikatakdang -X- _ O
moabot -X- _ O
alas -X- _ O
9 -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
buntag -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
pagasundan -X- _ O
og -X- _ O
misa -X- _ O
. -X- _ O

Magsugod -X- _ O
ang -X- _ O
send-off -X- _ O
mas -X- _ O
Enero -X- _ O
20 -X- _ O
alas -X- _ O
2 -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
kadlawon -X- _ O
ug -X- _ O
inig -X- _ O
ka -X- _ O
alas -X- _ O
3 -X- _ O
sugdan -X- _ O
ang -X- _ O
Traslacion -X- _ B-OTHER
paingon -X- _ O
ngadto -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
Virgen -X- _ B-LOC
de -X- _ I-LOC
Regla -X- _ I-LOC
National -X- _ I-LOC
Shrine -X- _ I-LOC
sa -X- _ O
Lapu-Lapu -X- _ B-LOC
City -X- _ I-LOC
. -X- _ O

Alas -X- _ O
4 -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
kadlawon -X- _ O
moabot -X- _ O
ang -X- _ O
mga -X- _ O
imahen -X- _ O
didto -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
Birhen -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
Regla -X- _ O
ug -X- _ O
ipahigayon -X- _ O
ang -X- _ O
welcome -X- _ O
mass -X- _ O
da­yon -X- _ O
mag-motorcade -X- _ O
paingon -X- _ O
ngadto -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
dockyard -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
Naval -X- _ B-ORG
Forces -X- _ I-ORG
Central -X- _ I-ORG
sa -X- _ O
barangay -X- _ O
Canjulao -X- _ B-LOC
. -X- _ O

Kon -X- _ O
naandan -X- _ O
ang -X- _ O
Galleon -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
mga -X- _ O
Ouano -X- _ O
, -X- _ O
niining -X- _ O
puntoha -X- _ O
ang -X- _ O
gamiton -X- _ O
mao -X- _ O
ang -X- _ O
barko -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
Navy -X- _ O
kansang -X- _ O
fluvial -X- _ O
procession -X- _ O
sugdan -X- _ O
alas -X- _ O
6 -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
buntag -X- _ O
. -X- _ O

Mosubay -X- _ O
gihapon -X- _ O
ang -X- _ O
mga -X- _ O
barko -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
karaang -X- _ O
rota -X- _ O
ug -X- _ O
motuyok -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
Mactan -X- _ B-LOC
Channel -X- _ I-LOC
sa -X- _ O
dili -X- _ O
pa -X- _ O
molabang -X- _ O
paingon -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
Pier -X- _ O
Uno -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
alas -X- _ O
8 -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
buntag -X- _ O
diin -X- _ O
ipahigayon -X- _ O
ang -X- _ O
mubo -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
foot -X- _ O
procession -X- _ O
. -X- _ O

Ang -X- _ O
Galleon -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
sakyanan -X- _ O
ni -X- _ O
Sto. -X- _ B-OTHER
Niño -X- _ I-OTHER
adunay -X- _ O
150 -X- _ O
ka -X- _ O
mga -X- _ O
tawo -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
gitugotang -X- _ O
makasakay -X- _ O
, -X- _ O
50 -X- _ O
gikan -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
Navy -X- _ O
ug -X- _ O
100 -X- _ O
gikan -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
Basilica -X- _ B-LOC
diin -X- _ O
gidili -X- _ O
ang -X- _ O
pagpalupad -X- _ O
og -X- _ O
mga -X- _ O
balloon -X- _ O
. -X- _ O

Atol -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
procession -X- _ O
inig -X- _ O
ka -X- _ O
hapon -X- _ O
, -X- _ O
giawhag -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
mga -X- _ O
pareng -X- _ O
Agustino -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
ang -X- _ O
tanan -X- _ O
magdala -X- _ O
og -X- _ O
rosario -X- _ O
ug -X- _ O
mag-ampo -X- _ O
ug -X- _ O
dili -X- _ O
mag-estorya -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
ilang -X- _ O
mga -X- _ O
kuyo -X- _ O
sanglit -X- _ O
gituyo -X- _ O
ang -X- _ O
maong -X- _ O
kalihukan -X- _ O
para -X- _ O
maghinusol -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
mga -X- _ O
sala -X- _ O
ug -X- _ O
magpasalamat -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
mga -X- _ O
grasya -X- _ O
. -X- _ O

Dili -X- _ O
na -X- _ O
tugotan -X- _ O
ni -X- _ O
Mayor -X- _ O
Tomas -X- _ B-PER
Osmeña -X- _ I-PER
nga -X- _ O
makaabli -X- _ O
pa -X- _ O
og -X- _ O
balik -X- _ O
ang -X- _ O
Vic -X- _ B-ORG
Enterprises -X- _ I-ORG
nga -X- _ O
nahimutang -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
barangay -X- _ O
Mabolo -X- _ B-LOC
human -X- _ O
niya -X- _ O
gipasirado -X- _ O
ang -X- _ O
ilang -X- _ O
tindahan -X- _ O
ug -X- _ O
bodega -X- _ O
. -X- _ O

Kagahapon -X- _ O
, -X- _ O
ang -X- _ O
personnel -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
City -X- _ O
Hall -X- _ O
nipasirado -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
ilang -X- _ O
tindahan -X- _ O
ug -X- _ O
12 -X- _ O
ka -X- _ O
bodega -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
maoy -X- _ O
gipundohan -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
ilang -X- _ O
construction -X- _ O
materials -X- _ O
gumikan -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
kakuwang -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
ilang -X- _ O
business -X- _ O
permit -X- _ O
. -X- _ O

Si -X- _ O
Osmeña -X- _ B-PER
nibutyag -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
makabalik -X- _ O
lang -X- _ O
ang -X- _ O
operas­yon -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
maong -X- _ O
hardware -X- _ O
kon -X- _ O
siya -X- _ O
pusilon -X- _ O
. -X- _ O

Ang -X- _ O
mayor -X- _ O
nagkanayon -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
dili -X- _ O
siya -X- _ O
maoy -X- _ O
angay -X- _ O
basulon -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
mga -X- _ O
gatusan -X- _ O
ka -X- _ O
mga -X- _ O
kawani -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
Vic -X- _ B-ORG
Enterprises -X- _ I-ORG
sang­lit -X- _ O
iyang -X- _ O
gipadayag -X- _ O
igo -X- _ O
ra -X- _ O
siyang -X- _ O
nagpatuman -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
balaod -X- _ O
. -X- _ O

Ang -X- _ O
12 -X- _ O
ka -X- _ O
warehouse -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
Vic -X- _ B-LOC
Enterprises -X- _ I-LOC
gihulagway -X- _ O
ni -X- _ O
Osmeña -X- _ B-PER
nga -X- _ O
walay -X- _ O
permit -X- _ O
ug -X- _ O
bisan -X- _ O
pending -X- _ O
permit -X- _ O
application -X- _ O
wala -X- _ O
siyay -X- _ O
nakita -X- _ O
. -X- _ O

Dugang -X- _ O
niya -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
dili -X- _ O
angay -X- _ O
mabalaka -X- _ O
ang -X- _ O
mga -X- _ O
kawani -X- _ O
sanglit -X- _ O
adunay -X- _ O
daghang -X- _ O
kwarta -X- _ O
ang -X- _ O
ilang -X- _ O
amo -X- _ O
ug -X- _ O
mahimo -X- _ O
silang -X- _ O
bayaran -X- _ O
. -X- _ O

Gitug-an -X- _ O
ni -X- _ O
Osmeña -X- _ B-PER
nga -X- _ O
mokita -X- _ O
kini -X- _ O
og -X- _ O
P1 -X- _ O
bilyon -X- _ O
matag -X- _ O
buwan -X- _ O
ug -X- _ O
nakapalit -X- _ O
kini -X- _ O
og -X- _ O
P600 -X- _ O
milyones -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
propriyedad -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
Mandaue -X- _ B-LOC
City -X- _ I-LOC
. -X- _ O

Giklaro -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
kadagkoan -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
Grab -X- _ B-ORG
nga -X- _ O
nisunod -X- _ O
sila -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
balaod -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
ilang -X- _ O
serbisyo -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
Grab -X- _ B-OTHER
Express -X- _ I-OTHER
diin -X- _ O
pag-deliver -X- _ O
og -X- _ O
parcel -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
Sugbo -X- _ B-LOC
. -X- _ O

Kini -X- _ O
sukwahi -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
taho -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
gihimo -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
mga -X- _ O
biker -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
kakompetinsya -X- _ O
niini -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
Angkas -X- _ B-OTHER
Padala -X- _ I-OTHER
nga -X- _ O
susama -X- _ O
lang -X- _ O
og -X- _ O
habalhabal -X- _ O
. -X- _ O

