-DOCSTART- -X- O
Pangandoy -X- _ O
ko -X- _ O
mag -X- _ O
crispy -X- _ B-LOC
king -X- _ I-LOC
! -X- _ O

Sent -X- _ O
to -X- _ O
us -X- _ O
by -X- _ O
a -X- _ O
concern -X- _ O
citizen. -X- _ O
Gamay -X- _ O
nalang -X- _ O
kulang -X- _ O
ma -X- _ O
actionan -X- _ O
na. -X- _ O
PAHIBALO -X- _ O
? -X- _ O
? -X- _ O
? -X- _ O
? -X- _ O
WALA -X- _ O
MI -X- _ O
KABALO -X- _ O
IF -X- _ O
SA -X- _ O
CITY -X- _ O
ENGINEERS -X- _ O
NI -X- _ O
NGA -X- _ O
TRABAHO -X- _ O
OR -X- _ O
WATER -X- _ B-LOC
DISTRICT -X- _ I-LOC
? -X- _ O
? -X- _ O
? -X- _ O
? -X- _ O
? -X- _ O
? -X- _ O
ALAYUN -X- _ O
MI -X- _ O
UG -X- _ O
ACTION -X- _ O
ANI -X- _ O
? -X- _ O
? -X- _ O
LOCATION -X- _ O
: -X- _ O
WEST -X- _ B-LOC
CITY -X- _ I-LOC
ELEMENTARY -X- _ I-LOC
SCHOOL -X- _ I-LOC
CROSSING -X- _ I-LOC
PADULONG -X- _ O
M.Y -X- _ B-LOC
HOTEL -X- _ I-LOC
INTAWUN -X- _ O
MAKA -X- _ O
DISGRASYA -X- _ O
KAAYO -X- _ O
NI. -X- _ O
GAMAY -X- _ O
NALANG -X- _ O
ANG -X- _ O
KULANG -X- _ O
MA -X- _ O
IROG -X- _ O
NAJUD -X- _ O
NG -X- _ O
TABON. -X- _ O
BALI -X- _ O
RABA -X- _ O
JUNG -X- _ O
LALUMA -X- _ O
SA -X- _ O
BANGAG. -X- _ O
DLI -X- _ O
UNTA -X- _ O
TA -X- _ O
MAGPA -X- _ O
ABUT -X- _ O
NAAY -X- _ O
MA -X- _ O
DISGRASYA -X- _ O
LABI -X- _ O
NAG -X- _ O
DLI -X- _ O
PD -X- _ O
MU -X- _ O
WILLING -X- _ O
MO -X- _ O
BAYAD -X- _ O
PANG -X- _ O
HOSPITAL. -X- _ O
DAGHANG -X- _ O
SALAMAT -X- _ O
! -X- _ O

Hi -X- _ O
admin.. -X- _ O
ganahan -X- _ O
ra -X- _ O
ko -X- _ O
clarification -X- _ O
jud. -X- _ O
Naa -X- _ O
man -X- _ O
gud -X- _ O
establishment -X- _ O
duol -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
west -X- _ B-LOC
city -X- _ I-LOC
bah -X- _ O
nya -X- _ O
layhan -X- _ O
unta -X- _ O
mo -X- _ O
magpaayu -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
among -X- _ O
gamit -X- _ O
so -X- _ O
ni -X- _ O
attempt -X- _ O
mi -X- _ O
ug -X- _ O
parking -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
ilang -X- _ O
atubangan -X- _ O
kay -X- _ O
vacant -X- _ O
man -X- _ O
siya. -X- _ O
now -X- _ O
ang -X- _ O
problema -X- _ O
ni -X- _ O
ana -X- _ O
tung -X- _ O
tag -X- _ O
bantay -X- _ O
dili -X- _ O
nila -X- _ O
pa -X- _ O
parkingan -X- _ O
ug -X- _ O
lain -X- _ O
kay -X- _ O
para -X- _ O
ra -X- _ O
na -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
tag -X- _ O
iya -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
sidewalk -X- _ O
lang -X- _ O
daw -X- _ O
mi -X- _ O
mag -X- _ O
park. -X- _ O
My -X- _ O
question -X- _ O
is -X- _ O
No. -X- _ O
1 -X- _ O
pwd -X- _ O
d -X- _ O
i -X- _ O
na -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
anha -X- _ O
man -X- _ O
unta -X- _ O
mi -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
ilaha -X- _ O
magpaayu -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
among -X- _ O
gamit -X- _ O
but -X- _ O
dili -X- _ O
mi -X- _ O
nila -X- _ O
pa -X- _ O
parkingun. -X- _ O
No.2. -X- _ O
Asa -X- _ O
dapit -X- _ O
na -X- _ O
law -X- _ O
or -X- _ O
republic -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
Pilipinas -X- _ B-LOC
ang -X- _ O
ga -X- _ O
ingun -X- _ O
na -X- _ O
pwd -X- _ O
ta -X- _ O
mag -X- _ O
park -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
sidewalk -X- _ O
but -X- _ O
not -X- _ O
on -X- _ O
a -X- _ O
establishment -X- _ O
na -X- _ O
naay -X- _ O
vacant -X- _ O
na -X- _ O
dako -X- _ O
as -X- _ O
n -X- _ O
masulog -X- _ O
jud -X- _ O
ang -X- _ O
3 -X- _ O
ka -X- _ O
sakyanan -X- _ O
ug -X- _ O
dli -X- _ O
lang -X- _ O
sila -X- _ O
dalo. -X- _ O
Salamat -X- _ O
admin -X- _ O

Brutala -X- _ O
rapod -X- _ O
kaau -X- _ O
oy -X- _ O
. -X- _ O

Impossible -X- _ O
nis -X- _ O
Dumaguete -X- _ B-LOC

Fiesta -X- _ O
na -X- _ O
hapit -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
Sibulan -X- _ B-LOC
! -X- _ O
Miss -X- _ B-MISC
Sibulan -X- _ I-MISC
tonight. -X- _ O
Photo -X- _ O
by -X- _ O
Jeben -X- _ O
Taob -X- _ O

magka -X- _ O
taas -X- _ O
ang -X- _ O
buwis -X- _ O
magka -X- _ O
mahal -X- _ O
na -X- _ O
ang -X- _ O
tanan -X- _ O
but -X- _ O
dile -X- _ O
rajapon -X- _ O
ta -X- _ O
maka -X- _ O
tilaw -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
atung -X- _ O
tax -X- _ O
kay -X- _ O
ehem. -X- _ O
Sila -X- _ O
ray -X- _ O
ma -X- _ O
dato -X- _ O
. -X- _ O

# -X- _ O
awareness -X- _ O
Good -X- _ O
morning -X- _ O
Hope -X- _ O
you -X- _ O
can -X- _ O
help -X- _ O
us -X- _ O
to -X- _ O
promote -X- _ O
awareness -X- _ O
aning -X- _ O
mga -X- _ O
tindira -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
isda -X- _ O
na -X- _ O
please -X- _ O
naman -X- _ O
be -X- _ O
reasonable -X- _ O
naman -X- _ O
asa -X- _ O
nila -X- _ O
gi -X- _ O
dispose -X- _ O
ilang -X- _ O
mga -X- _ O
tina-e -X- _ O
or -X- _ O
hasang -X- _ O
bana -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
isa. -X- _ O
Usa -X- _ O
ka -X- _ O
sako -X- _ O
diri -X- _ O
dapit -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
amoa -X- _ O
Batinguel -X- _ B-LOC
purok -X- _ I-LOC
7 -X- _ I-LOC
gilabay -X- _ O
, -X- _ O
ang -X- _ O
uban -X- _ O
anaa -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
dapit -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
katrina -X- _ B-LOC
home -X- _ I-LOC
sa -X- _ O
may -X- _ O
gate -X- _ O
then -X- _ O
ang -X- _ O
uban -X- _ O
anaa -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
Camanjac. -X- _ B-LOC
Kani -X- _ O
na -X- _ O
pictures -X- _ O
this -X- _ O
morning -X- _ O
ra -X- _ O
gyod -X- _ O
ni -X- _ O
. -X- _ O

hello -X- _ O
admin -X- _ O
, -X- _ O
naa -X- _ O
lang -X- _ O
unta -X- _ O
koy -X- _ O
e -X- _ O
raise -X- _ O
ba -X- _ O
... -X- _ O
Nahitabo -X- _ O
ni -X- _ O
siya -X- _ O
last -X- _ O
week -X- _ O
, -X- _ O
katong -X- _ O
naa -X- _ O
ang -X- _ O
Birhen -X- _ B-MISC
sa -X- _ I-MISC
Simala -X- _ I-MISC
sa -X- _ O
Cathedral. -X- _ I-LOC
traffic -X- _ O
kaayo -X- _ O
ni -X- _ O
that -X- _ O
time -X- _ O
and -X- _ O
naa -X- _ O
ko -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
BPI -X- _ B-ORG
gawas -X- _ O
ga -X- _ O
tindog -X- _ O
Wala -X- _ O
ko -X- _ O
kabalo -X- _ O
unsa -X- _ O
juy -X- _ O
violation -X- _ O
ani -X- _ O
niya -X- _ O
but -X- _ O
curious -X- _ O
lang -X- _ O
ko -X- _ O
, -X- _ O
possible -X- _ O
diay -X- _ O
ma -X- _ O
ticketan -X- _ O
ang -X- _ O
nangolekta -X- _ O
ug -X- _ O
basura -X- _ O
? -X- _ O
( -X- _ O
white -X- _ O
pick -X- _ O
up -X- _ O
) -X- _ O
On -X- _ O
the -X- _ O
other -X- _ O
side -X- _ O
, -X- _ O
same -X- _ O
time -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
panghitabo -X- _ O
, -X- _ O
wala -X- _ O
gani -X- _ O
nila -X- _ O
ticketi -X- _ O
ang -X- _ O
usa -X- _ O
ka -X- _ O
sakyanan -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
naas -X- _ O
tunga -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
kalsada -X- _ O
... -X- _ O
... -X- _ O
which -X- _ O
is -X- _ O
naka -X- _ O
cause -X- _ O
ug -X- _ O
traffic -X- _ O

Luoya -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
driver -X- _ O
. -X- _ O

Diba -X- _ O
Gender -X- _ O
neutral -X- _ O
man -X- _ O
jud -X- _ O
ang -X- _ O
Toga -X- _ O
? -X- _ O
Unsay -X- _ O
kailangan -X- _ O
usbon -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
pwede -X- _ O
man -X- _ O
gud -X- _ O
siya -X- _ O
for -X- _ O
Male -X- _ O
and -X- _ O
Female -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
mu -X- _ O
graduate -X- _ O
? -X- _ O
Let -X- _ O
us -X- _ O
not -X- _ O
be -X- _ O
influence -X- _ O
by -X- _ O
western -X- _ O
ideology -X- _ O
but -X- _ O
be -X- _ O
proud -X- _ O
of -X- _ O
what -X- _ O
we -X- _ O
have -X- _ O
in -X- _ O
culture -X- _ O
and -X- _ O
tradition. -X- _ O
Congrats -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
nang -X- _ O
graduate -X- _ O
be -X- _ O
the -X- _ O
future -X- _ O
be -X- _ O
the -X- _ O
best -X- _ O
as -X- _ O
what -X- _ O
Philippines -X- _ B-LOC
can -X- _ O
be -X- _ O
. -X- _ O

# -X- _ O
Dumashares -X- _ O
Truck -X- _ O
collision -X- _ O
in -X- _ O
Brgy. -X- _ B-LOC
Mayabon -X- _ I-LOC
Zamboanguita. -X- _ I-LOC
Zamboanguita -X- _ B-ORG
PNP -X- _ I-ORG
immediately -X- _ O
responded -X- _ O
the -X- _ O
incident. -X- _ O
Matod -X- _ O
pa -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
ato'ng -X- _ O
pakig-hinabi -X- _ O
, -X- _ O
nawad-on -X- _ O
ug -X- _ O
prino -X- _ O
ang -X- _ O
mao'ng -X- _ O
truck -X- _ O
hinungdan -X- _ O
ni-dasmag -X- _ O
kini -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
may -X- _ O
gemelina -X- _ O
ug -X- _ O
na-among -X- _ O
ang -X- _ O
lai'ng -X- _ O
naka-sugata -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
truck. -X- _ O
Gerome -X- _ O
Jaboni -X- _ O

Maka -X- _ O
intriga -X- _ O
pod -X- _ O
ni -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
maritest -X- _ O
skills -X- _ O
nato -X- _ O
. -X- _ O

Nakit.an -X- _ O
naba -X- _ O
ni -X- _ O
? -X- _ O
Lost -X- _ O
Dog -X- _ O
, -X- _ O
near -X- _ O
Science -X- _ B-LOC
High -X- _ I-LOC
School -X- _ I-LOC
area -X- _ O
, -X- _ O
along -X- _ O
St. -X- _ B-LOC
Peter -X- _ I-LOC
& -X- _ I-LOC
St. -X- _ I-LOC
Ignatius -X- _ I-LOC
Streets. -X- _ I-LOC
by -X- _ O
Ron -X- _ B-PER
Bacs -X- _ I-PER

Ang -X- _ O
bag.ung -X- _ O
megamall -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
dakpayan -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
Dumaguete -X- _ B-LOC
! -X- _ O
Ang -X- _ O
New -X- _ O
Unitop -X- _ B-LOC
mall -X- _ O
10 -X- _ O
times -X- _ O
bigger -X- _ O
than -X- _ O
what -X- _ O
we -X- _ O
previously -X- _ O
had -X- _ O
in -X- _ O
Dumaguete. -X- _ B-LOC
But -X- _ O
did -X- _ O
you -X- _ O
know -X- _ O
around -X- _ O
the -X- _ O
Philippines -X- _ B-LOC
they -X- _ O
already -X- _ O
have -X- _ O
bigger -X- _ O
Unitops -X- _ B-LOC
mall -X- _ O
, -X- _ O
only -X- _ O
dire -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
Dumaguete -X- _ B-LOC
did -X- _ O
we -X- _ O
have -X- _ O
the -X- _ O
smaller -X- _ O
version -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
ilang -X- _ O
tindahan. -X- _ O
Soft -X- _ O
openning -X- _ O
karong -X- _ O
June -X- _ O
9 -X- _ O
so -X- _ O
if -X- _ O
ganahan -X- _ O
mu -X- _ O
avoid -X- _ O
ug -X- _ O
traffic -X- _ O
ayaw -X- _ O
lang -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
ug -X- _ O
agi -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
tiangge -X- _ O
, -X- _ O
likod -X- _ O
FU -X- _ B-LOC
ug -X- _ O
colon -X- _ B-LOC
ext. -X- _ I-LOC
Reginald -X- _ O
Aragones -X- _ O

Mga -X- _ O
linya -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
scammers -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
nagka -X- _ O
daghan -X- _ O
na -X- _ O
especially -X- _ O
dire -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
Dumaguete -X- _ B-LOC
city -X- _ I-LOC
. -X- _ O

Ayaw -X- _ O
koya -X- _ O

Kana -X- _ O
bang -X- _ O
abi -X- _ O
nimug -X- _ O
basket -X- _ O
ra -X- _ O
imung -X- _ O
gi -X- _ O
tan.aw -X- _ O
nya -X- _ O
bonus -X- _ O
kay -X- _ O
naampod -X- _ O
diay -X- _ O
royal -X- _ O
rumble -X- _ O
. -X- _ O

Strickto -X- _ O
nis -X- _ O
first -X- _ O
week -X- _ O
! -X- _ O
Second -X- _ O
week -X- _ O
mejo -X- _ O
manakop -X- _ O
pa -X- _ O
! -X- _ O
Third -X- _ O
week -X- _ O
mangape -X- _ O
nas -X- _ O
tiangge -X- _ O
! -X- _ O
? -X- _ O
The -X- _ O
power -X- _ O
of -X- _ O
Dumaguete -X- _ B-LOC
enforcement -X- _ O
! -X- _ O
? -X- _ O
? -X- _ O

Naa -X- _ O
tay -X- _ O
ing.ani -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
Dumaguete. -X- _ B-LOC
Ma -X- _ O
dakpan -X- _ O
my -X- _ O
hilak -X- _ O
baaah -X- _ O

Imagine -X- _ O
pa -X- _ O
byahe -X- _ O
kag -X- _ O
Cebu -X- _ B-LOC
ani -X- _ O
. -X- _ O

Pa -X- _ O
shout -X- _ O
out -X- _ O
nalang -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
mga -X- _ O
biktima -X- _ O

Admin -X- _ O
maaung -X- _ O
hapon -X- _ O
na -X- _ O
kawat -X- _ O
akung -X- _ O
cellphone -X- _ O
this -X- _ O
morning -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
boulevard -X- _ B-LOC
Jerrys -X- _ I-LOC
dapit. -X- _ O
Pang -X- _ O
spread -X- _ O
rakog -X- _ O
awareness -X- _ O
basin -X- _ O
nay -X- _ O
naka -X- _ O
kita -X- _ O
admin. -X- _ O
Mu -X- _ O
hatag -X- _ O
rakog -X- _ O
reward -X- _ O
please -X- _ O
rako -X- _ O
pa -X- _ O
contact -X- _ O
Jeben -X- _ B-PER
Taob -X- _ I-PER
09061005118 -X- _ O

Coming -X- _ O
from -X- _ O
sender -X- _ O
Need -X- _ O
nato -X- _ O
e -X- _ O
priotize -X- _ O
ang -X- _ O
school -X- _ O
zone -X- _ O
slowdown -X- _ O
within -X- _ O
national -X- _ B-LOC
highway -X- _ I-LOC
and -X- _ O
anywhere -X- _ O
naay -X- _ O
school -X- _ O
zone -X- _ O
and -X- _ O
also -X- _ O
re -X- _ O
affirm -X- _ O
to -X- _ O
educate -X- _ O
children -X- _ O
of -X- _ O
looking -X- _ O
left -X- _ O
and -X- _ O
right -X- _ O
once -X- _ O
crossing -X- _ O
the -X- _ O
street -X- _ O
within -X- _ O
the -X- _ O
school -X- _ O
system. -X- _ O
" -X- _ O
Nikalit -X- _ O
daw -X- _ O
labang -X- _ O
Ang -X- _ O
bata -X- _ O
na -X- _ O
abtan -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
ga -X- _ O
motor -X- _ O
looy -X- _ O
kaayo -X- _ O
pud -X- _ O
Ang -X- _ O
rider -X- _ O
sir -X- _ O
" -X- _ O

Expect -X- _ O
nalang -X- _ O
tas -X- _ O
Sabado -X- _ O
mag -X- _ O
ulan -X- _ O
ulan -X- _ O
. -X- _ O

Royal -X- _ B-MISC
daun -X- _ O
gi -X- _ O
palit -X- _ O
. -X- _ O

Goodmorning -X- _ O
admin -X- _ O
, -X- _ O
permission -X- _ O
to -X- _ O
post -X- _ O
po. -X- _ O
Naa -X- _ O
mi -X- _ O
nakit-an -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
PASSBOOK -X- _ O
ni -X- _ O
BERNABE -X- _ B-PER
ROMANO -X- _ I-PER
CADAYONA -X- _ I-PER
taga -X- _ O
SITIO -X- _ B-LOC
SANLAGAN -X- _ I-LOC
, -X- _ I-LOC
OKIOT -X- _ I-LOC
, -X- _ I-LOC
BAIS -X- _ I-LOC
, -X- _ I-LOC
NEGROS -X- _ I-LOC
ORIENTAL. -X- _ I-LOC
Mamalihog -X- _ O
mi -X- _ O
kung -X- _ O
kinsa -X- _ O
ang -X- _ O
nakaila -X- _ O
ani -X- _ O
niya. -X- _ O
Pwde -X- _ O
niya -X- _ O
iclain -X- _ O
ang -X- _ O
iyang -X- _ O
PASSBOOK -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
F -X- _ B-LOC
& -X- _ I-LOC
FO -X- _ I-LOC
MOTOR -X- _ I-LOC
PARTS -X- _ I-LOC
VILLA -X- _ I-LOC
AMADA -X- _ I-LOC
near -X- _ O
Wheeltek -X- _ B-LOC
og -X- _ O
Qualfon. -X- _ B-LOC
Thank -X- _ O
you -X- _ O
. -X- _ O

Kana -X- _ O
ganeng -X- _ O
naka -X- _ O
car -X- _ O
raka -X- _ O
but -X- _ O
wala -X- _ O
japon -X- _ O
kay -X- _ O
buot -X- _ O
. -X- _ O

Daghan -X- _ O
naman -X- _ O
gud -X- _ O
inchek -X- _ B-MISC
nationals -X- _ O
dire -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
Pinas -X- _ B-LOC
mura -X- _ O
ganeg -X- _ O
kinsa -X- _ O
nang -X- _ O
uban -X- _ O
. -X- _ O

Good -X- _ O
Morning -X- _ O
Everyone -X- _ O
! -X- _ O
Basi -X- _ O
naa -X- _ O
nakakita -X- _ O
Brown -X- _ O
Wallet -X- _ O
, -X- _ O
RRJ -X- _ B-MISC
na -X- _ O
brand. -X- _ O
May -X- _ O
16 -X- _ O
, -X- _ O
2023 -X- _ O
around -X- _ O
5:40pm -X- _ O
, -X- _ O
Dumaguete-Dauin -X- _ B-LOC
na -X- _ O
route -X- _ O
, -X- _ O
vice -X- _ O
versa. -X- _ O
Naa -X- _ O
didto -X- _ O
ang -X- _ O
Driver -X- _ O
's -X- _ O
License -X- _ O
, -X- _ O
cash -X- _ O
, -X- _ O
rehistro -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
motor -X- _ O
and -X- _ O
other -X- _ O
Stuff -X- _ O
ni -X- _ O
Vincent -X- _ B-PER
Marlon -X- _ I-PER
Macadildig. -X- _ I-PER
PLEASE -X- _ O
CONTACT -X- _ O
ME -X- _ O
/ -X- _ O
US -X- _ O
IF -X- _ O
EVER -X- _ O
NAA -X- _ O
MO -X- _ O
MAKIT.AN. -X- _ O
THANK -X- _ O
YOU -X- _ O
SO -X- _ O
MUCH -X- _ O
! -X- _ O
Pwede -X- _ O
ko -X- _ O
ninyo -X- _ O
ma -X- _ O
PM -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
messenger -X- _ O
or -X- _ O
call -X- _ O
/ -X- _ O
text -X- _ O
ani -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
number -X- _ O
09637396116 -X- _ O

Tsk -X- _ O
tsk -X- _ O
tsk -X- _ O
... -X- _ O
looyas -X- _ O
mga -X- _ O
school -X- _ O
heads -X- _ O
... -X- _ O
disgrasya -X- _ O
going -X- _ O
to -X- _ O
Capipines -X- _ B-LOC
, -X- _ I-LOC
Bindoy -X- _ I-LOC
kay -X- _ O
na -X- _ O
tangtang -X- _ O
ang -X- _ O
ligid -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
karaang -X- _ O
sakyanan -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
LGU -X- _ B-ORG
! -X- _ O
Salamat -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
mga -X- _ O
ma -X- _ O
abtikon -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
Recue -X- _ O
Team..dali -X- _ O
ra -X- _ O
sila -X- _ O
nka -X- _ O
angat -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
bukid -X- _ O
kay -X- _ O
nindot -X- _ O
na -X- _ O
kaayo -X- _ O
ang -X- _ O
mga -X- _ O
karsada -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
kabukiran -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
Bindoy -X- _ B-LOC
! -X- _ O

MISSING -X- _ O
DOG -X- _ O
To -X- _ O
anyone -X- _ O
living -X- _ O
in -X- _ O
Taclobo -X- _ B-LOC
, -X- _ I-LOC
Bag-ong -X- _ I-LOC
Dalan -X- _ I-LOC
or -X- _ O
Purok -X- _ B-LOC
Santan -X- _ I-LOC
Area. -X- _ O
Please -X- _ O
see -X- _ O
below -X- _ O
a -X- _ O
photo -X- _ O
of -X- _ O
our -X- _ O
missing -X- _ O
dog. -X- _ O
A -X- _ O
simple -X- _ O
share -X- _ O
to -X- _ O
this -X- _ O
post -X- _ O
can -X- _ O
go -X- _ O
a -X- _ O
long -X- _ O
way -X- _ O
, -X- _ O
please -X- _ O
help -X- _ O
us -X- _ O
bring -X- _ O
our -X- _ O
boy -X- _ O
home. -X- _ O
Thank -X- _ O
you -X- _ O
! -X- _ O
Name -X- _ O
: -X- _ O
Adbin -X- _ B-MISC
Breed -X- _ O
: -X- _ O
Shitzu -X- _ B-MISC
Color -X- _ O
: -X- _ O
Tricolor -X- _ O
( -X- _ O
white -X- _ O
, -X- _ O
brown -X- _ O
, -X- _ O
black -X- _ O
) -X- _ O
Collar -X- _ O
: -X- _ O
SANDUGO -X- _ O
Nakagawas -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
gate -X- _ O
around -X- _ O
2pm -X- _ O
Saturday -X- _ O
May -X- _ O
13 -X- _ O
, -X- _ O
then -X- _ O
nidalagan -X- _ O
diretso -X- _ O
paguwas -X- _ O
wala -X- _ O
na -X- _ O
nasundan -X- _ O
last -X- _ O
seen -X- _ O
Crossing -X- _ B-LOC
Taclobo -X- _ I-LOC
area. -X- _ O
Basin -X- _ O
naay -X- _ O
makakita -X- _ O
please -X- _ O
mi -X- _ O
help -X- _ O
kay -X- _ O
naguol -X- _ O
na -X- _ O
among -X- _ O
lola -X- _ O
pinangita -X- _ O
palangga -X- _ O
kaayo -X- _ O
to -X- _ O
niya. -X- _ O
Muhatag -X- _ O
lang -X- _ O
mi -X- _ O
ug -X- _ O
gamayng -X- _ O
pahalipay -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
makakita -X- _ O
or -X- _ O
makauli -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
among -X- _ O
dog. -X- _ O
Please -X- _ O
contact -X- _ O
09154156973 -X- _ O
or -X- _ O
09354448371 -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
mga -X- _ O
naay -X- _ O
info. -X- _ O
Salamat -X- _ O
admins -X- _ O
ug -X- _ O
salamat -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
tanan -X- _ O
mag -X- _ O
share. -X- _ O
Godbless -X- _ O
! -X- _ O

For -X- _ O
further -X- _ O
education -X- _ O
para -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
atung -X- _ O
mga -X- _ O
instant -X- _ O
disensya -X- _ O
dire -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
Dumaguete -X- _ B-LOC
city -X- _ I-LOC
. -X- _ O

Hello -X- _ O
Ma'am -X- _ O
/ -X- _ O
Sir -X- _ O
good -X- _ O
evening. -X- _ O
Hangyo -X- _ O
langko -X- _ O
daan -X- _ O
na -X- _ O
ianonymous -X- _ O
ra -X- _ O
ko. -X- _ O
Unhan -X- _ O
na -X- _ O
nako -X- _ O
daan -X- _ O
ang -X- _ O
tanan -X- _ O
, -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
DILI -X- _ O
NI -X- _ O
PANGDAOT -X- _ O
, -X- _ O
KUNDI -X- _ O
PARA -X- _ O
MA -X- _ O
AWARE -X- _ O
MO -X- _ O
DIHA -X- _ O
TANAN. -X- _ O
Kay -X- _ O
bisan -X- _ O
pag -X- _ O
unsa -X- _ O
mo -X- _ O
ka -X- _ O
busy -X- _ O
diha -X- _ O
, -X- _ O
inyoha -X- _ O
gihapon -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
OBLIGASYON -X- _ O
na -X- _ O
ipabiling -X- _ O
LIMPYO -X- _ O
ang -X- _ O
inyong -X- _ O
ginabaligya. -X- _ O
So -X- _ O
maoto -X- _ O
, -X- _ O
pa -X- _ O
shout -X- _ O
out -X- _ O
lang -X- _ O
unta -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
TANANG -X- _ O
namaligya -X- _ O
ug -X- _ O
GINABOT -X- _ O
diha -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
CHEESE -X- _ B-LOC
STICK -X- _ I-LOC
COUNTRY -X- _ I-LOC
na -X- _ O
unta -X- _ O
ilang -X- _ O
icheck -X- _ O
kanunay -X- _ O
ilang -X- _ O
stante -X- _ O
/ -X- _ O
sulodlan -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
ilang -X- _ O
mga -X- _ O
baligya. -X- _ O
Kay -X- _ O
diha -X- _ O
mi -X- _ O
ganiha -X- _ O
, -X- _ O
unya -X- _ O
diay -X- _ O
DAKO -X- _ O
KAAYONG -X- _ O
LAGONG -X- _ O
ang -X- _ O
ga -X- _ O
hinambid -X- _ O
sulod -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
stante. -X- _ O
Sure -X- _ O
gyud -X- _ O
ko -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
ganiha -X- _ O
ra -X- _ O
naa -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
sulod -X- _ O
ang -X- _ O
maong -X- _ O
LAGONG -X- _ O
kay -X- _ O
ang -X- _ O
GINABOT -X- _ O
na -X- _ O
ITLOGAN -X- _ O
NA -X- _ O
SA -X- _ O
LAGONG. -X- _ O
Clear -X- _ O
kaayo -X- _ O
ang -X- _ O
glass -X- _ O
, -X- _ O
so -X- _ O
klaro -X- _ O
kaayo -X- _ O
gyud -X- _ O
ang -X- _ O
itlog -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
LAGONG. -X- _ O
Sa -X- _ O
wa -X- _ O
kaila -X- _ O
unsay -X- _ O
LAGONG -X- _ O
, -X- _ O
ANTYKUL -X- _ O
na -X- _ O
sya -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
LANGAW. -X- _ O
Before -X- _ O
diay -X- _ O
namo -X- _ O
nakit -X- _ O
an -X- _ O
ang -X- _ O
itlog -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
maong -X- _ O
LAGONG -X- _ O
, -X- _ O
amo -X- _ O
diay -X- _ O
giingnan -X- _ O
ang -X- _ O
tindera -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
naay -X- _ O
LAGONG -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
sulod. -X- _ O
Din -X- _ O
while -X- _ O
ga -X- _ O
duha2 -X- _ O
nami -X- _ O
mo -X- _ O
order -X- _ O
, -X- _ O
usa -X- _ O
pa -X- _ O
namo -X- _ O
nakit -X- _ O
an -X- _ O
ang -X- _ O
ITLOG -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
LAGONG -X- _ O
ug -X- _ O
wala -X- _ O
nagyud -X- _ O
mi -X- _ O
nidayun. -X- _ O
Nilakaw -X- _ O
mi -X- _ O
, -X- _ O
ng -X- _ O
tuyok -X- _ O
para -X- _ O
d -X- _ O
ra -X- _ O
kaayo -X- _ O
insulto -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
ilaha. -X- _ O
Didto -X- _ O
nami -X- _ O
gawas -X- _ O
balik -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
may -X- _ O
Silliman -X- _ B-LOC
Beach -X- _ I-LOC
na -X- _ O
kalsada -X- _ O
, -X- _ O
so -X- _ O
ky -X- _ O
ganahan -X- _ O
man -X- _ O
ko -X- _ O
mukaon -X- _ O
gyud -X- _ O
ug -X- _ O
GINABOT -X- _ O
inspite -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
among -X- _ O
nakita. -X- _ O
Nangeta -X- _ O
mig -X- _ O
laing -X- _ O
stall -X- _ O
, -X- _ O
so -X- _ O
ddto -X- _ O
nasab -X- _ O
mi -X- _ O
, -X- _ O
BTW -X- _ O
tag -X- _ O
35 -X- _ O
diay -X- _ O
to -X- _ O
ilang -X- _ O
GINABOT. -X- _ O
Unya -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
2nd -X- _ O
attempt -X- _ O
namo -X- _ O
na -X- _ O
mo -X- _ O
order -X- _ O
ug -X- _ O
GINABOT -X- _ O
tag -X- _ O
35 -X- _ O
gihapon -X- _ O
, -X- _ O
PASTILAN -X- _ O
! -X- _ O
! -X- _ O
! -X- _ O
Tua -X- _ O
naman -X- _ O
say -X- _ O
LAGONG -X- _ O
, -X- _ O
ga -X- _ O
kiss -X- _ O
kiss -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
GINABOT. -X- _ O
Maoto -X- _ O
wa -X- _ O
nalang -X- _ O
ko -X- _ O
namuyag -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
ga -X- _ O
bantay -X- _ O
ky -X- _ O
naa -X- _ O
raba -X- _ O
syay -X- _ O
laing -X- _ O
costumer -X- _ O
, -X- _ O
basin -X- _ O
unyag -X- _ O
lainon -X- _ O
niyag -X- _ O
sabot. -X- _ O
So -X- _ O
wa -X- _ O
mi -X- _ O
nidayun -X- _ O
, -X- _ O
manguli -X- _ O
na -X- _ O
unta -X- _ O
mi. -X- _ O
Pero -X- _ O
ky -X- _ O
sayang -X- _ O
manpud -X- _ O
, -X- _ O
naa -X- _ O
na -X- _ O
mis -X- _ O
area -X- _ O
unya -X- _ O
d -X- _ O
mi -X- _ O
kakaog -X- _ O
GINABOT -X- _ O
so -X- _ O
nangeta -X- _ O
nasab -X- _ O
mig -X- _ O
laing -X- _ O
stall. -X- _ O
And -X- _ O
napunta -X- _ O
mi -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
tag -X- _ O
50 -X- _ O
, -X- _ O
ug -X- _ O
THANKS -X- _ O
G -X- _ O
WALAY -X- _ O
LAGONG. -X- _ O
Ga -X- _ O
joke-kay -X- _ O
pa -X- _ O
mi -X- _ O
na -X- _ O
" -X- _ O
d -X- _ O
lagi -X- _ O
ta -X- _ O
papaliton -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
tag -X- _ O
35 -X- _ O
ky -X- _ O
naay -X- _ O
libreng -X- _ O
LAGONG -X- _ O
diria -X- _ O
lagi -X- _ O
ta -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
tag -X- _ O
50 -X- _ O
ky -X- _ O
wala. -X- _ O
" -X- _ O
" -X- _ O
Wala -X- _ O
lang -X- _ O
ta -X- _ O
kakita -X- _ O
pero -X- _ O
gikataw -X- _ O
an -X- _ O
na -X- _ O
diay -X- _ O
ta -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
LAGONG -X- _ O
, -X- _ O
ky -X- _ O
diria -X- _ O
na -X- _ O
sya -X- _ O
gikan. -X- _ O
" -X- _ O
So -X- _ O
maoto -X- _ O
, -X- _ O
NAKAKAON -X- _ O
RA -X- _ O
BIYA -X- _ O
GYUD -X- _ O
TAWUN -X- _ O
MIG -X- _ O
GINABOT. -X- _ O
Unya -X- _ O
kay -X- _ O
kaning -X- _ O
nakakita -X- _ O
na -X- _ O
ta -X- _ O
daan -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
naay -X- _ O
GINABOT -X- _ O
g -X- _ O
itlogan -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
LAGONG -X- _ O
ga -X- _ O
hinay2 -X- _ O
nalang -X- _ O
pudkog -X- _ O
kaon -X- _ O
, -X- _ O
so -X- _ O
far -X- _ O
LAMI -X- _ O
RAMAN -X- _ O
SAB. -X- _ O
Mga -X- _ O
MAMSER -X- _ O
, -X- _ O
PLEASE -X- _ O
LANG -X- _ O
PUD -X- _ O
ICHECK -X- _ O
NINYO -X- _ O
KANUNAY -X- _ O
INYONG -X- _ O
STANTE. -X- _ O
PLEASE -X- _ O
, -X- _ O
ALAYON -X- _ O
. -X- _ O

Amin -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
dire -X- _ O
bi. -X- _ O
Aldrinne -X- _ O
Ferrer -X- _ O

Towing -X- _ O
nalang -X- _ O
juy -X- _ O
kulang -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
Dumaguete -X- _ B-LOC
. -X- _ O

Dile -X- _ O
raman -X- _ O
traffic -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
Dumaguete. -X- _ B-LOC
Ryly -X- _ O
Dre -X- _ O
Pontino -X- _ O

Amping -X- _ O
jud -X- _ O
kanunay -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
pagdrive -X- _ O
especially -X- _ O
pa -X- _ O
angat -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
dalan -X- _ O
. -X- _ O

Wa -X- _ O
man -X- _ O
jud -X- _ O
ga -X- _ O
huna -X- _ O
huna -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
uban. -X- _ O
Dako -X- _ O
raba -X- _ O
kaau -X- _ O
ug -X- _ O
sakyanan. -X- _ O
" -X- _ O
Kuyawa -X- _ O
jd -X- _ O
nila -X- _ O
mamalit -X- _ O
ug -X- _ O
coke -X- _ B-MISC
kay -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
tunga -X- _ O
mans -X- _ O
dalan -X- _ O
" -X- _ O

BREAKING -X- _ O
: -X- _ O
Sunog -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
usa -X- _ O
ka -X- _ O
bodega -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
Bantayan -X- _ B-LOC
, -X- _ I-LOC
Dumaguete -X- _ I-LOC
CityGrafe -X- _ I-LOC
Bear -X- _ O

DENR -X- _ B-ORG
sa -X- _ O
Negros -X- _ B-LOC
? -X- _ O

Congrats -X- _ O
trending -X- _ O
najud -X- _ O
ang -X- _ O
Dumaguete -X- _ B-LOC
city -X- _ I-LOC
! -X- _ O
! -X- _ O
Well -X- _ O
known -X- _ O
najud -X- _ O
ang -X- _ O
ka -X- _ O
maau -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
atung -X- _ O
systema -X- _ O
aning -X- _ O
shudad. -X- _ O
But -X- _ O
bale -X- _ O
wala -X- _ O
rajapon -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
atung -X- _ O
mga -X- _ O
LGU -X- _ B-ORG
, -X- _ O
people -X- _ O
encharge. -X- _ O
Little -X- _ O
by -X- _ O
little -X- _ O
the -X- _ O
name -X- _ O
Dumaguete -X- _ B-LOC
city -X- _ I-LOC
will -X- _ O
slowly -X- _ O
be -X- _ O
known -X- _ O
as -X- _ O
not -X- _ O
of -X- _ O
the -X- _ O
gentle -X- _ O
people -X- _ O
but -X- _ O
something -X- _ O
else. -X- _ O
PANTALAN -X- _ B-LOC
SA -X- _ I-LOC
DUMAGUETE -X- _ I-LOC
CITY -X- _ I-LOC
, -X- _ O
DAGHANG -X- _ O
FIXER -X- _ O
, -X- _ O
GIREKLAMO -X- _ O
SA -X- _ O
PASAHEROMga -X- _ O
pasahero -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
mo -X- _ O
lukat -X- _ O
ug -X- _ O
ticket -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
pantalan -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
Dumaguete -X- _ B-LOC
City -X- _ I-LOC
, -X- _ O
nag -X- _ O
reklamo -X- _ O
kay -X- _ O
sige -X- _ O
lang -X- _ O
ka -X- _ O
Fully -X- _ O
Book -X- _ O
pero -X- _ O
matod -X- _ O
pa -X- _ O
daghang -X- _ O
fixer -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
palibot -X- _ O
nag -X- _ O
laroy-laroy -X- _ O
ug -X- _ O
mo -X- _ O
tanyag -X- _ O
pero -X- _ O
mahal -X- _ O
na -X- _ O
ang -X- _ O
ticket -X- _ O
. -X- _ O

Uwako -X- _ O
kaya -X- _ O
papi -X- _ O
! -X- _ O

Joke -X- _ O
kaau -X- _ O
ning -X- _ O
ilang -X- _ O
signage. -X- _ O
But -X- _ O
at -X- _ O
the -X- _ O
same -X- _ O
time -X- _ O
obstacle -X- _ O
nas -X- _ O
4 -X- _ O
lane -X- _ O
highway -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
delicado -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
mga -X- _ O
riders. -X- _ O
good -X- _ O
morning -X- _ O
, -X- _ O
can -X- _ O
you -X- _ O
post -X- _ O
this -X- _ O
one -X- _ O
to -X- _ O
address -X- _ O
the -X- _ O
law -X- _ O
in -X- _ O
forces -X- _ O
about -X- _ O
ani -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
sign -X- _ O
na -X- _ O
gi -X- _ O
butang -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
outer -X- _ O
lane -X- _ O
dirs -X- _ O
diversion -X- _ B-LOC
road -X- _ I-LOC
batinguel -X- _ B-LOC
to -X- _ O
camanjac.. -X- _ B-LOC
thank -X- _ O
you -X- _ O

Kung -X- _ O
hugawan -X- _ O
mos -X- _ O
mga -X- _ O
spagetti -X- _ O
wires -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
mga -X- _ O
poste -X- _ O
huna-huna -X- _ O
nalang -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
inter-dimension -X- _ O
nang -X- _ O
kada -X- _ O
linya. -X- _ O
Art -X- _ O
from -X- _ O
Alex -X- _ O
Hyner -X- _ O

Ing.ani -X- _ O
ra -X- _ O
diay -X- _ O
pag -X- _ O
gama -X- _ O
ug -X- _ O
katol -X- _ O
ka -X- _ O
daghan -X- _ O
man -X- _ O
aning -X- _ O
tanoma -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
mga -X- _ O
kilid -X- _ O
kilid -X- _ O
. -X- _ O

Di -X- _ O
mag -X- _ O
dugay -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
ang -X- _ O
kahoi -X- _ O
ma -X- _ O
himo -X- _ O
nalang -X- _ O
og -X- _ O
thing -X- _ O
of -X- _ O
the -X- _ O
past. -X- _ O
With -X- _ O
all -X- _ O
the -X- _ O
development -X- _ O
that -X- _ O
is -X- _ O
going -X- _ O
on -X- _ O
and -X- _ O
the -X- _ O
quarry -X- _ O
around -X- _ O
Negros -X- _ B-LOC
Oriental -X- _ I-LOC
unsa -X- _ O
nalang -X- _ O
kaha -X- _ O
ma -X- _ O
abtan -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
atung -X- _ O
mga -X- _ O
bata -X- _ O
if -X- _ O
we -X- _ O
still -X- _ O
do -X- _ O
nothing -X- _ O
. -X- _ O

We -X- _ O
need -X- _ O
more -X- _ O
entrapment -X- _ O
like -X- _ O
these -X- _ O
especially -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
Dumaguete -X- _ B-LOC
city. -X- _ I-LOC
Kay -X- _ O
murag -X- _ O
ubay -X- _ O
ubay -X- _ O
kaau -X- _ O
dire -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
atung -X- _ O
nasod -X- _ O
. -X- _ O

Ay -X- _ O
hala -X- _ O
ang -X- _ O
mga -X- _ O
kuan -X- _ O
nawala -X- _ O
! -X- _ O

Gina -X- _ O
gamit -X- _ O
man -X- _ O
last -X- _ O
minute -X- _ O
lang -X- _ O
. -X- _ O

TAN-AWA -X- _ O
: -X- _ O
Isda -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
trap -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
linaw -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
Shoreline -X- _ O
Protection -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
Tinago -X- _ B-LOC
, -X- _ I-LOC
Dumaguete -X- _ I-LOC
, -X- _ O
nanggawas -X- _ O
na -X- _ O
, -X- _ O
pipila -X- _ O
ka -X- _ O
mga -X- _ O
lumolopyo -X- _ O
namulot -X- _ O
nalang -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
isdaVIA -X- _ O
Radyo -X- _ O
Bandera -X- _ O
Dumaguete -X- _ O
97.7 -X- _ O
Sweet -X- _ O
FM -X- _ O

Im -X- _ O
sending -X- _ O
you -X- _ O
some.photos -X- _ O
of -X- _ O
fish -X- _ O
killing -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
tinago -X- _ B-LOC
. -X- _ O
Na -X- _ O
trap -X- _ O
ang -X- _ O
mga -X- _ O
isda. -X- _ O
Gipangkuha -X- _ O
sa.mga -X- _ O
tawo -X- _ O
and -X- _ O
not -X- _ O
sure -X- _ O
of -X- _ O
na -X- _ O
poison. -X- _ O
Pero -X- _ O
it -X- _ O
seem -X- _ O
wala -X- _ O
sila -X- _ O
oxygen -X- _ O
kay -X- _ O
gisira -X- _ O
na -X- _ O
ang -X- _ O
opening -X- _ O
dapit -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
banica -X- _ B-LOC
to -X- _ O
connect -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
bridge -X- _ O
. -X- _ O

hello -X- _ O
good -X- _ O
day -X- _ O
ma'am -X- _ O
/ -X- _ O
sir -X- _ O
! -X- _ O
ganahan -X- _ O
ra -X- _ O
unta -X- _ O
ko -X- _ O
hatagan -X- _ O
ug -X- _ O
attention -X- _ O
ng -X- _ O
mga -X- _ O
V-hire -X- _ B-MISC
diri -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
negros -X- _ B-LOC
kay -X- _ O
grabi -X- _ O
ka -X- _ O
abusado -X- _ O
na. -X- _ O
Kusog -X- _ O
kaayo -X- _ O
mag -X- _ O
padagan -X- _ O
ug -X- _ O
overtake -X- _ O
dayon -X- _ O
himan -X- _ O
himan -X- _ O
mupadaplin -X- _ O
way -X- _ O
signal -X- _ O
kay -X- _ O
mukuha -X- _ O
diay -X- _ O
ug -X- _ O
pasahero. -X- _ O
Dayon -X- _ O
grabi -X- _ O
kaayo -X- _ O
makabusina -X- _ O
murag -X- _ O
tag-iya -X- _ O
na -X- _ O
ug -X- _ O
dalan. -X- _ O
mahal -X- _ O
na -X- _ O
gani -X- _ O
plete -X- _ O
dayon -X- _ O
walay -X- _ O
assurance -X- _ O
imong -X- _ O
kinabuhi -X- _ O
if -X- _ O
musakay -X- _ O
ka -X- _ O
ana -X- _ O
nila -X- _ O
tungod -X- _ O
ana -X- _ O
ilang -X- _ O
style -X- _ O
mag -X- _ O
padagan. -X- _ O
grabi -X- _ O
na -X- _ O
jd. -X- _ O
Please -X- _ O
lang -X- _ O
ko -X- _ O
ayaw -X- _ O
ra -X- _ O
ipost -X- _ O
ako -X- _ O
name. -X- _ O
thank -X- _ O
you -X- _ O

Oi -X- _ O
finally -X- _ O
ang -X- _ O
dalan -X- _ O
na -X- _ O
maka -X- _ O
guba -X- _ O
ug -X- _ O
gugma -X- _ O
gi -X- _ O
guba -X- _ O
na -X- _ O
! -X- _ O

Bali -X- _ O
rabang -X- _ O
lamia -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
crispy -X- _ B-LOC
king -X- _ I-LOC
baaa -X- _ O
. -X- _ O

We -X- _ O
all -X- _ O
know -X- _ O
najud -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
nay -X- _ O
bahin -X- _ O
ang -X- _ O
kada -X- _ O
usa -X- _ O
ani -X- _ O
nila. -X- _ O
Mau -X- _ O
nang -X- _ O
wala -X- _ O
juy -X- _ O
klaro -X- _ O
ang -X- _ O
systema -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
Dumaguete -X- _ B-LOC
port. -X- _ I-LOC
We -X- _ O
are -X- _ O
progressive -X- _ O
daw -X- _ O
as -X- _ O
a -X- _ O
city -X- _ O
but -X- _ O
as -X- _ O
locals -X- _ O
we -X- _ O
all -X- _ O
know -X- _ O
that -X- _ O
those -X- _ O
are -X- _ O
just -X- _ O
BS. -X- _ O
Daghan -X- _ O
kaau -X- _ O
major -X- _ O
problem -X- _ O
ang -X- _ O
Dumaguete -X- _ B-LOC
nga -X- _ O
gi -X- _ O
bale -X- _ O
wala -X- _ O
ra. -X- _ O
Sad -X- _ O
part -X- _ O
is -X- _ O
kita -X- _ O
pajud -X- _ O
ga -X- _ O
bayad -X- _ O
ug -X- _ O
Tax -X- _ O
. -X- _ O

basin -X- _ O
naay -X- _ O
makakita -X- _ O
ani -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
puppy -X- _ O
7 -X- _ O
mos -X- _ O
old. -X- _ O
shitzu. -X- _ B-MISC
or -X- _ O
naa -X- _ O
ibaligya. -X- _ O
pls -X- _ O
palihug -X- _ O
ko -X- _ O
pm -X- _ O
Kay -X- _ O
gikawat -X- _ O
amoa -X- _ O
puppy -X- _ O
iya -X- _ O
me -X- _ O
snowball..sa -X- _ B-MISC
ako -X- _ O
intawon -X- _ O
to -X- _ O
son -X- _ O
8 -X- _ O
yrs -X- _ O
old. -X- _ O
cge -X- _ O
sya -X- _ O
bulong. -X- _ O
ug -X- _ O
hilak -X- _ O
. -X- _ O

Sa -X- _ O
atung -X- _ O
mga -X- _ O
friends -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
ga -X- _ O
plan -X- _ O
mu -X- _ O
travel -X- _ O
via -X- _ O
Dumaguete -X- _ B-LOC
port -X- _ I-LOC
good -X- _ O
luck -X- _ O
nalang -X- _ O
ninyu -X- _ O
diha. -X- _ O
Until -X- _ O
now -X- _ O
it -X- _ O
's -X- _ O
the -X- _ O
same -X- _ O
dump -X- _ O
as -X- _ O
it -X- _ O
was -X- _ O
before. -X- _ O
Maau -X- _ O
ra -X- _ O
mag -X- _ O
pa -X- _ O
press -X- _ O
briefing -X- _ O
na -X- _ O
sila -X- _ O
then -X- _ O
back -X- _ O
to -X- _ O
its -X- _ O
old -X- _ O
corrupt -X- _ O
self -X- _ O
. -X- _ O

Murag -X- _ O
sauna -X- _ O
raman -X- _ O
ning -X- _ O
problemaha -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
pantalan -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
Dumaguete -X- _ B-LOC
kada -X- _ O
summer -X- _ O
ingon -X- _ O
ani -X- _ O
ang -X- _ O
problema -X- _ O
. -X- _ O

" -X- _ O
Hi -X- _ O
admin -X- _ O
basin -X- _ O
you -X- _ O
have -X- _ O
information -X- _ O
or -X- _ O
name -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
person -X- _ O
incharge -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
highway -X- _ O
and -X- _ O
safety -X- _ O
construction -X- _ O
dire -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
Sibulan -X- _ B-LOC
area -X- _ O
para -X- _ O
ma -X- _ O
address -X- _ O
namo -X- _ O
personally -X- _ O
ang -X- _ O
amung -X- _ O
mga -X- _ O
concern -X- _ O
regarding -X- _ O
ignoring -X- _ O
public -X- _ O
safety -X- _ O
aning -X- _ O
mga -X- _ O
roads -X- _ O
signs -X- _ O
ug -X- _ O
non -X- _ O
existing -X- _ O
early -X- _ O
warning -X- _ O
devices -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
road -X- _ O
construction -X- _ O
? -X- _ O
" -X- _ O

Wala -X- _ O
najud -X- _ O
tingale -X- _ O
kausuban -X- _ O
no -X- _ O
? -X- _ O
Unless -X- _ O
dato -X- _ O
ka -X- _ O
priority -X- _ O
ka -X- _ O
! -X- _ O
Capitalism -X- _ O
! -X- _ O
A -X- _ O
friendly -X- _ O
reminder -X- _ O
lang -X- _ O
since -X- _ O
wala -X- _ O
namay -X- _ O
mga -X- _ O
canopy -X- _ O
nya -X- _ O
super -X- _ O
duper -X- _ O
init -X- _ O
ang -X- _ O
panahon -X- _ O
likay -X- _ O
nalang -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
heat -X- _ O
stroke. -X- _ O
Good -X- _ O
luck -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
mga -X- _ O
tourista -X- _ O
ani -X- _ O

" -X- _ O
concerning -X- _ O
anang -X- _ O
walay -X- _ O
suga -X- _ O
ninyu -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
post -X- _ O
here -X- _ O
is -X- _ O
one -X- _ O
coming -X- _ O
from -X- _ O
the -X- _ O
most -X- _ O
notorious -X- _ O
contractors -X- _ O
when -X- _ O
it -X- _ O
comes -X- _ O
to -X- _ O
ignoring -X- _ O
the -X- _ O
safety -X- _ O
policy -X- _ O
when -X- _ O
constructing -X- _ O
roads -X- _ O
and -X- _ O
highways. -X- _ O
Gi -X- _ O
unsa -X- _ O
kaha -X- _ O
ni -X- _ O
pag -X- _ O
pasar -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
DPWH -X- _ B-ORG
naka -X- _ O
dawat -X- _ O
na -X- _ O
tingale -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
dugay -X- _ O
naman -X- _ O
ning -X- _ O
gina -X- _ O
ignore. -X- _ O
Walay -X- _ O
pay -X- _ O
street -X- _ O
light -X- _ O
wala -X- _ O
pajuy -X- _ O
tarong -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
reflector -X- _ O
! -X- _ O
No -X- _ O
warning -X- _ O
lights -X- _ O
meters -X- _ O
away -X- _ O
from -X- _ O
the -X- _ O
pile -X- _ O
up -X- _ O
and -X- _ O
its -X- _ O
been -X- _ O
months -X- _ O
since -X- _ O
na -X- _ O
kalimtan -X- _ O
ra -X- _ O
ni. -X- _ O
Maygane -X- _ O
wala -X- _ O
pay -X- _ O
na -X- _ O
accidente -X- _ O
kay -X- _ O
diha -X- _ O
pa -X- _ O
nila -X- _ O
e -X- _ O
lihok. -X- _ O
Plus -X- _ O
ingon -X- _ O
daun -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
sala -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
driver -X- _ O
kay -X- _ O
kusug -X- _ O
kaau. -X- _ O
Tisk -X- _ O
! -X- _ O
please -X- _ O
share -X- _ O
for -X- _ O
awareness. -X- _ O
" -X- _ O
Located -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
Looc -X- _ B-LOC
Sibulan -X- _ I-LOC
pasulod -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
quarry -X- _ O
sight -X- _ O
. -X- _ O

basin -X- _ O
naay -X- _ O
nakaila -X- _ O
ani -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
iro..didto -X- _ O
ni -X- _ O
gabie -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
boulevard -X- _ B-LOC
nagka -X- _ O
pangka2x -X- _ O
tawun -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
mga -X- _ O
bato -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
baybay -X- _ O
dapit -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
pantawan -X- _ B-LOC
kay -X- _ O
balod..naa -X- _ O
cya -X- _ O
karon -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
police -X- _ O
station -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
dumaguete..luoy -X- _ B-LOC
kaayo.. -X- _ O

Hi -X- _ O
admin -X- _ O
nakita -X- _ O
ko -X- _ O
earlier -X- _ O
today -X- _ O
and -X- _ O
was -X- _ O
just -X- _ O
wondering -X- _ O
gi -X- _ O
unsa -X- _ O
ni -X- _ O
pag -X- _ O
lusot -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
mga -X- _ O
check -X- _ O
point -X- _ O
? -X- _ O
No -X- _ O
lights -X- _ O
nya -X- _ O
ga -X- _ O
dagan -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
dulom -X- _ O
mejo -X- _ O
delikado -X- _ O
jud -X- _ O
kaau -X- _ O
para -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
mga -X- _ O
motorista -X- _ O
dire -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
Dumaguete. -X- _ B-LOC
Unsay -X- _ O
may -X- _ O
purpose -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
mga -X- _ O
police -X- _ O
kung -X- _ O
dile -X- _ O
nila -X- _ O
ma -X- _ O
uphold -X- _ O
ang -X- _ O
mga -X- _ O
balaod -X- _ O
? -X- _ O
Di -X- _ O
pod -X- _ O
kay -X- _ O
e -X- _ O
pasa -X- _ O
nato -X- _ O
nis -X- _ O
traffic -X- _ O
ug -X- _ O
highway -X- _ O
patrol -X- _ O
na -X- _ O
mas -X- _ O
daghan -X- _ O
paman -X- _ O
ug -X- _ O
police -X- _ O
. -X- _ O

Ang -X- _ O
dagat -X- _ O
nato -X- _ O
dire -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
Negros -X- _ B-LOC
hapit -X- _ O
napod -X- _ O
ma -X- _ O
parehas -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
ning -X- _ O
pictures -X- _ O
. -X- _ O

Naka -X- _ O
xerox -X- _ B-MISC
naba -X- _ O
tanan -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
ilang -X- _ O
disensya -X- _ O
? -X- _ O

Hi -X- _ O
admin -X- _ O
unsay -X- _ O
policy -X- _ O
kung -X- _ O
nay -X- _ O
sakyanan -X- _ O
mag -X- _ O
dagan -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
dalan -X- _ O
kusug -X- _ O
but -X- _ O
wala -X- _ O
gapa -X- _ O
suga -X- _ O
? -X- _ O
Murag -X- _ O
unsafe -X- _ O
man -X- _ O
para -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
publico -X- _ O
admin -X- _ O
. -X- _ O

Temporaryo -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
iisyu -X- _ O
ang -X- _ O
maong -X- _ O
papel -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
mga -X- _ O
aplikante -X- _ O
samtang -X- _ O
naglisod -X- _ O
pa -X- _ O
ang -X- _ O
Land -X- _ B-ORG
Transportation -X- _ I-ORG
Office -X- _ I-ORG
( -X- _ O
LTO -X- _ B-ORG
) -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
supply -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
plastic -X- _ O
cards.Sumala -X- _ O
pa -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
LTO -X- _ B-ORG
, -X- _ O
anaa -X- _ O
lang -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
147,000 -X- _ O
ka -X- _ O
plastic -X- _ O
cards -X- _ O
ang -X- _ O
anaa -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
tibuok -X- _ O
nasud. -X- _ O
Ug -X- _ O
mahimo -X- _ O
kining -X- _ O
hangtod -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
katapusan -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
Abril.via -X- _ O
ABS-CBN -X- _ O
News -X- _ O

A -X- _ O
friendly -X- _ O
reminder -X- _ O
unta -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
di -X- _ O
ta -X- _ O
ma -X- _ O
wad.an -X- _ O
ug -X- _ O
common -X- _ O
sense. -X- _ O
Ang -X- _ O
motor -X- _ O
is -X- _ O
the -X- _ O
most -X- _ O
convenient -X- _ O
vehicle -X- _ O
to -X- _ O
park. -X- _ O
Dali -X- _ O
rajud -X- _ O
e -X- _ O
parking -X- _ O
and -X- _ O
efficient -X- _ O
kaau -X- _ O
, -X- _ O
compara -X- _ O
mo -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
mga -X- _ O
4 -X- _ O
wheels -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
baling -X- _ O
kapoya -X- _ O
e -X- _ O
parking -X- _ O
jud -X- _ O
tuod. -X- _ O
But -X- _ O
dile -X- _ O
jud -X- _ O
pod -X- _ O
ta -X- _ O
mag -X- _ O
tinapolan -X- _ O
ug -X- _ O
pagka -X- _ O
selfish -X- _ O
mo -X- _ O
parking -X- _ O
. -X- _ O

Ma -X- _ O
appreciate -X- _ O
jud -X- _ O
namo -X- _ O
nang -X- _ O
mga -X- _ O
batan.on -X- _ O
karon -X- _ O
panohona -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
kabalo -X- _ O
mag -X- _ O
hunu -X- _ O
huna -X- _ O
para -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
uban -X- _ O
. -X- _ O

Wala -X- _ O
nay -X- _ O
problema -X- _ O
ug -X- _ O
ice -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
Mabinay. -X- _ B-LOC
Ice -X- _ O
rain -X- _ O
in -X- _ O
Mabyinay -X- _ B-LOC
April -X- _ O
21,2023.Para -X- _ O
accurate -X- _ O
hail -X- _ O
storm -X- _ O
ni -X- _ O
siya -X- _ O
mini -X- _ O
version -X- _ O
lang. -X- _ O
Video -X- _ O
by -X- _ O
Jocadz -X- _ O
Zildac -X- _ O

Kusug -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
Ulan -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
ice -X- _ O
karon -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
Mabinay -X- _ B-LOC
April -X- _ O
21 -X- _ O
, -X- _ O
2023By -X- _ O
Miel -X- _ O
Paculanang -X- _ O

Di -X- _ O
nata -X- _ O
maka -X- _ O
kita -X- _ O
ug -X- _ O
ing.ani -X- _ O
karong -X- _ O
panahona. -X- _ O
Long -X- _ O
Horn -X- _ O
Carabao -X- _ O
's -X- _ O
, -X- _ O
PhilippinesCirca -X- _ B-LOC
1900 -X- _ O
's -X- _ O
- -X- _ O
1950'sImage -X- _ O
Ctto -X- _ O

Gwapo -X- _ O
ug -X- _ O
view -X- _ O
oy -X- _ O
kana -X- _ O
rang -X- _ O
no -X- _ O
parking -X- _ O
moy -X- _ O
samok. -X- _ O
Pila -X- _ O
kahay -X- _ O
timbang -X- _ O
ana -X- _ O
? -X- _ O

Bali -X- _ O
pong -X- _ O
klaruha -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
wala -X- _ O
najud -X- _ O
poy -X- _ O
sidewalk -X- _ O
na -X- _ O
bilin -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
style -X- _ O
ug -X- _ O
pag -X- _ O
park -X- _ O
mau -X- _ O
tingale -X- _ O
gipang -X- _ O
ticketan. -X- _ O
Ang -X- _ O
panhutana -X- _ O
naka -X- _ O
learn -X- _ O
naba -X- _ O
ug -X- _ O
lesson -X- _ O
ang -X- _ O
gi -X- _ O
ticketan -X- _ O
or -X- _ O
need -X- _ O
pajud -X- _ O
na -X- _ O
pa -X- _ O
impound -X- _ O
? -X- _ O
Luoy -X- _ O
kaau -X- _ O
atung -X- _ O
mga -X- _ O
tig -X- _ O
lakaw -X- _ O
dire -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
Dumaguete -X- _ B-LOC
wala -X- _ O
najuy -X- _ O
safe -X- _ O
way -X- _ O
or -X- _ O
convenient -X- _ O
way -X- _ O
of -X- _ O
walking -X- _ O
around -X- _ O
the -X- _ O
city -X- _ O
because -X- _ O
of -X- _ O
no -X- _ O
proper -X- _ O
sidewalk. -X- _ O
Na -X- _ O
himo -X- _ O
lang -X- _ O
ug -X- _ O
parkingan -X- _ O
tanan -X- _ O
! -X- _ O
Lupad -X- _ B-ORG
Dumaguete -X- _ I-ORG
dile -X- _ O
pod -X- _ O
mi -X- _ O
mang -X- _ O
lupad -X- _ O
lang -X- _ O
ani -X- _ O
tanan -X- _ O
? -X- _ O

Dire -X- _ O
Dumaguete -X- _ B-LOC
daghan -X- _ O
man -X- _ O
pod -X- _ O
tag -X- _ O
concern -X- _ O
wala -X- _ O
ra -X- _ O
gi -X- _ O
hatagan -X- _ O
ug -X- _ O
pag -X- _ O
tagad -X- _ O
. -X- _ O

# -X- _ O
dumasharesSir -X- _ O
pwd -X- _ O
pa -X- _ O
help. -X- _ O
Regarding -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
water -X- _ O
namo -X- _ O
dri -X- _ O
Motong -X- _ B-LOC
Dumaguete -X- _ I-LOC
City -X- _ I-LOC
. -X- _ O

Mangape -X- _ O
pagane -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
udto -X- _ O
? -X- _ O

Nay -X- _ O
puture -X- _ O
ning -X- _ O
bata.a -X- _ O
dah. -X- _ O
Better -X- _ O
then -X- _ O
most -X- _ O
auto -X- _ O
tuned -X- _ O
singers -X- _ O
. -X- _ O

LOOK -X- _ O
: -X- _ O
PATAY'NG -X- _ O
LAWAS -X- _ O
SA -X- _ O
LALAKI -X- _ O
NAKIT-AN -X- _ O
SA -X- _ O
TERMINAL -X- _ O
SA -X- _ O
PANTALAN -X- _ B-LOC
SA -X- _ I-LOC
DUMAGUETE -X- _ I-LOC
GIDALA -X- _ O
NA -X- _ O
SA -X- _ O
USA -X- _ O
KA -X- _ O
FUNERAL -X- _ O
PARLORGidala -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
usa -X- _ O
ka -X- _ O
funerral -X- _ O
parlor -X- _ O
ang -X- _ O
patay'ng -X- _ O
lalaki -X- _ O
taga -X- _ O
Mindanao -X- _ B-LOC
, -X- _ O
kinsa -X- _ O
nakit-an -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
bangko -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
natulog -X- _ O
sulod -X- _ O
terminal -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
Pantalan -X- _ B-LOC
sa -X- _ I-LOC
Dumaguete -X- _ I-LOC
karong -X- _ O
kadlawon -X- _ O
April -X- _ O
17,2023.Sa -X- _ O
initial -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
paksisusi -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
PNP -X- _ B-ORG
Dumaguete -X- _ I-ORG
nga -X- _ O
biktima -X- _ O
nailhan -X- _ O
lamang -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
pangalan -X- _ O
" -X- _ O
Haslik -X- _ B-MISC
" -X- _ O
hingkod -X- _ O
ang -X- _ O
panuigon.And -X- _ O
biktima -X- _ O
diha -X- _ O
kini -X- _ O
sulod -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
terminal -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
pantalan -X- _ B-LOC
sa -X- _ I-LOC
Dumaguete -X- _ I-LOC
naghulat -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
makasakay -X- _ O
barko -X- _ O
paingon -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
Dapitan -X- _ B-LOC
kinsa -X- _ O
molaraga -X- _ O
pagka -X- _ O
alas -X- _ O
7:00 -X- _ O
am -X- _ O
karong -X- _ O
buntag.Sa -X- _ O
dihang -X- _ O
gipukaw -X- _ O
kini -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
usa -X- _ O
lady -X- _ O
guard -X- _ O
wala -X- _ O
na -X- _ O
kini -X- _ O
molihok -X- _ O
og -X- _ O
nigahi -X- _ O
na -X- _ O
lawas -X- _ O
niini -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
naghigda -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
bangko -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
sulod -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
terminal.Basi -X- _ O
sugilanon -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
kauban -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
trabaho -X- _ O
niini -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
si -X- _ O
Danilo -X- _ B-PER
nga -X- _ O
gabii -X- _ O
nagkaon -X- _ O
kini -X- _ O
daghan -X- _ O
litson -X- _ O
dayon -X- _ O
nag-inom -X- _ O
kauban -X- _ O
kinininom -X- _ O
, -X- _ O
unya -X- _ O
nilakaw -X- _ O
kini -X- _ O
gabii -X- _ O
og -X- _ O
iya -X- _ O
nalang -X- _ O
nabal-an -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
namatay -X- _ O
na -X- _ O
karong -X- _ O
buntag.Ipahigayon -X- _ O
usab -X- _ O
ang -X- _ O
post -X- _ O
mortem -X- _ O
examination -X- _ O
kon -X- _ O
unsa -X- _ O
gayud -X- _ O
ang -X- _ O
namatyan -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
biktima -X- _ O
, -X- _ O
matud -X- _ O
pa -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
kapolisan.SGR -X- _ O
| -X- _ O
April -X- _ O
17 -X- _ O
, -X- _ O
2023Via -X- _ O
Radyo -X- _ O
Bandera -X- _ O
Dumaguete -X- _ O
sweet -X- _ O
fm -X- _ O

Gi -X- _ O
unsa -X- _ O
kaha -X- _ O
pag -X- _ O
pasar -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
safety -X- _ O
inspector -X- _ O
ani -X- _ O
da -X- _ O
dpwh -X- _ B-ORG
nga -X- _ O
gipasag-daan -X- _ O
raman -X- _ O
nila -X- _ O
ang -X- _ O
contractor -X- _ O
na -X- _ O
bale -X- _ O
wala -X- _ O
ra -X- _ O
ang -X- _ O
safety -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
publico. -X- _ O
Maaung -X- _ O
gabie -X- _ O
admin -X- _ O
hapit -X- _ O
mi -X- _ O
nang -X- _ O
lupad -X- _ O
to -X- _ O
Dumaguete -X- _ B-LOC
jud -X- _ O
ani -X- _ O
admin. -X- _ O
Walay -X- _ O
juy -X- _ O
bisag -X- _ O
usang -X- _ O
warning -X- _ O
sign -X- _ O
naka -X- _ O
butang -X- _ O
aning -X- _ O
gi -X- _ O
gubang -X- _ O
dalan -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
Sibulan. -X- _ B-LOC
Ga -X- _ O
hulat -X- _ O
ni -X- _ O
sila -X- _ O
nay -X- _ O
ma -X- _ O
accidente -X- _ O
? -X- _ O

Maaung -X- _ O
gabie -X- _ O
diha -X- _ O
! -X- _ O

Drivers -X- _ O
especially -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
4 -X- _ O
wheels -X- _ O
should -X- _ O
know -X- _ O
the -X- _ O
ethic -X- _ O
of -X- _ O
proper -X- _ O
driving -X- _ O
and -X- _ O
parking -X- _ O
especially -X- _ O
aning -X- _ O
very -X- _ O
small -X- _ O
city -X- _ O
of -X- _ O
Dumaguete.Good -X- _ B-LOC
afternoon -X- _ O
admin. -X- _ O
Basin -X- _ O
naa -X- _ O
nakaila -X- _ O
ani -X- _ O
na -X- _ O
sakyanan -X- _ O
? -X- _ O
Ganina -X- _ O
pami -X- _ O
mga -X- _ O
12 -X- _ O
ani -X- _ O
dili -X- _ O
mi -X- _ O
makagawas -X- _ O
. -X- _ O

Maypa -X- _ O
ipa -X- _ O
timbang -X- _ O
nalang -X- _ O
nang -X- _ O
no -X- _ O
parking -X- _ O
sign. -X- _ O
Wala -X- _ O
juy -X- _ O
justice -X- _ O
ang -X- _ O
tig -X- _ O
lakaw -X- _ O
lang -X- _ O
dire -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
Dumaguete -X- _ B-LOC
ila -X- _ O
rajud -X- _ O
gipang -X- _ O
priorities -X- _ O
ang -X- _ O
mga -X- _ O
naka -X- _ O
sakyanan. -X- _ O
Kung -X- _ O
pubri -X- _ O
ka -X- _ O
naa -X- _ O
rana -X- _ O
nimu -X- _ O
kung -X- _ O
ma -X- _ O
ligsan -X- _ O
ka -X- _ O
o -X- _ O
dile. -X- _ O
Nay -X- _ O
TMO -X- _ B-ORG
nay -X- _ O
Discipline -X- _ O
zone -X- _ O
wala -X- _ O
japoy -X- _ O
na -X- _ O
hitabo -X- _ O
motor -X- _ O
rajapoy -X- _ O
kaya -X- _ O
dakpon. -X- _ O
Hadlok -X- _ O
pod -X- _ O
silang -X- _ O
mayor -X- _ O
mamuyag -X- _ O
kay -X- _ O
basin -X- _ O
dile -X- _ O
supporta.an -X- _ O
next -X- _ O
election. -X- _ O
Wa -X- _ O
najuy -X- _ O
ayu -X- _ O
ning -X- _ O
Dumaguete -X- _ B-LOC
. -X- _ O

Wala -X- _ O
pagane -X- _ O
ang -X- _ O
pag -X- _ O
turn -X- _ O
overNAGKAYO -X- _ O
GIHAPONMao -X- _ O
kini -X- _ O
ang -X- _ O
kasamtangang -X- _ O
sitwasyon -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
sunog -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
miigo -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
usa -X- _ O
ka -X- _ O
high-rise -X- _ O
building -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
Barangay -X- _ B-LOC
Kasambagan -X- _ I-LOC
, -X- _ I-LOC
Cebu -X- _ I-LOC
City -X- _ I-LOC
alas -X- _ O
6:46 -X- _ O
p.m. -X- _ O
Biyernes -X- _ O
, -X- _ O
Abril -X- _ O
14 -X- _ O
, -X- _ O
2023. -X- _ O
Pagka -X- _ O
alas -X- _ O
4:38 -X- _ O
p.m. -X- _ O
Biyernes -X- _ O
, -X- _ O
giisa -X- _ O
ngadto -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
Task -X- _ B-MISC
Force -X- _ I-MISC
Bravo -X- _ I-MISC
ang -X- _ O
maong -X- _ O
sunog. -X- _ O
| -X- _ O
via -X- _ O
BBT -X- _ O

If -X- _ O
ever -X- _ O
naa -X- _ O
man -X- _ O
gani -X- _ O
nakakita -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
akong -X- _ O
IPhone -X- _ B-MISC
13 -X- _ O
dark -X- _ O
blue -X- _ O
ug -X- _ O
color. -X- _ O
Please -X- _ O
ko -X- _ O
contact -X- _ O
ani -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
number -X- _ O
09759658480. -X- _ O
Mu -X- _ O
hatag -X- _ O
rami -X- _ O
ug -X- _ O
gamay -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
pahalipay -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
makakita. -X- _ O
Please -X- _ O
ko -X- _ O
help -X- _ O
guys -X- _ O
kay -X- _ O
naa -X- _ O
ddto -X- _ O
ang -X- _ O
mga -X- _ O
accounts -X- _ O
para -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
akong -X- _ O
work. -X- _ O
Ug -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
gakawat -X- _ O
, -X- _ O
unta -X- _ O
maluoy -X- _ O
ka -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
e -X- _ O
uli -X- _ O
ang -X- _ O
phone. -X- _ O
Can -X- _ O
not -X- _ O
be -X- _ O
reached -X- _ O
na -X- _ O
akong -X- _ O
phone. -X- _ O
If -X- _ O
mahimo -X- _ O
please -X- _ O
ayaw -X- _ O
ra -X- _ O
e -X- _ O
airplane -X- _ O
mode -X- _ O
or -X- _ O
kuhaa -X- _ O
ang -X- _ O
sim -X- _ O
kay -X- _ O
para -X- _ O
matawagan -X- _ O
lang -X- _ O
kay -X- _ O
daghang -X- _ O
importante -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
accounts -X- _ O
naka -X- _ O
attach -X- _ O
ana -X- _ O
. -X- _ O

" -X- _ O
hi -X- _ O
admin -X- _ O
ask -X- _ O
lang -X- _ O
ko. -X- _ O
Okey -X- _ O
ra -X- _ O
diay -X- _ O
gamiton -X- _ O
nang -X- _ O
vehicle -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
naka -X- _ O
red -X- _ O
ug -X- _ O
plaka -X- _ O
for -X- _ O
personal -X- _ O
use -X- _ O
? -X- _ O
Pang -X- _ O
kaun -X- _ O
kaun -X- _ O
ug -X- _ O
restaurant -X- _ O
pang -X- _ O
laag -X- _ O
ug -X- _ O
mall -X- _ O
? -X- _ O
Dile -X- _ O
ba -X- _ O
kita -X- _ O
ga -X- _ O
bayad -X- _ O
ana -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
ilang -X- _ O
gasolin -X- _ O
consumption -X- _ O
? -X- _ O
Kita -X- _ O
ga -X- _ O
bayad -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
atung -X- _ O
buwis -X- _ O
nya -X- _ O
sila -X- _ O
mag -X- _ O
salig -X- _ O
ra -X- _ O
kay -X- _ O
unlimited -X- _ O
gasolina -X- _ O
daw -X- _ O
? -X- _ O
Okey -X- _ O
ra -X- _ O
diay -X- _ O
nang -X- _ O
ing.ana -X- _ O
admin -X- _ O
? -X- _ O
" -X- _ O
Internet -X- _ O
photo -X- _ O
only -X- _ O

Naa -X- _ O
jud -X- _ O
tay -X- _ O
dakong -X- _ O
plaka -X- _ O
or -X- _ O
public -X- _ O
information -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
mag -X- _ O
inform -X- _ O
da -X- _ O
publico -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
rason -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
gina -X- _ O
guba -X- _ O
nang -X- _ O
mga -X- _ O
dalan -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
tarong -X- _ O
pa -X- _ O
ug -X- _ O
nganung -X- _ O
ang -X- _ O
mga -X- _ O
gubang -X- _ O
dalan -X- _ O
ma -X- _ O
abtan -X- _ O
nalang -X- _ O
ug -X- _ O
dekada -X- _ O
wala -X- _ O
man -X- _ O
jud -X- _ O
ma -X- _ O
lihok -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
DPWH -X- _ B-ORG
no -X- _ O
? -X- _ O
Good -X- _ O
roads -X- _ O
need -X- _ O
fixing -X- _ O
Bad -X- _ O
roads -X- _ O
are -X- _ O
worth -X- _ O
getting -X- _ O
ignored -X- _ O

Ang -X- _ O
mga -X- _ O
maot -X- _ O
ray -X- _ O
dakpon -X- _ O
daw -X- _ O
. -X- _ O

Sadly -X- _ O
this -X- _ O
is -X- _ O
Dumaguete -X- _ B-LOC
city. -X- _ I-LOC
Instead -X- _ O
nay -X- _ O
dalan -X- _ O
para -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
mga -X- _ O
tawo -X- _ O
gina -X- _ O
himo -X- _ O
ug -X- _ O
parking -X- _ O
spot. -X- _ O
Kita -X- _ O
nalay -X- _ O
mu -X- _ O
adjust -X- _ O
bahalag -X- _ O
ma -X- _ O
ligsan. -X- _ O
hello -X- _ O
admin.. -X- _ O
pa -X- _ O
help -X- _ O
ko -X- _ O
pangita -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
tag.iya -X- _ O
aning -X- _ O
sakyanan -X- _ O
naka -X- _ O
park -X- _ O
dapit -X- _ O
BIR..gahapon -X- _ B-ORG
pa -X- _ O
ni -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
buntag -X- _ O
ng -X- _ O
park -X- _ O
hangtud -X- _ O
ron -X- _ O
naka -X- _ O
park -X- _ O
ra -X- _ O
japon.. -X- _ O
sidewalk -X- _ O
kaayo -X- _ O
ang -X- _ O
gi -X- _ O
parkingan.. -X- _ O
lapas -X- _ O
na -X- _ O
24hrs -X- _ O
naka -X- _ O
park.. -X- _ O
wala -X- _ O
ga -X- _ O
hunahuna -X- _ O
ang -X- _ O
tag.eya -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
sidewalk -X- _ O
man -X- _ O
eya -X- _ O
giparkingan. -X- _ O
agi.anan -X- _ O
ug -X- _ O
tawo -X- _ O
nya -X- _ O
parkingan -X- _ O
, -X- _ O
asa -X- _ O
naman -X- _ O
mo -X- _ O
agi -X- _ O
ang -X- _ O
tawo -X- _ O
ani -X- _ O
, -X- _ O
.. -X- _ O
palit-palit -X- _ O
ug -X- _ O
sakyanan -X- _ O
dayon -X- _ O
walay -X- _ O
parking -X- _ O
space.. -X- _ O
thank -X- _ O
u.. -X- _ O

Sahay -X- _ O
slowmo -X- _ O
pod -X- _ O
ma -X- _ O
labang -X- _ O
selpon -X- _ O
selpon -X- _ O
is -X- _ O
lifer. -X- _ O
Ctto -X- _ O
Glevin -X- _ O
Lumjod -X- _ O

Daghan -X- _ O
raba -X- _ O
tang -X- _ O
layaw -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
iro -X- _ O
dire -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
Dumaguete. -X- _ B-LOC
Diha -X- _ O
paraba -X- _ O
ta -X- _ O
mu -X- _ O
active -X- _ O
kung -X- _ O
naa -X- _ O
nay -X- _ O
dungog -X- _ O
ug -X- _ O
buang -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
iro. -X- _ O
Look -X- _ O
! -X- _ O
CCTV -X- _ O
footage -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
iro -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
gihangkab-patay -X- _ O
ang -X- _ O
mag -X- _ O
3 -X- _ O
ka -X- _ O
bulan -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
baby -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
Irasan -X- _ B-LOC
, -X- _ I-LOC
Roxas -X- _ I-LOC
Zamboanga -X- _ I-LOC
del -X- _ I-LOC
Norte -X- _ I-LOC
ning -X- _ O
Abril -X- _ O
3 -X- _ O
, -X- _ O
2023 -X- _ O
bandang -X- _ O
alas -X- _ O
4:30 -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
hapon -X- _ O
. -X- _ O

Mau -X- _ O
ning -X- _ O
kahimtang -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
mga -X- _ O
1st -X- _ O
world -X- _ O
countries. -X- _ O
Wala -X- _ O
nay -X- _ O
moral -X- _ O
values -X- _ O
tungud -X- _ O
na -X- _ O
subraan -X- _ O
ilang -X- _ O
pagka -X- _ O
privilage. -X- _ O
Some -X- _ O
are -X- _ O
battling -X- _ O
the -X- _ O
morality -X- _ O
of -X- _ O
their -X- _ O
country. -X- _ O
Importante -X- _ O
jud -X- _ O
nang -X- _ O
moralidad -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
tawo -X- _ O
. -X- _ O

Daghang -X- _ O
bata -X- _ O
deserving -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
pag -X- _ O
skwela -X- _ O
dile -X- _ O
kaning -X- _ O
mga -X- _ O
wokes -X- _ O
. -X- _ O

Dahan -X- _ O
duol -X- _ O
rang -X- _ O
shell -X- _ B-ORG
sa -X- _ O
airport -X- _ O

Ay -X- _ O
hala -X- _ O
lake -X- _ O
dinuldog -X- _ O
! -X- _ O

The -X- _ O
infamous -X- _ O
dead -X- _ O
zone -X- _ O
road -X- _ O
that -X- _ O
caused -X- _ O
accidents -X- _ O
in -X- _ O
the -X- _ O
past -X- _ O
in -X- _ O
CAMANJAC-MAGATAS -X- _ B-LOC
DUMAGUETE -X- _ I-LOC
DIVERSION -X- _ I-LOC
ROAD -X- _ I-LOC
MAAGIAN -X- _ O
NA -X- _ O
! -X- _ O
Mahimo -X- _ O
sab -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
makaagi -X- _ O
ang -X- _ O
mga -X- _ O
dagkong -X- _ O
trak -X- _ O
dekarga -X- _ O
ug -X- _ O
mga -X- _ O
pribadong -X- _ O
sakyanan -X- _ O
gikan -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
Barangay -X- _ B-LOC
Camanjac -X- _ I-LOC
lapos -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
Barangay -X- _ B-LOC
Candau-ay -X- _ I-LOC
luyo -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
Vida -X- _ B-LOC
Royal -X- _ I-LOC
padulong -X- _ O
Cadawinonan -X- _ B-LOC
, -X- _ O
Junob -X- _ B-LOC
, -X- _ O
Cantil-e -X- _ B-LOC
, -X- _ O
Bajumpandan -X- _ B-LOC
ug -X- _ O
Bacong-Valencia -X- _ B-LOC
Road -X- _ I-LOC
sa -X- _ O
Isugan -X- _ B-LOC
Bacong.Via -X- _ I-LOC
/ -X- _ O
mu -X- _ O
lupad -X- _ O
Dumaguete -X- _ O

# -X- _ O
dumathoughtsNanung -X- _ O
lisod -X- _ O
man -X- _ O
jud -X- _ O
mag -X- _ O
impliment -X- _ O
ug -X- _ O
balaud -X- _ O
para -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
ka-ayuhan -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
public -X- _ O
dire -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
Dumaguete -X- _ B-LOC
city -X- _ I-LOC
? -X- _ O
Gamay -X- _ O
rajud -X- _ O
ang -X- _ O
Dumaguete -X- _ B-LOC
interms -X- _ O
of -X- _ O
land -X- _ O
mas -X- _ O
area -X- _ O
and -X- _ O
daghan -X- _ O
na -X- _ O
kaau -X- _ O
establishment -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
ga -X- _ O
bayad -X- _ O
ug -X- _ O
tax. -X- _ O
Nganu -X- _ O
murag -X- _ O
impossible -X- _ O
man -X- _ O
jud -X- _ O
ang -X- _ O
balaud -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
maka -X- _ O
benefit -X- _ O
both -X- _ O
ang -X- _ O
city -X- _ O
ug -X- _ O
ang -X- _ O
mga -X- _ O
tawo -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
naa -X- _ O
dire -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
Dumaguete -X- _ B-LOC
sa -X- _ O
mga -X- _ O
balaod -X- _ O
? -X- _ O
" -X- _ O
Japan -X- _ B-LOC
has -X- _ O
strict -X- _ O
parking -X- _ O
laws -X- _ O
that -X- _ O
prohibit -X- _ O
parking -X- _ O
on -X- _ O
the -X- _ O
street -X- _ O
in -X- _ O
most -X- _ O
areas -X- _ O
unless -X- _ O
there -X- _ O
is -X- _ O
a -X- _ O
designated -X- _ O
parking -X- _ O
sign -X- _ O
with -X- _ O
a -X- _ O
time -X- _ O
limit -X- _ O
or -X- _ O
a -X- _ O
parking -X- _ O
meter. -X- _ O
Parking -X- _ O
in -X- _ O
front -X- _ O
of -X- _ O
building -X- _ O
entrances -X- _ O
, -X- _ O
near -X- _ O
street -X- _ O
junctions -X- _ O
, -X- _ O
and -X- _ O
close -X- _ O
to -X- _ O
emergency -X- _ O
exits -X- _ O
is -X- _ O
also -X- _ O
illegal. -X- _ O
To -X- _ O
register -X- _ O
a -X- _ O
car -X- _ O
in -X- _ O
Japan -X- _ B-LOC
, -X- _ O
one -X- _ O
must -X- _ O
have -X- _ O
a -X- _ O
proof -X- _ O
of -X- _ O
parking -X- _ O
certificate -X- _ O
that -X- _ O
shows -X- _ O
they -X- _ O
have -X- _ O
access -X- _ O
to -X- _ O
a -X- _ O
parking -X- _ O
space -X- _ O
within -X- _ O
2 -X- _ O
km -X- _ O
of -X- _ O
their -X- _ O
residence. -X- _ O
There -X- _ O
are -X- _ O
different -X- _ O
types -X- _ O
of -X- _ O
parking -X- _ O
lots -X- _ O
available -X- _ O
in -X- _ O
Japan -X- _ B-LOC
, -X- _ O
such -X- _ O
as -X- _ O
basement -X- _ O
car -X- _ O
parks -X- _ O
, -X- _ O
coin -X- _ O
parking -X- _ O
lots -X- _ O
, -X- _ O
and -X- _ O
monthly -X- _ O
parking -X- _ O
rentals. -X- _ O
The -X- _ O
parking -X- _ O
fees -X- _ O
vary -X- _ O
depending -X- _ O
on -X- _ O
the -X- _ O
location -X- _ O
and -X- _ O
duration -X- _ O
of -X- _ O
parking -X- _ O
. -X- _ O
" -X- _ O

Even -X- _ O
on -X- _ O
the -X- _ O
start -X- _ O
of -X- _ O
the -X- _ O
Holy -X- _ B-MISC
week -X- _ I-MISC
naa -X- _ O
rajapon -X- _ O
ning -X- _ O
atung -X- _ O
mga -X- _ O
VIP -X- _ O
double -X- _ O
parkers. -X- _ O
Bahala -X- _ O
na -X- _ O
basta -X- _ O
maka -X- _ O
parking -X- _ O
rajud -X- _ O
sila -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
tunga -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
dalan. -X- _ O
Naa -X- _ O
man -X- _ O
tingale -X- _ O
tay -X- _ O
traffic -X- _ O
management -X- _ O
unit -X- _ O
dire -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
Dumaguete -X- _ B-LOC
no -X- _ O
or -X- _ O
katung -X- _ O
atung -X- _ O
discipline -X- _ O
zone -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
? -X- _ O
Sige -X- _ O
ra -X- _ O
lage -X- _ O
mi -X- _ O
maka -X- _ O
dawat -X- _ O
ug -X- _ O
mga -X- _ O
reklamo -X- _ O
? -X- _ O

Baling -X- _ O
daghanang -X- _ O
seben -X- _ B-LOC
elebenHello -X- _ I-LOC
admin -X- _ O
! -X- _ O
Please -X- _ O
kog -X- _ O
post -X- _ O
ani. -X- _ O
Nawala -X- _ O
akong -X- _ O
cellphone -X- _ O
atong -X- _ O
April -X- _ O
02 -X- _ O
, -X- _ O
2023 -X- _ O
ddto -X- _ O
dapit -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
7 -X- _ B-LOC
/ -X- _ I-LOC
11 -X- _ I-LOC
while -X- _ O
akong -X- _ O
Gibilin -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
motor. -X- _ O
Installment -X- _ O
pa -X- _ O
mn -X- _ O
Gud -X- _ O
to -X- _ O
sya -X- _ O
Mao -X- _ O
nasayangan -X- _ O
kaau -X- _ O
ko -X- _ O
Kay -X- _ O
almost -X- _ O
26k -X- _ O
jud -X- _ O
to -X- _ O
sya. -X- _ O
Ang -X- _ O
model -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
phone -X- _ O
is -X- _ O
Oppo -X- _ B-MISC
Reno -X- _ I-MISC
8. -X- _ I-MISC
I -X- _ O
hope -X- _ O
ma -X- _ O
notice -X- _ O
ni -X- _ O
Admin. -X- _ O
Daghan -X- _ O
Salamat -X- _ O
! -X- _ O

A -X- _ O
friendly -X- _ O
reminder -X- _ O
kung -X- _ O
dile -X- _ O
ma -X- _ O
register -X- _ O
inyung -X- _ O
sim -X- _ O
card -X- _ O
ma -X- _ O
deactivate -X- _ O
na -X- _ O
siya -X- _ O
ug -X- _ O
dile -X- _ O
magamit. -X- _ O
Kung -X- _ O
makay -X- _ O
gcash -X- _ B-MISC
nya -X- _ O
wala -X- _ O
na -X- _ O
register -X- _ O
goodbye -X- _ O
. -X- _ O

Lisod -X- _ O
ni -X- _ O
e -X- _ O
apply -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
Dumaguete -X- _ B-LOC
city -X- _ I-LOC
daghang -X- _ O
special -X- _ O
drivers -X- _ O
hadlok -X- _ O
ang -X- _ O
balaud -X- _ O
nila -X- _ O
! -X- _ O
The -X- _ O
anti-distracted -X- _ B-MISC
driving -X- _ I-MISC
act -X- _ I-MISC
carries -X- _ O
a -X- _ O
penalty -X- _ O
of -X- _ O
? -X- _ O
5,000 -X- _ O
for -X- _ O
the -X- _ O
first -X- _ O
offense -X- _ O
. -X- _ O

I -X- _ O
received -X- _ O
this -X- _ O
picture -X- _ O
thru -X- _ O
my -X- _ O
messenger. -X- _ O
This -X- _ O
looks -X- _ O
familiar. -X- _ O
Ag -X- _ O
lakturanan -X- _ O
man -X- _ O
ni -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
mga -X- _ O
tagka -X- _ O
lower -X- _ O
Pancil -X- _ B-LOC
nga -X- _ O
buot -X- _ O
mogawas -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
highway. -X- _ O
Gebutangan -X- _ O
gyud -X- _ O
gani -X- _ O
ni -X- _ O
ug -X- _ O
hagdan -X- _ O
, -X- _ O
adto -X- _ O
man -X- _ O
ni -X- _ O
mogawas -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
kilid -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
Ocoy -X- _ B-LOC
bridge.Akong -X- _ I-LOC
awhagon -X- _ O
ang -X- _ O
nagbutang -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
alad -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
mo -X- _ O
set -X- _ O
back -X- _ O
mo -X- _ O
ug -X- _ O
3 -X- _ O
meters -X- _ O
, -X- _ O
respetaran -X- _ O
nato -X- _ O
ang -X- _ O
easement -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
gisitar -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
balaod. -X- _ O
Tapad -X- _ O
man -X- _ O
ta -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
Ocoy -X- _ B-LOC
river -X- _ I-LOC
mao -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
ipagawas -X- _ O
gyud -X- _ O
nato -X- _ O
ang -X- _ O
maong -X- _ O
easement -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
atong -X- _ O
alad.Engineer -X- _ O
Fontelo -X- _ B-PER
please -X- _ O
look -X- _ O
into -X- _ O
this. -X- _ O
I -X- _ O
am -X- _ O
sure -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
ug -X- _ O
naglukat -X- _ O
nig -X- _ O
fencing -X- _ O
permit -X- _ O
nihatag -X- _ O
na -X- _ O
ka -X- _ O
daan -X- _ O
ug -X- _ O
pahemangno. -X- _ O
Palihog -X- _ O
lantawa -X- _ O
ug -X- _ O
nasunod -X- _ O
ba -X- _ O
ang -X- _ O
3-meter -X- _ O
easement -X- _ O
gekan -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
kilid -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
Ocoy -X- _ B-LOC
river -X- _ I-LOC
. -X- _ O

Para -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
awareness -X- _ O
tanan -X- _ O
gkan -X- _ O
ni -X- _ O
Jake -X- _ B-PER
Kwong -X- _ I-PER
, -X- _ O
with -X- _ O
Dumaguete -X- _ B-LOC
city -X- _ I-LOC
having -X- _ O
low -X- _ O
police -X- _ O
patrol -X- _ O
visibility -X- _ O
on -X- _ O
late -X- _ O
nights -X- _ O
, -X- _ O
it -X- _ O
is -X- _ O
important -X- _ O
that -X- _ O
we -X- _ O
must -X- _ O
be -X- _ O
vigilant. -X- _ O
Guys -X- _ O
awareness -X- _ O
! -X- _ O
Pagbantay -X- _ O
mo -X- _ O
diha -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
park -X- _ O
or -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
red -X- _ O
cross -X- _ O
office -X- _ O
dapit -X- _ O
kay -X- _ O
ni -X- _ O
park -X- _ O
ko -X- _ O
diha -X- _ O
gabie -X- _ O
kay -X- _ O
puno -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
boulevard -X- _ B-LOC
, -X- _ O
naa -X- _ O
ray -X- _ O
mo -X- _ O
kalit -X- _ O
sulod -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
inyo -X- _ O
sakyanan -X- _ O
niya -X- _ O
di -X- _ O
na -X- _ O
mo -X- _ O
naog -X- _ O
na -X- _ O
bantan-on -X- _ O
, -X- _ O
unya -X- _ O
ni -X- _ O
kalit -X- _ O
rag -X- _ O
sakay -X- _ O
mangayo -X- _ O
kwarta -X- _ O
ug -X- _ O
mang -X- _ O
threat -X- _ O
( -X- _ O
duda -X- _ O
pud -X- _ O
nako -X- _ O
call -X- _ O
boy -X- _ O
siya -X- _ O
) -X- _ O
ug -X- _ O
( -X- _ O
abig -X- _ O
minor -X- _ O
guro -X- _ O
siya -X- _ O
ages -X- _ O
16-18 -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
ako -X- _ O
assessment -X- _ O
) -X- _ O
panaugon -X- _ O
kay -X- _ O
i -X- _ O
threat -X- _ O
ka -X- _ O
niya -X- _ O
, -X- _ O
ni -X- _ O
ingon -X- _ O
man -X- _ O
jud -X- _ O
ko -X- _ O
na -X- _ O
unsa -X- _ O
man -X- _ O
di -X- _ O
ka -X- _ O
mo -X- _ O
naog -X- _ O
kay -X- _ O
mo -X- _ O
tawag -X- _ O
ko -X- _ O
ug -X- _ O
police -X- _ O
ug -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
dihang -X- _ O
niingon -X- _ O
siya -X- _ O
na -X- _ O
iyang -X- _ O
pud -X- _ O
daw -X- _ O
ingnon -X- _ O
ang -X- _ O
police -X- _ O
na -X- _ O
gisakay -X- _ O
na -X- _ O
nako -X- _ O
siya -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
sakyanan -X- _ O
ug -X- _ O
gihikap. -X- _ O
So -X- _ O
probably -X- _ O
ginabuhat -X- _ O
na -X- _ O
to -X- _ O
niya -X- _ O
multiple -X- _ O
times -X- _ O
kay -X- _ O
maayu -X- _ O
man -X- _ O
kaayu -X- _ O
mo -X- _ O
rason -X- _ O
, -X- _ O
walay -X- _ O
kahadlok. -X- _ O
Ni -X- _ O
hatag -X- _ O
nalang -X- _ O
ko -X- _ O
ug -X- _ O
300 -X- _ O
para -X- _ O
mo -X- _ O
naog -X- _ O
siya -X- _ O
infront -X- _ O
of -X- _ O
Plaza -X- _ B-LOC
maria -X- _ I-LOC
luiza -X- _ I-LOC
hotel -X- _ I-LOC
kay -X- _ O
naay -X- _ O
guard -X- _ O
ug -X- _ O
katong -X- _ O
staff -X- _ O
at -X- _ O
around -X- _ O
11:30PM -X- _ O
then -X- _ O
ni -X- _ O
diritso -X- _ O
kos -X- _ O
police -X- _ O
pa -X- _ O
blotter. -X- _ O
Mo -X- _ O
dako -X- _ O
tung -X- _ O
bataa -X- _ O
its -X- _ O
either -X- _ O
murder -X- _ O
or -X- _ O
robbery -X- _ O
ang -X- _ O
mabuhat -X- _ O
pa -X- _ O
ato -X- _ O
kay -X- _ O
very -X- _ O
aggressive -X- _ O
and -X- _ O
demanding. -X- _ O
Dili -X- _ O
klaro -X- _ O
ang -X- _ O
pic -X- _ O
kay -X- _ O
kulbaan -X- _ O
nako -X- _ O
kaayu -X- _ O
gabie -X- _ O
. -X- _ O

Ang -X- _ O
ka -X- _ O
lisod -X- _ O
lang -X- _ O
jud -X- _ O
dire -X- _ O
Dumaguete -X- _ B-LOC
gama -X- _ O
gama -X- _ O
ug -X- _ O
balaod -X- _ O
para -X- _ O
lang -X- _ O
pogi -X- _ O
points. -X- _ O
Nothing -X- _ O
done -X- _ O
to -X- _ O
maintain -X- _ O
the -X- _ O
law -X- _ O
that -X- _ O
is -X- _ O
good -X- _ O
for -X- _ O
the -X- _ O
public. -X- _ O
Hi -X- _ O
admin -X- _ O
, -X- _ O
wan -X- _ O
na -X- _ O
share -X- _ O
my -X- _ O
experience -X- _ O
driving -X- _ O
home -X- _ O
using -X- _ O
a -X- _ O
motorcycle. -X- _ O
Naay -X- _ O
truck -X- _ O
gauna -X- _ O
nako -X- _ O
with -X- _ O
a -X- _ O
passenger -X- _ O
holding -X- _ O
a -X- _ O
lit -X- _ O
cigarette. -X- _ O
Napuling -X- _ O
kos -X- _ O
iyang -X- _ O
upos -X- _ O
ug -X- _ O
hapdos -X- _ O
jud -X- _ O
kaayo -X- _ O
akong -X- _ O
mata.I -X- _ O
cut -X- _ O
them -X- _ O
off -X- _ O
the -X- _ O
road -X- _ O
and -X- _ O
reprimanded -X- _ O
them. -X- _ O
Wala -X- _ O
na -X- _ O
ba -X- _ O
tay -X- _ O
city -X- _ O
mandate -X- _ O
kabahin -X- _ O
aning -X- _ O
cigarette -X- _ O
? -X- _ O
Delikado -X- _ O
kaayo -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
motor -X- _ O
riders -X- _ O
, -X- _ O
especially -X- _ O
kung -X- _ O
kids -X- _ O
ang -X- _ O
mutungnan -X- _ O
ani.I -X- _ O
hope -X- _ O
I -X- _ O
make -X- _ O
sense -X- _ O
. -X- _ O

Lisod -X- _ O
lage -X- _ O
kaau -X- _ O
naka -X- _ O
4wheels -X- _ O
ta -X- _ O
but -X- _ O
we -X- _ O
still -X- _ O
park -X- _ O
like -X- _ O
naka -X- _ O
2wheels -X- _ O
lang. -X- _ O
Daghan -X- _ O
kaau -X- _ O
ma -X- _ O
alahig -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
atung -X- _ O
ka -X- _ O
dangag. -X- _ O
Let -X- _ O
's -X- _ O
not -X- _ O
be -X- _ O
selfish -X- _ O
pod -X- _ O
be -X- _ O
proper -X- _ O
in -X- _ O
driving -X- _ O
andn -X- _ O
have -X- _ O
ethics -X- _ O
as -X- _ O
well. -X- _ O
Hi -X- _ O
sir -X- _ O
, -X- _ O
naa -X- _ O
lang -X- _ O
mi -X- _ O
concern -X- _ O
anang -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
west -X- _ B-LOC
elem -X- _ I-LOC
school. -X- _ I-LOC
Lisod -X- _ O
kaayo -X- _ O
ang -X- _ O
traffic -X- _ O
dirang -X- _ O
dapita -X- _ O
samot -X- _ O
nag -X- _ O
naka -X- _ O
4wheels -X- _ O
kay -X- _ O
maglisod -X- _ O
mig -X- _ O
pangita -X- _ O
parkinganan -X- _ O
, -X- _ O
maong -X- _ O
magsayo. -X- _ O
Unsaon -X- _ O
man -X- _ O
namo -X- _ O
pagpwesto -X- _ O
tarong -X- _ O
kung -X- _ O
ang -X- _ O
uban -X- _ O
mismo -X- _ O
dili -X- _ O
kabalo -X- _ O
mupark. -X- _ O
Mao -X- _ O
pay -X- _ O
galeft -X- _ O
and -X- _ O
right -X- _ O
na -X- _ O
nang -X- _ O
parking -X- _ O
dira -X- _ O
. -X- _ O

Silliman -X- _ B-LOC
University -X- _ I-LOC
is -X- _ O
a -X- _ O
car -X- _ O
priority -X- _ O
school -X- _ O
leaving -X- _ O
people -X- _ O
to -X- _ O
walk -X- _ O
on -X- _ O
the -X- _ O
road -X- _ O
way -X- _ O
rather -X- _ O
than -X- _ O
on -X- _ O
a -X- _ O
sidewalk. -X- _ O
( -X- _ O
sana -X- _ O
all -X- _ O
tanang -X- _ O
studente -X- _ O
maka -X- _ O
car -X- _ O
) -X- _ O
Kailangan -X- _ O
najud -X- _ O
e -X- _ O
regulate -X- _ O
ang -X- _ O
mga -X- _ O
sakyanan -X- _ O
dire -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
Dumaguete -X- _ B-LOC
city. -X- _ I-LOC
Coding -X- _ O
should -X- _ O
be -X- _ O
introduced -X- _ O
and -X- _ O
enhanced -X- _ O
traffic -X- _ O
management -X- _ O
should -X- _ O
be -X- _ O
applied -X- _ O
. -X- _ O

Hello -X- _ O
maam -X- _ O
sirs -X- _ O
naglakw -X- _ O
rakos -X- _ O
boulevard -X- _ B-LOC
the -X- _ O
other -X- _ O
day. -X- _ O
Dle -X- _ O
jud -X- _ O
ing.ana -X- _ O
ka -X- _ O
layu -X- _ O
ang -X- _ O
basurahan -X- _ O
as -X- _ O
in -X- _ O
ang -X- _ O
mga -X- _ O
tawo -X- _ O
dire -X- _ O
kay -X- _ O
nagka -X- _ O
tapulan -X- _ O
ug -X- _ O
nagka -X- _ O
hugawan -X- _ O
. -X- _ O

Naka -X- _ O
bisita -X- _ O
naba -X- _ O
tanan -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
Lakeside -X- _ B-LOC
Pantawan -X- _ I-LOC
located -X- _ O
near -X- _ O
the -X- _ O
boulevard -X- _ B-LOC
? -X- _ O
Nindot -X- _ O
og -X- _ O
biew -X- _ O
, -X- _ O
" -X- _ O
i -X- _ O
like -X- _ O
da -X- _ O
biew -X- _ O
" -X- _ O

" -X- _ O
Wla -X- _ O
na -X- _ O
ba -X- _ O
gyud -X- _ O
control -X- _ O
ang -X- _ O
city -X- _ O
ani -X- _ O
mga -X- _ O
badjao -X- _ B-MISC
bali -X- _ O
nman -X- _ O
gyud -X- _ O
dghana -X- _ O
kaau -X- _ O
... -X- _ O
ang -X- _ O
ila -X- _ O
mga -X- _ O
hugaw -X- _ O
og -X- _ O
basura -X- _ O
ipangbilin -X- _ O
ra -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
mga -X- _ O
kilid2x -X- _ O
... -X- _ O
ang -X- _ O
mga -X- _ O
stablishment -X- _ O
mao -X- _ O
ang -X- _ O
manglimpyo -X- _ O
maayo -X- _ O
ba -X- _ O
? -X- _ O
? -X- _ O
? -X- _ O
basin -X- _ O
matagaan -X- _ O
og -X- _ O
pgtagad -X- _ O
sir.. -X- _ O
" -X- _ O

" -X- _ O
hi -X- _ O
admin -X- _ O
excempted -X- _ O
diay -X- _ O
nang -X- _ O
police -X- _ O
motorbike -X- _ O
mu -X- _ O
agi -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
sidewalk -X- _ O
? -X- _ O
Mismo -X- _ O
sila -X- _ O
above -X- _ O
the -X- _ O
law -X- _ O
pod -X- _ O
diay -X- _ O
? -X- _ O
I -X- _ O
happened -X- _ O
to -X- _ O
see -X- _ O
one -X- _ O
the -X- _ O
other -X- _ O
day -X- _ O
while -X- _ O
driving -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
Saint -X- _ B-LOC
Paul -X- _ I-LOC
area. -X- _ O
" -X- _ O
Kung -X- _ O
ang -X- _ O
police -X- _ O
magpa -X- _ O
buyag -X- _ O
Kinsa -X- _ O
may -X- _ O
mu -X- _ O
buyag -X- _ O
pod -X- _ O
nila -X- _ O
? -X- _ O

Atay -X- _ O
maam -X- _ O
/ -X- _ O
sir -X- _ O
tunga -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
dalan -X- _ O
ga -X- _ O
parking. -X- _ O
Klaro -X- _ O
naman -X- _ O
kaayu -X- _ O
ning -X- _ O
no -X- _ O
parking -X- _ O
sign -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
iyang -X- _ O
likod. -X- _ O
4wheel -X- _ O
kamote -X- _ O
driver -X- _ O
jud -X- _ O
ni -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
driver -X- _ O
? -X- _ O
? -X- _ O
wala -X- _ O
bay -X- _ O
tow -X- _ O
truck -X- _ O
dire -X- _ O
dumaguete -X- _ B-LOC
bali -X- _ O
jung -X- _ O
traffika -X- _ O
tungud -X- _ O
ani -X- _ O
niya -X- _ O
? -X- _ O
? -X- _ O

Kaya -X- _ O
baya -X- _ O
buhaton -X- _ O
nis -X- _ O
Dumaguete -X- _ B-LOC
samot -X- _ O
panang -X- _ O
mga -X- _ O
4 -X- _ O
wheels -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
balabag -X- _ O
kaau -X- _ O
mag -X- _ O
parking -X- _ O
. -X- _ O

LOOK -X- _ O
: -X- _ O
Nakita -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
duha -X- _ O
ka -X- _ O
mga -X- _ O
hiker -X- _ O
ang -X- _ O
Visayan -X- _ B-MISC
leopard -X- _ I-MISC
cat -X- _ I-MISC
, -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
lokal -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
nailhan -X- _ O
isip -X- _ O
" -X- _ O
Maral -X- _ B-MISC
, -X- _ O
" -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
Mt. -X- _ B-LOC
Talinis -X- _ I-LOC
sa -X- _ O
Negros -X- _ B-LOC
Oriental -X- _ I-LOC
niadtong -X- _ O
Jan. -X- _ O
2 -X- _ O
, -X- _ O
2023.Usa -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
mga -X- _ O
hikers -X- _ O
, -X- _ O
Jovy -X- _ B-PER
Tuting -X- _ I-PER
, -X- _ O
ang -X- _ O
nikuha -X- _ O
og -X- _ O
litrato -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
samaran -X- _ O
daw -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
Maral -X- _ B-MISC
nga -X- _ O
nagtago -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
mga -X- _ O
dahon -X- _ O
diin -X- _ O
sila -X- _ O
niagi. -X- _ O
Ang -X- _ O
maong -X- _ O
'specie -X- _ O
' -X- _ O
, -X- _ O
usa -X- _ O
ka -X- _ O
lumad -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
isla -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
Negros -X- _ B-LOC
, -X- _ I-LOC
Cebu -X- _ I-LOC
, -X- _ O
ug -X- _ O
Panay. -X- _ B-LOC
Jovy -X- _ O
Tuting -X- _ O
via -X- _ O
The -X- _ O
Philippine -X- _ O
Star -X- _ O

# -X- _ O
Dumashares -X- _ O
Admin -X- _ O
maaung -X- _ O
buntag -X- _ O
while -X- _ O
driving -X- _ O
along -X- _ O
going -X- _ O
to -X- _ O
Bantayan -X- _ B-LOC
naka -X- _ O
sunud -X- _ O
napod -X- _ O
kog -X- _ O
cement -X- _ O
truck -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
nag -X- _ O
pa -X- _ O
awas -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
ilang -X- _ O
mga -X- _ O
karga -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
dalan. -X- _ O
Diba -X- _ O
mau -X- _ O
maning -X- _ O
mga -X- _ O
cause -X- _ O
mag -X- _ O
deform -X- _ O
ang -X- _ O
mga -X- _ O
dalan -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
Dumaguete -X- _ B-LOC
adding -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
nay -X- _ O
mga -X- _ O
daghang -X- _ O
pebbles -X- _ O
pajud -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
maka -X- _ O
slide -X- _ O
ug -X- _ O
mga -X- _ O
motorista. -X- _ O
Dile -X- _ O
jud -X- _ O
ni -X- _ O
ma -X- _ O
buyag -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
atung -X- _ O
LGU -X- _ B-ORG
sa -X- _ O
Dumaguete -X- _ B-LOC
aning -X- _ O
mga -X- _ O
construction -X- _ O
company -X- _ O
? -X- _ O

Kana -X- _ O
bang -X- _ O
fixer -X- _ O
raka -X- _ O
taman -X- _ O
nya -X- _ O
mura -X- _ O
pod -X- _ O
kag -X- _ O
sweto -X- _ O
kay -X- _ O
nas -X- _ O
googel -X- _ B-ORG

Kita -X- _ O
namog -X- _ O
consehal -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
Dumaguete -X- _ B-LOC
city -X- _ I-LOC
mu -X- _ O
sakay -X- _ O
ug -X- _ O
pedicab -X- _ O
? -X- _ O

Admin -X- _ O
look -X- _ O
new -X- _ O
yellow -X- _ O
lines -X- _ O
now -X- _ O
called -X- _ O
double -X- _ O
black -X- _ O
lanes -X- _ O
Nag -X- _ O
butang -X- _ O
sila -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
hayag -X- _ O
nya -X- _ O
traffic -X- _ O
kaau -X- _ O
walay -X- _ O
chance -X- _ O
mu -X- _ O
permanent -X- _ O
dry -X- _ O
ang -X- _ O
paint -X- _ O
, -X- _ O
nya -X- _ O
balo -X- _ O
baya -X- _ O
kas -X- _ O
Dumaguete -X- _ B-LOC
drivers -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
walay -X- _ O
na -X- _ O
hibal.an -X- _ O
na -X- _ O
balaod -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
pag -X- _ O
drive. -X- _ O
Pa -X- _ O
share -X- _ O
lang -X- _ O
admin -X- _ O
para -X- _ O
awareness -X- _ O

Maayong -X- _ O
Adlaw -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
tanan -X- _ O
! -X- _ O
! -X- _ O
! -X- _ O
Kung -X- _ O
kinsa -X- _ O
man -X- _ O
ang -X- _ O
nakita -X- _ O
ingon -X- _ O
ani -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
envelope -X- _ O
, -X- _ O
nisakay -X- _ O
kog -X- _ O
easy -X- _ O
ride -X- _ O
color -X- _ O
red -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
crossing -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
Maslog -X- _ B-LOC
going -X- _ O
to -X- _ O
Dumaguete -X- _ B-LOC
possible -X- _ O
nahulog -X- _ O
atbang -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
People -X- _ B-LOC
's -X- _ I-LOC
Choice -X- _ I-LOC
Pharmacy -X- _ I-LOC
atbang -X- _ O
tiyangge -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
Dumaguete -X- _ B-LOC
o -X- _ O
kay -X- _ O
ddto -X- _ O
man -X- _ O
ko -X- _ O
nanaog -X- _ O
naa -X- _ O
or -X- _ O
paingon -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
COSCA -X- _ B-LOC
kay -X- _ O
dha -X- _ O
pod -X- _ O
ko -X- _ O
ni -X- _ O
agi -X- _ O
to -X- _ O
syay -X- _ O
sulod -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
importante -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
documents. -X- _ O
Palihug -X- _ O
kog -X- _ O
contact -X- _ O
lang -X- _ O
ani -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
number -X- _ O
09519707420 -X- _ O
or -X- _ O
09540692670. -X- _ O
Mo -X- _ O
hatag -X- _ O
lang -X- _ O
kog -X- _ O
pahalipay -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
makabalik -X- _ O
ato. -X- _ O
Daghang -X- _ O
Salamat -X- _ O
ug -X- _ O
God -X- _ O
bless -X- _ O

# -X- _ O
SurveytimePara -X- _ O
ninyo -X- _ O
asa -X- _ O
man -X- _ O
mapalit -X- _ O
ang -X- _ O
pinakalami -X- _ O
na -X- _ O
siopao -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
Dumaguete -X- _ B-LOC
? -X- _ O
I.comment -X- _ O
na -X- _ O
mga -X- _ O
badi -X- _ O
! -X- _ O

Murag -X- _ O
ubay -X- _ O
ubay -X- _ O
nanis -X- _ O
atua. -X- _ O
Pa -X- _ O
kusug -X- _ O
ug -X- _ O
drive -X- _ O
nya -X- _ O
maka -X- _ O
dasmag -X- _ O
ug -X- _ O
laing -X- _ O
motorista -X- _ O
. -X- _ O

Bagay -X- _ O
nis -X- _ O
Dumaguete -X- _ B-LOC
kay -X- _ O
baling -X- _ O
daghanang -X- _ O
iro. -X- _ O
Dako -X- _ O
kaau -X- _ O
tag -X- _ O
bayad -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
hospital -X- _ O
kay -X- _ O
naka -X- _ O
ligid -X- _ O
tag -X- _ O
iro -X- _ O
and -X- _ O
until -X- _ O
now -X- _ O
it -X- _ O
's -X- _ O
still -X- _ O
a -X- _ O
growing -X- _ O
problem -X- _ O
para -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
mga -X- _ O
motorist. -X- _ O
No -X- _ O
hate -X- _ O
towards -X- _ O
dogs -X- _ O
but -X- _ O
daghang -X- _ O
iro -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
walay -X- _ O
tag -X- _ O
iya. -X- _ O
Mga -X- _ O
gangsta -X- _ O
dogs -X- _ O
. -X- _ O

Kusug -X- _ O
raba -X- _ O
kaau -X- _ O
maningil -X- _ O
ning -X- _ O
BIR -X- _ B-ORG
. -X- _ O

Pila -X- _ O
kahay -X- _ O
timbang -X- _ O
anang -X- _ O
no -X- _ O
parking -X- _ O
sign -X- _ O
? -X- _ O
Murag -X- _ O
useless -X- _ O
decoration -X- _ O
raman -X- _ O
na -X- _ O
dire -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
Dumaguete. -X- _ B-LOC
Balabag -X- _ O
pas -X- _ O
mga -X- _ O
parkingan -X- _ O
gud -X- _ O
samot -X- _ O
patung -X- _ O
gi -X- _ O
butang -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
escao -X- _ B-LOC
dapit -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
atbang -X- _ O
kaau -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
dagat -X- _ O
ug -X- _ O
ni -X- _ O
taya -X- _ O
nalang. -X- _ O
( -X- _ O
pagka -X- _ O
bright -X- _ O
jud -X- _ O
) -X- _ O

One -X- _ O
thing -X- _ O
about -X- _ O
Dumaguete -X- _ B-LOC
city -X- _ I-LOC
kay -X- _ O
bisag -X- _ O
unsa -X- _ O
kadugay -X- _ O
mu -X- _ O
parking -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
parke -X- _ O
bahalag -X- _ O
bahu -X- _ O
ug -X- _ O
ihi -X- _ O
ug -X- _ O
tae -X- _ O
dihang -X- _ O
dapita -X- _ O
dile -X- _ O
rajud -X- _ O
hilabtan -X- _ O
imung -X- _ O
sakyanan. -X- _ O
It -X- _ O
's -X- _ O
a -X- _ O
safe -X- _ O
city -X- _ O
jud -X- _ O
! -X- _ O
Naa -X- _ O
pay -X- _ O
warning -X- _ O
cone -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
sulod -X- _ O
to -X- _ O
warn -X- _ O
others -X- _ O
, -X- _ O
very -X- _ O
thoughtful -X- _ O
. -X- _ O

Tax -X- _ O
payer -X- _ O
ka -X- _ O
but -X- _ O
ikaw -X- _ O
ray -X- _ O
gipa -X- _ O
lisod. -X- _ O
Asa -X- _ O
daw -X- _ O
pwede -X- _ O
ma -X- _ O
report -X- _ O
? -X- _ O

Para -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
awareness -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
tanan -X- _ O
regarding -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
BIR -X- _ B-ORG
. -X- _ O

Unsay -X- _ O
pulos -X- _ O
mu -X- _ O
sunud -X- _ O
ug -X- _ O
systemang -X- _ O
binutchuk -X- _ O
? -X- _ O
Ikaw -X- _ O
pay -X- _ O
ga -X- _ O
bayad -X- _ O
ikaw -X- _ O
pay -X- _ O
magka -X- _ O
lisod -X- _ O
? -X- _ O
Ikaw -X- _ O
ga -X- _ O
sweldo -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
gobyerno -X- _ O
ikaw -X- _ O
ang -X- _ O
mag -X- _ O
kalisod -X- _ O
? -X- _ O
Okey -X- _ O
ramo -X- _ O
ing.ani -X- _ O
sige -X- _ O
ang -X- _ O
systema -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
Dumaguete -X- _ B-ORG
BIR -X- _ I-ORG
? -X- _ O
Lantawa -X- _ O
: -X- _ O
Daw -X- _ O
bag-o -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
Campsite -X- _ O
ang -X- _ O
usa -X- _ O
ka -X- _ O
Opisina -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
Goberyno -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
Dakbayan -X- _ O
diin -X- _ O
makita -X- _ O
ang -X- _ O
mga -X- _ O
clienti -X- _ O
ani -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
naghigda -X- _ O
ug -X- _ O
nagtapok -X- _ O
gawas -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
opisina -X- _ O
adlaw -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
Domingo -X- _ O
alas -X- _ O
11 -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
gabie -X- _ O
para -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
ilang -X- _ O
transaction -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
8am.Apan -X- _ O
Lamok -X- _ O
ug -X- _ O
katugnaw -X- _ O
ang -X- _ O
dangatan -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
mga -X- _ O
Cliente -X- _ O
kay -X- _ O
tungod -X- _ O
walay -X- _ O
nindot -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
view -X- _ O
aning -X- _ O
dapita -X- _ O
ug -X- _ O
daplin -X- _ O
kini -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
dalan -X- _ O
ang -X- _ O
katulgan -X- _ O
. -X- _ O

Lisod -X- _ O
jud -X- _ O
kung -X- _ O
ang -X- _ O
dakpon -X- _ O
taman -X- _ O
ras -X- _ O
bike -X- _ O
ug -X- _ O
motor. -X- _ O
kaning -X- _ O
mga -X- _ O
4wheels -X- _ O
entitled -X- _ O
kaau -X- _ O
mu -X- _ O
parking -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
sidewalk -X- _ O
para -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
mga -X- _ O
tawo. -X- _ O
Ikaw -X- _ O
mag -X- _ O
lakaw -X- _ O
ma -X- _ O
pugus -X- _ O
nalang -X- _ O
kag -X- _ O
agi -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
dalan -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
daghan -X- _ O
sakyanan -X- _ O
mu -X- _ O
agi. -X- _ O
Lisod -X- _ O
kaau -X- _ O
ning -X- _ O
kahimtan -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
Dumaguete -X- _ B-LOC
nga -X- _ O
mas -X- _ O
pabor -X- _ O
nila -X- _ O
ning -X- _ O
mga -X- _ O
4 -X- _ O
wheels -X- _ O
kaysa -X- _ O
mga -X- _ O
tawo. -X- _ O
Daghang -X- _ O
4wheels -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
entitled -X- _ O
kaau -X- _ O
, -X- _ O
abi -X- _ O
naka -X- _ O
sakyanan -X- _ O
wala -X- _ O
nay -X- _ O
paghuna -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
mga -X- _ O
tig -X- _ O
lakaw. -X- _ O
Wala -X- _ O
najud -X- _ O
hope -X- _ O
ning -X- _ O
systema -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
dumaguete -X- _ B-LOC
admin -X- _ O
? -X- _ O

Pang -X- _ O
awareness -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
tanan -X- _ O
kay -X- _ O
diha -X- _ O
paraba -X- _ O
mu -X- _ O
lihok -X- _ O
ang -X- _ O
LGU -X- _ B-ORG
naa -X- _ O
nay -X- _ O
ma -X- _ O
accidente -X- _ O
. -X- _ O

Mura -X- _ O
nata -X- _ O
tag -X- _ O
amerika -X- _ B-LOC
karon. -X- _ O
Dile -X- _ O
safe -X- _ O
ang -X- _ O
mga -X- _ O
schools -X- _ O
. -X- _ O

Hit -X- _ O
and -X- _ O
run -X- _ O
incident -X- _ O
by -X- _ O
a -X- _ O
NO -X- _ O
PLATE -X- _ O
BLUE -X- _ O
HONDA -X- _ B-MISC
CLICK -X- _ I-MISC
TWO -X- _ O
ladies -X- _ O
riding -X- _ O
in -X- _ O
tandemWhen -X- _ O
: -X- _ O
March -X- _ O
1 -X- _ O
, -X- _ O
2023 -X- _ O
- -X- _ O
5pmWhere -X- _ O
: -X- _ O
Brgy. -X- _ B-LOC
Motong -X- _ I-LOC
, -X- _ O
( -X- _ O
along -X- _ O
2bil -X- _ B-LOC
Gas -X- _ I-LOC
station -X- _ I-LOC
going -X- _ O
to -X- _ O
corner -X- _ O
EJ -X- _ B-LOC
Blanco -X- _ I-LOC
) -X- _ O
Among -X- _ O
white -X- _ O
Xpander -X- _ B-MISC
ilang -X- _ O
nabundol -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
likod. -X- _ O
Ganahan -X- _ O
rata -X- _ O
namo -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
bsag -X- _ O
mameet -X- _ O
ra -X- _ O
sila -X- _ O
and -X- _ O
maaccountable -X- _ O
sila -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
damage -X- _ O
ky -X- _ O
pwd -X- _ O
raman -X- _ O
ta -X- _ O
to -X- _ O
sabutan -X- _ O
niikyas -X- _ O
lng -X- _ O
gyud -X- _ O
sila -X- _ O
basin -X- _ O
walai -X- _ O
rehistro -X- _ O
or -X- _ O
license. -X- _ O
Wala -X- _ O
actually -X- _ O
nakuha -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
cctv -X- _ O
ang -X- _ O
mismong -X- _ O
incident -X- _ O
pero -X- _ O
naidentify -X- _ O
sila -X- _ O
namo -X- _ O
and -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
mga -X- _ O
resident -X- _ O
didto -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
area -X- _ O
during -X- _ O
the -X- _ O
incident. -X- _ O
Mao -X- _ O
natrace -X- _ O
lng -X- _ O
namo -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
cctv -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
niliko -X- _ O
na -X- _ O
sila -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
EJ -X- _ B-LOC
Blanco -X- _ I-LOC
since -X- _ O
nakita -X- _ O
pud -X- _ O
nko -X- _ O
ilang -X- _ O
palakaw -X- _ O
after -X- _ O
nakadasmag -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
among -X- _ O
likod. -X- _ O
Ang -X- _ O
kuha -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
cctv -X- _ O
is -X- _ O
kana -X- _ O
lng -X- _ O
nihunong -X- _ O
sila -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
may -X- _ O
Dela -X- _ B-LOC
Vena -X- _ I-LOC
corner -X- _ I-LOC
EJ -X- _ I-LOC
Blanco -X- _ I-LOC
sa -X- _ O
may -X- _ O
tindahan -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
kilid -X- _ O
after -X- _ O
few -X- _ O
minutes -X- _ O
nilakaw -X- _ O
sila -X- _ O
padayun -X- _ O
EJ -X- _ B-LOC
Blanco. -X- _ I-LOC
Ipaadto -X- _ O
lng -X- _ O
sila -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
police -X- _ O
station -X- _ O
ky -X- _ O
nakablotter -X- _ O
nana -X- _ O
and -X- _ O
ang -X- _ O
police -X- _ O
ra -X- _ O
mucommunicate -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
amo -X- _ O
to -X- _ O
meet -X- _ O
them.by -X- _ O
April -X- _ O
1 -X- _ O
dli -X- _ O
pa -X- _ O
sila -X- _ O
muapproach -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
amoa -X- _ O
or -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
police -X- _ O
station -X- _ O
, -X- _ O
mufile -X- _ O
nami -X- _ O
ug -X- _ O
kaso. -X- _ O
Since -X- _ O
na -X- _ O
identify -X- _ O
na -X- _ O
namo -X- _ O
ilang -X- _ O
identity -X- _ O
thru -X- _ O
additional -X- _ O
cctv -X- _ O
footage -X- _ O
and -X- _ O
eyewitnesses -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
mismong -X- _ O
incident. -X- _ O
Trivia -X- _ O
lng -X- _ O
, -X- _ O
we -X- _ O
know -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
mother -X- _ O
n -X- _ O
daughter -X- _ O
sila -X- _ O
. -X- _ O

U-turn -X- _ O
is -X- _ O
da -X- _ O
keyPH -X- _ B-ORG
ARMY -X- _ I-ORG
, -X- _ O
NAGPADALA -X- _ O
OG -X- _ O
DUGANG -X- _ O
NGA -X- _ O
TROPA -X- _ O
SA -X- _ O
NEGOR -X- _ B-LOC
HUMAN -X- _ O
SA -X- _ O
PAGPATAY -X- _ O
NI -X- _ O
GOV. -X- _ O
ROEL -X- _ B-PER
DEGAMOUnom -X- _ I-PER
ka -X- _ O
batalyon -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
Philippine -X- _ B-ORG
Army -X- _ I-ORG
ang -X- _ O
gipadala -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
Negros -X- _ B-LOC
Oriental -X- _ I-LOC
niadtong -X- _ O
Domiggo -X- _ O
, -X- _ O
usa -X- _ O
ka -X- _ O
semana -X- _ O
ang -X- _ O
nilabay -X- _ O
human -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
pagpatay -X- _ O
ni -X- _ O
kanhi -X- _ O
Gov. -X- _ O
Roel -X- _ B-PER
Degamo.Gilangkuban -X- _ I-PER
ang -X- _ O
mga -X- _ O
tropa -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
11th -X- _ O
, -X- _ O
94th -X- _ O
, -X- _ O
79th -X- _ O
, -X- _ O
62nd -X- _ O
, -X- _ O
15th -X- _ O
, -X- _ O
ug -X- _ O
47th -X- _ O
Infantry -X- _ O
Battalions.Ipakatap -X- _ O
ang -X- _ O
mga -X- _ O
personahe -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
kasundalohan -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
ikaduha -X- _ O
ug -X- _ O
ikatulo -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
distrito -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
Negros -X- _ B-LOC
Oriental -X- _ I-LOC
isip -X- _ O
parte -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
pagpaningkamot -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
gobyerno -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
pakusgan -X- _ O
ang -X- _ O
joint -X- _ O
law -X- _ O
enforcement -X- _ O
operations -X- _ O
uban -X- _ O
Philippine -X- _ B-ORG
National -X- _ I-ORG
Police -X- _ I-ORG
( -X- _ O
PNP -X- _ B-ORG
) -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
probinsya.Sumala -X- _ O
pa -X- _ O
ni -X- _ O
AFP -X- _ B-ORG
Visayas -X- _ I-ORG
Command -X- _ I-ORG
( -X- _ O
VISCOM -X- _ B-ORG
) -X- _ O
Commander -X- _ O
Lt. -X- _ O
Gen. -X- _ O
Benedict -X- _ B-PER
Arevalo -X- _ I-PER
, -X- _ O
makigtinabangay -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
PNP -X- _ B-ORG
ang -X- _ O
mga -X- _ O
gipadala -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
tropa -X- _ O
aron -X- _ O
masikop -X- _ O
ang -X- _ O
mga -X- _ O
nipatay -X- _ O
ni -X- _ O
Degamo -X- _ B-PER
ug -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
uban -X- _ O
pang -X- _ O
mga -X- _ O
biktima -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
wala -X- _ O
pa -X- _ O
nadakpan.with -X- _ O
reports -X- _ O
from -X- _ O
ABS-CBN -X- _ O
NewsDenniz -X- _ O
Futalan -X- _ O

# -X- _ O
dumasharesGihatod -X- _ O
na -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
iyang -X- _ O
hometown -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
Bonawon -X- _ B-LOC
, -X- _ I-LOC
Siaton -X- _ I-LOC
ang -X- _ O
patayng -X- _ O
lawas -X- _ O
ni -X- _ O
anhing -X- _ O
Governor -X- _ O
Roel -X- _ B-PER
Degamo. -X- _ I-PER
Samtang -X- _ O
gihatod -X- _ O
kini -X- _ O
didto -X- _ O
, -X- _ O
nanggawas -X- _ O
ang -X- _ O
mga -X- _ O
residente -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
mga -X- _ O
lungsod -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
Bacong -X- _ B-LOC
ug -X- _ O
Dauin -X- _ B-LOC
gisugat -X- _ O
ang -X- _ O
iyang -X- _ O
lungon. -X- _ O
Nagpagawas -X- _ O
sab -X- _ O
sila -X- _ O
og -X- _ O
mga -X- _ O
mensahe -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
pagbangutan -X- _ O
ug -X- _ O
pagpasalamat -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
napatay -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
gobernador -X- _ O
. -X- _ O

NEGOR -X- _ B-LOC
, -X- _ O
GI-BAN -X- _ O
SAB -X- _ O
ANG -X- _ O
PORK -X- _ O
PRODUCTS -X- _ O
GIKAN -X- _ O
SA -X- _ O
CEBUGipahamtang -X- _ B-LOC
sa -X- _ O
provincial -X- _ O
government -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
Negros -X- _ B-LOC
Oriental -X- _ I-LOC
ang -X- _ O
total -X- _ O
ban -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
baboy -X- _ O
ug -X- _ O
uban -X- _ O
pang -X- _ O
produkto -X- _ O
gikan -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
probinsya -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
Cebu -X- _ B-LOC
human -X- _ O
nakatala -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
unang -X- _ O
kaso -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
African -X- _ B-MISC
Swine -X- _ I-MISC
Fever -X- _ I-MISC
sa -X- _ O
Carcar -X- _ B-LOC
City.Mo-epekto -X- _ I-LOC
ang -X- _ O
total -X- _ O
ban -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
mosunod -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
45 -X- _ O
ka -X- _ O
adlaw -X- _ O
base -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
usa -X- _ O
ka -X- _ O
executive -X- _ O
order -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
gi-isyu -X- _ O
niadtong -X- _ O
Mar. -X- _ O
3.Mao -X- _ O
kini -X- _ O
ang -X- _ O
gibutyag -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
chief -X- _ O
operations -X- _ O
officer -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
Provincial -X- _ B-ORG
Veterinary -X- _ I-ORG
Office -X- _ I-ORG
( -X- _ O
PVO -X- _ B-ORG
) -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
si -X- _ O
Ophelia -X- _ B-PER
Felisilda. -X- _ I-PER
" -X- _ O
( -X- _ O
The -X- _ O
late -X- _ O
) -X- _ O
Governor -X- _ O
Degamo -X- _ B-PER
signed -X- _ O
and -X- _ O
issued -X- _ O
the -X- _ O
executive -X- _ O
order -X- _ O
on -X- _ O
the -X- _ O
total -X- _ O
ban -X- _ O
even -X- _ O
before -X- _ O
the -X- _ O
news -X- _ O
of -X- _ O
the -X- _ O
ASF -X- _ B-MISC
cases -X- _ O
in -X- _ O
Carcar -X- _ B-LOC
City -X- _ I-LOC
came -X- _ O
out -X- _ O
, -X- _ O
to -X- _ O
prevent -X- _ O
the -X- _ O
swine -X- _ O
industry -X- _ O
in -X- _ O
Negros -X- _ B-LOC
Oriental -X- _ I-LOC
from -X- _ O
being -X- _ O
affected -X- _ O
by -X- _ O
the -X- _ O
animal -X- _ O
disease -X- _ O
, -X- _ O
" -X- _ O
sumala -X- _ O
pa -X- _ O
ni -X- _ O
Felisilda.Niadtong -X- _ B-PER
Miyerkules -X- _ O
, -X- _ O
gikompirma -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
Bureau -X- _ B-ORG
of -X- _ I-ORG
Animal -X- _ I-ORG
Industry -X- _ I-ORG
( -X- _ O
BAI -X- _ B-ORG
) -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
Region -X- _ B-LOC
7 -X- _ I-LOC
ang -X- _ O
unang -X- _ O
kaso -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
ASF -X- _ B-MISC
sa -X- _ O
Carcar -X- _ B-LOC
City -X- _ I-LOC
, -X- _ O
human -X- _ O
58 -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
149 -X- _ O
ka -X- _ O
pig -X- _ O
blood -X- _ O
samples -X- _ O
ang -X- _ O
nagpositibo -X- _ O
niadtong -X- _ O
Mar. -X- _ O
1 -X- _ O
. -X- _ O

Ubos -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
directiba -X- _ O
ni -X- _ O
mayor -X- _ O
Pepe -X- _ B-PER
Abiera -X- _ I-PER
uban -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
Ldrrmo -X- _ B-ORG
Sibulan -X- _ I-ORG
atong -X- _ O
gibisita -X- _ O
kagahapon -X- _ O
ang -X- _ O
twin -X- _ B-LOC
lake -X- _ I-LOC
Balinsasayao -X- _ I-LOC
aron -X- _ O
iverify -X- _ O
ang -X- _ O
report -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
gipa -X- _ O
abot -X- _ O
ni -X- _ O
sir -X- _ O
Rico -X- _ B-PER
Mier -X- _ I-PER
discoloration -X- _ O
niini -X- _ O
ug -X- _ O
adunay -X- _ O
baho -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
sulfur -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
palibot. -X- _ O
Ug -X- _ O
tuod -X- _ O
man -X- _ O
atong -X- _ O
nakita -X- _ O
didto -X- _ O
ang -X- _ O
kausbanan. -X- _ O
Ato -X- _ O
pong -X- _ O
na -X- _ O
abtan -X- _ O
ang -X- _ O
mga -X- _ O
taga -X- _ O
DENR -X- _ B-ORG
nagkuha -X- _ O
usab -X- _ O
ug -X- _ O
water -X- _ O
samples -X- _ O
aron -X- _ O
paghimo -X- _ O
ug -X- _ O
dugang -X- _ O
pag -X- _ O
tuon. -X- _ O
Matod -X- _ O
pod -X- _ O
ni -X- _ O
Engr -X- _ O
Mulac -X- _ B-PER
sa -X- _ O
Phivolcs -X- _ B-ORG
wala -X- _ O
sab -X- _ O
silay -X- _ O
namatikdan -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
seismic -X- _ O
activity -X- _ O
diri -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
atong -X- _ O
palibot -X- _ O
ug -X- _ O
ni -X- _ O
recommendar -X- _ O
siya -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
pag -X- _ O
paabot -X- _ O
niini -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
mga -X- _ O
Phivolcs -X- _ B-LOC
national -X- _ I-LOC
office -X- _ I-LOC
aron -X- _ O
makapadala -X- _ O
ug -X- _ O
mga -X- _ O
experto -X- _ O
gikan -X- _ O
volcanology -X- _ O
section -X- _ O
aron -X- _ O
maka -X- _ O
himo -X- _ O
pa -X- _ O
ug -X- _ O
dugang -X- _ O
pag -X- _ O
tuon -X- _ O
niini. -X- _ O
Matod -X- _ O
pa -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
mga -X- _ O
locals -X- _ O
didto -X- _ O
adunay -X- _ O
susamang -X- _ O
pang -X- _ O
hitabo -X- _ O
ni -X- _ O
adto -X- _ O
pang -X- _ O
2007. -X- _ O
Ato -X- _ O
sab -X- _ O
kini -X- _ O
gipa -X- _ O
abot -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
SB -X- _ B-ORG
ug -X- _ O
gi -X- _ O
actionan -X- _ O
dayon -X- _ O
kini -X- _ O
ni -X- _ O
vice -X- _ O
mayor -X- _ O
Dirkie -X- _ B-PER
Fontelo -X- _ I-PER
pina -X- _ O
agi -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
pag -X- _ O
assign -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
comitiba -X- _ O
ug -X- _ O
pag -X- _ O
imbitar -X- _ O
ug -X- _ O
local -X- _ O
experts -X- _ O
aron -X- _ O
maghimo -X- _ O
ug -X- _ O
dugang -X- _ O
pag -X- _ O
tuon.Salamat -X- _ O
sir -X- _ O
Rico -X- _ B-PER
, -X- _ O
DENR -X- _ B-ORG
UG -X- _ O
PHIVOLCS -X- _ B-ORG
. -X- _ O

LOOK -X- _ O
: -X- _ O
Nagbangga -X- _ O
ang -X- _ O
Maayo -X- _ B-ORG
Shipping -X- _ I-ORG
Roro -X- _ O
ug -X- _ O
Petro -X- _ B-MISC
Helen -X- _ I-MISC
Tanker -X- _ I-MISC
sa -X- _ O
Tampi -X- _ B-LOC
Port -X- _ I-LOC
, -X- _ I-LOC
San -X- _ I-LOC
Jose -X- _ I-LOC
sa -X- _ O
Negros -X- _ B-LOC
Oriental -X- _ I-LOC
mga -X- _ O
9:30 -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
buntag -X- _ O
karong -X- _ O
adlawa -X- _ O
, -X- _ O
March -X- _ O
7 -X- _ O
, -X- _ O
2023.Sa -X- _ O
pagkakaron -X- _ O
, -X- _ O
dili -X- _ O
pa -X- _ O
klaro -X- _ O
ang -X- _ O
hinungdan -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
insidente -X- _ O
apan -X- _ O
wala'y -X- _ O
natala -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
naangol -X- _ O
kon -X- _ O
oil -X- _ O
spill. -X- _ O
Caption -X- _ O
via -X- _ O
yes -X- _ O
the -X- _ O
best -X- _ O

VICE -X- _ O
GOV. -X- _ O
CHACO -X- _ B-PER
SAGARBARRIA -X- _ I-PER
MIBISITA -X- _ O
SA -X- _ O
HAYA -X- _ O
NI -X- _ O
ANHING -X- _ O
NEG -X- _ B-LOC
OR -X- _ I-LOC
GOV. -X- _ O
ROEL -X- _ B-PER
RAGAY -X- _ I-PER
DEGAMO. -X- _ I-PER
MARCH -X- _ O
5 -X- _ O
, -X- _ O
2023Via -X- _ O
Negor -X- _ O
Balita -X- _ O

BREAKING -X- _ O
NEWS -X- _ O
and -X- _ O
LATEST -X- _ O
UPDATENegros -X- _ B-LOC
Oriental -X- _ I-LOC
Governor -X- _ O
Roel -X- _ B-PER
Degamo -X- _ I-PER
was -X- _ O
pronounced -X- _ O
dead -X- _ O
at -X- _ O
11:41am -X- _ O
today.GOVERNOR -X- _ O
DEGAMO -X- _ B-PER
SA -X- _ O
NEGROS -X- _ B-LOC
ORIENTAL -X- _ I-LOC
PATAY -X- _ O
SA -X- _ O
PAGPAMUSIL -X- _ O
! -X- _ O
Gisuwayan -X- _ O
pa -X- _ O
og -X- _ O
revive -X- _ O
si -X- _ O
Negros -X- _ B-LOC
Oriental -X- _ I-LOC
Roel -X- _ B-PER
Ragay -X- _ I-PER
Degamo -X- _ I-PER
apan -X- _ O
nakabsan -X- _ O
gayud -X- _ O
kini -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
kinabuhi -X- _ O
human -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
adunay -X- _ O
mga -X- _ O
armadong -X- _ O
tawo -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
mibanhig -X- _ O
niini -X- _ O
kaganihang -X- _ O
pasado -X- _ O
alas -X- _ O
10 -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
kabuntagon -X- _ O
didto -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
iyang -X- _ O
panimalay -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
Nuebe -X- _ B-LOC
, -X- _ I-LOC
Pamplona. -X- _ I-LOC
Gikataho -X- _ O
usab -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
patay -X- _ O
ang -X- _ O
5 -X- _ O
ka -X- _ O
mga -X- _ O
sakop -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
iyang -X- _ O
security -X- _ O
og -X- _ O
uban -X- _ O
na -X- _ O
civilian -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
pagpamusil.Mao -X- _ O
ni -X- _ O
ang -X- _ O
sitwasyon -X- _ O
human -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
pagsulod -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
mga -X- _ O
armadong -X- _ O
tawo -X- _ O
didto -X- _ O
mismo -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
panimalay -X- _ O
ni -X- _ O
Negros -X- _ B-LOC
Oriental -X- _ I-LOC
Governor -X- _ O
Roel -X- _ B-PER
Degamo -X- _ I-PER
sa -X- _ O
Nuebe -X- _ B-LOC
Pamplona -X- _ I-LOC
. -X- _ O

Developing -X- _ O
story -X- _ O
? -X- _ O
? -X- _ O
UPDATE -X- _ O
: -X- _ O
Gov. -X- _ O
Degamo -X- _ B-PER
was -X- _ O
pronounced -X- _ O
dead -X- _ O
at -X- _ O
11:41 -X- _ O
am -X- _ O
today-5 -X- _ O
KA -X- _ O
SIBILYAN -X- _ O
PATAY -X- _ O
SAMTANG -X- _ O
GOV. -X- _ O
DEGAMO -X- _ B-PER
SA -X- _ O
NEGROS -X- _ B-LOC
ORIENTAL -X- _ I-LOC
ANGOL -X- _ O
SA -X- _ O
STRAFING -X- _ O
Gikataho -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
lima -X- _ O
ka -X- _ O
sibilyan -X- _ O
ang -X- _ O
patay -X- _ O
ug -X- _ O
samaron -X- _ O
si -X- _ O
Negros -X- _ B-LOC
Oriental -X- _ I-LOC
Gov. -X- _ O
Roel -X- _ B-PER
Ragay -X- _ I-PER
Degamo -X- _ I-PER
ug -X- _ O
duha -X- _ O
niini -X- _ O
ka -X- _ O
Police -X- _ O
Escort -X- _ O
human -X- _ O
gi -X- _ O
Straffing -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
nagpaka -X- _ O
aron -X- _ O
ingnon -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
mga -X- _ O
pulis. -X- _ O
Nagpahigayon -X- _ O
ug -X- _ O
usa -X- _ O
ka -X- _ O
pulong-pulong -X- _ O
ang -X- _ O
gobernador -X- _ O
kaganiha -X- _ O
mga -X- _ O
alas -X- _ O
9:40 -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
lungsod -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
Pamplona -X- _ B-LOC
, -X- _ I-LOC
Negros -X- _ I-LOC
Oriental. -X- _ I-LOC
Sigon -X- _ O
pa -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
mga -X- _ O
naka -X- _ O
saksi -X- _ O
, -X- _ O
naputos -X- _ O
ug -X- _ O
samad -X- _ O
pinusilan -X- _ O
ang -X- _ O
gobernador -X- _ O
uban -X- _ O
ang -X- _ O
escort -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
sila -X- _ O
si -X- _ O
PFC -X- _ O
Malunes -X- _ B-PER
ug -X- _ O
Sgt. -X- _ O
Sayon. -X- _ B-PER
Ang -X- _ O
gisakyan -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
mga -X- _ O
armadong -X- _ O
mipusil -X- _ O
duha -X- _ O
ka -X- _ O
SUV -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
Montero -X- _ B-MISC