-DOCSTART- -X- O
Aduna'y -X- _ O
pagsaka -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
presyo -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
lana -X- _ O
, -X- _ O
epektibo -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
Martes -X- _ O
, -X- _ O
Hunyo -X- _ O
27 -X- _ O
, -X- _ O
2023 -X- _ O
. -X- _ O

MOTORISTA -X- _ O
, -X- _ O
PATAY -X- _ O
HUMAN -X- _ O
MALIGSAN -X- _ O
ANG -X- _ O
ULO -X- _ O
SA -X- _ O
10-WHEELER -X- _ O
DUMP -X- _ O
TRUCK -X- _ O
Patay -X- _ O
ang -X- _ O
usa -X- _ O
ka -X- _ O
motorista -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
usa -X- _ O
ka -X- _ O
vehicular -X- _ O
accident -X- _ O
ang -X- _ O
nahitabo -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
Barangay -X- _ B-LOC
Caidiocan -X- _ I-LOC
sa -X- _ O
Valencia -X- _ B-LOC
mga -X- _ O
alas-6:20 -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
gabii -X- _ O
niadtong -X- _ O
Sabado -X- _ O
, -X- _ O
Hunyo -X- _ O
24,2023. -X- _ O
Giila -X- _ O
ang -X- _ O
biktima -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
si -X- _ O
Ruperto -X- _ B-PER
Solamillo -X- _ I-PER
Ausejo -X- _ I-PER
Jr. -X- _ I-PER
, -X- _ O
46 -X- _ O
anyos -X- _ O
, -X- _ O
ulitawo -X- _ O
, -X- _ O
ug -X- _ O
lumolupyo -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
Barangay -X- _ B-LOC
Pulang -X- _ I-LOC
Bato -X- _ I-LOC
sa -X- _ O
naasoy -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
lungsod. -X- _ O
Sumala -X- _ O
pa -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
imbestigasyon -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
kapulisan -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
Valencia -X- _ B-LOC
, -X- _ O
nagbiyahe -X- _ O
ang -X- _ O
duha -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
managlahing -X- _ O
direksyon. -X- _ O
Pag-abot -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
nahisgutang -X- _ O
lugar -X- _ O
, -X- _ O
ni-overtake -X- _ O
si -X- _ O
Ausejo -X- _ B-PER
sa -X- _ O
truck -X- _ O
ug -X- _ O
nawad-an -X- _ O
og -X- _ O
kontrol -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
gimanehong -X- _ O
motorsiklo -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
niresulta -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
iyang -X- _ O
pagkatumba -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
karsada. -X- _ O
Tungod -X- _ O
niini -X- _ O
, -X- _ O
aksidenteng -X- _ O
naligsan -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
10-wheeler -X- _ O
dump -X- _ O
truck -X- _ O
ang -X- _ O
ulo -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
biktima -X- _ O
hinungdan -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
iyang -X- _ O
hinanaling -X- _ O
kamatayon -X- _ O
. -X- _ O

9 -X- _ O
KA -X- _ O
MAYOR -X- _ O
SA -X- _ O
NEGOR -X- _ B-LOC
, -X- _ O
NANAWAGAN -X- _ O
NGA -X- _ O
I-POSTPONE -X- _ O
ANG -X- _ O
BARANGAY -X- _ O
, -X- _ O
SK -X- _ B-OTHER
ELECTION -X- _ I-OTHER
Nipadayag -X- _ O
og -X- _ O
suporta -X- _ O
ang -X- _ O
siyam -X- _ O
ka -X- _ O
mga -X- _ O
mayor -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
Negros -X- _ B-LOC
Oriental -X- _ I-LOC
sa -X- _ O
sugyot -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
i-postpone -X- _ O
ang -X- _ O
eleksyon -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
Barangay -X- _ O
ug -X- _ O
Sangguniang -X- _ B-ORG
Kabataan -X- _ I-ORG
( -X- _ I-ORG
SK -X- _ I-ORG
) -X- _ I-ORG
sa -X- _ O
probinsya -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
gitakda -X- _ O
karong -X- _ O
Oktubre. -X- _ O
Ilang -X- _ O
gisubli -X- _ O
ang -X- _ O
mga -X- _ O
kabalaka -X- _ O
bahin -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
seguridad -X- _ O
lakip -X- _ O
na -X- _ O
ang -X- _ O
" -X- _ O
deep-rooted -X- _ O
fear -X- _ O
" -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
mga -X- _ O
residente -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
probinsya -X- _ O
human -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
pagpatay -X- _ O
kang -X- _ O
Gov. -X- _ O
Roel -X- _ B-PER
Degamo. -X- _ I-PER
Lakip -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
mga -X- _ O
nipirma -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
manipesto -X- _ O
ang -X- _ O
biyuda -X- _ O
ni -X- _ O
Degamo -X- _ B-PER
nga -X- _ O
si -X- _ O
Janice -X- _ O
Degamo -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
Pamplona -X- _ B-LOC
, -X- _ O
iyang -X- _ O
pag-umangkon -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
si -X- _ O
Fritz -X- _ B-PER
Diaz -X- _ I-PER
sa -X- _ O
Siaton -X- _ B-LOC
, -X- _ O
ug -X- _ O
mga -X- _ O
kaalyado -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
sila -X- _ O
si -X- _ O
Felipe -X- _ B-PER
Remollo -X- _ I-PER
sa -X- _ O
Dumaguete -X- _ B-LOC
City -X- _ I-LOC
, -X- _ O
Galicano -X- _ B-PER
Truita -X- _ I-PER
sa -X- _ O
Dauin -X- _ B-LOC
, -X- _ O
Mel -X- _ B-PER
Nick -X- _ I-PER
Logronio -X- _ I-PER
sa -X- _ O
San -X- _ B-LOC
Jose -X- _ I-LOC
, -X- _ O
Eniego -X- _ B-PER
Jabagat -X- _ I-PER
sa -X- _ O
Bindoy -X- _ B-LOC
, -X- _ O
Dennis -X- _ B-PER
Amancio -X- _ I-PER
sa -X- _ O
Ayungon -X- _ B-LOC
, -X- _ O
Filomeno -X- _ B-PER
Reyes -X- _ I-PER
sa -X- _ O
Guihulngan -X- _ B-LOC
City -X- _ I-LOC
, -X- _ O
ug -X- _ O
Susano -X- _ B-PER
Ruperto -X- _ I-PER
sa -X- _ O
Tayasan -X- _ B-LOC
. -X- _ O

LALAKI -X- _ O
SA -X- _ O
INDIA -X- _ B-LOC
, -X- _ O
NIPUYO -X- _ O
OG -X- _ O
DUL-AN -X- _ O
2 -X- _ O
KA -X- _ O
TUIG -X- _ O
SA -X- _ O
USA -X- _ O
KA -X- _ O
5-STAR -X- _ O
HOTEL -X- _ O
NGA -X- _ O
WALA’Y -X- _ O
BAYAD-BAYAD -X- _ O
Usa -X- _ O
ka -X- _ O
lalaki -X- _ O
ang -X- _ O
giimbestigaran -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
kapulisan -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
India -X- _ B-LOC
human -X- _ O
giingong -X- _ O
nagpuyo -X- _ O
kini -X- _ O
og -X- _ O
halos -X- _ O
duha -X- _ O
ka -X- _ O
tuig -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
usa -X- _ O
ka -X- _ O
five-star -X- _ O
hotel -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
New -X- _ B-LOC
Delhi -X- _ I-LOC
nga -X- _ O
wala'y -X- _ O
bayad-bayad. -X- _ O
Nag-book -X- _ O
og -X- _ O
kwarto -X- _ O
si -X- _ O
Ankush -X- _ B-PER
Dutta -X- _ I-PER
sa -X- _ O
Roseate -X- _ B-LOC
House -X- _ I-LOC
hotel -X- _ I-LOC
niadtong -X- _ O
May -X- _ O
30 -X- _ O
, -X- _ O
2019 -X- _ O
ug -X- _ O
mo-check -X- _ O
out -X- _ O
unta -X- _ O
dayon -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
sunod -X- _ O
adlaw. -X- _ O
Apan -X- _ O
na-extend -X- _ O
kini -X- _ O
og -X- _ O
603 -X- _ O
ka -X- _ O
mga -X- _ O
adlaw -X- _ O
hangtod -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
iyang -X- _ O
pagbiya -X- _ O
niadtong -X- _ O
Jan. -X- _ O
22 -X- _ O
, -X- _ O
2021 -X- _ O
, -X- _ O
ug -X- _ O
gibiyaan -X- _ O
ang -X- _ O
iyang -X- _ O
$ -X- _ O
70,000 -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
balayran. -X- _ O
Nipasaka -X- _ O
og -X- _ O
reklamo -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
kapulisan -X- _ O
ang -X- _ O
hotel -X- _ O
managers -X- _ O
kontra -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
pipila -X- _ O
ka -X- _ O
mga -X- _ O
empleyado -X- _ O
niini -X- _ O
tungod -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
" -X- _ O
conspiracy -X- _ O
, -X- _ O
forgery -X- _ O
and -X- _ O
cheating. -X- _ O
" -X- _ O
Dugang -X- _ O
pa -X- _ O
, -X- _ O
giingong -X- _ O
gisuholan -X- _ O
ni -X- _ O
Dutta -X- _ B-PER
ang -X- _ O
pipila -X- _ O
ka -X- _ O
mga -X- _ O
kawani -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
hotel -X- _ O
aron -X- _ O
pagmaniobra -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
in-house -X- _ O
software -X- _ O
systems -X- _ O
. -X- _ O

Mao -X- _ O
kini -X- _ O
ang -X- _ O
hulagyway -X- _ O
ni -X- _ O
President -X- _ O
Ferdinand -X- _ B-PER
Marcos -X- _ I-PER
Jr. -X- _ I-PER
uban -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
pipila -X- _ O
ka -X- _ O
mga -X- _ O
lokal -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
opisyales -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
probinsya -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
Negros -X- _ B-LOC
Oriental. -X- _ I-LOC
Nakigpulong -X- _ O
ang -X- _ O
presidente -X- _ O
aron -X- _ O
hisgutan -X- _ O
ang -X- _ O
mga -X- _ O
isyu -X- _ O
bahin -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
kalambuan -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
probinsya. -X- _ O
Lakip -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
mga -X- _ O
nakigpulong -X- _ O
ni -X- _ O
Marcos -X- _ B-PER
mao -X- _ O
sila -X- _ O
si -X- _ O
San -X- _ B-LOC
Jose -X- _ I-LOC
Mayor -X- _ O
Mel -X- _ B-PER
Nick -X- _ I-PER
Logronio -X- _ I-PER
, -X- _ O
Pamplona -X- _ B-LOC
Mayor -X- _ O
Janice -X- _ B-PER
Degamo -X- _ I-PER
, -X- _ O
ug -X- _ O
Siaton -X- _ B-LOC
Mayor -X- _ O
Fritz -X- _ B-PER
Diaz -X- _ I-PER
. -X- _ O

STATE -X- _ O
OF -X- _ O
CALAMITY -X- _ O
SA -X- _ O
TIBUOK -X- _ O
PILIPINAS -X- _ O
TUNGOD -X- _ O
SA -X- _ O
ASF -X- _ B-OTHER
, -X- _ O
GITUN-AN -X- _ O
Gitun-an -X- _ O
karon -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
Department -X- _ B-ORG
of -X- _ I-ORG
Agriculture -X- _ I-ORG
( -X- _ I-ORG
DA -X- _ I-ORG
) -X- _ I-ORG
ang -X- _ O
pagsugyot -X- _ O
ngadto -X- _ O
ni -X- _ O
Pres. -X- _ O
Ferdinand -X- _ B-PER
Marcos -X- _ I-PER
Jr. -X- _ I-PER
nga -X- _ O
magdeklarar -X- _ O
og -X- _ O
state -X- _ O
of -X- _ O
calamity -X- _ O
taliwala -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
pagkaylap -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
African -X- _ B-OTHER
Swine -X- _ I-OTHER
Fever -X- _ I-OTHER
( -X- _ I-OTHER
ASF -X- _ I-OTHER
) -X- _ I-OTHER
sa -X- _ O
nasud. -X- _ O
Sumala -X- _ O
pa -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
tigpamaba -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
DA -X- _ B-ORG
nga -X- _ O
si -X- _ O
Kristine -X- _ B-PER
Evangelista -X- _ I-PER
, -X- _ O
nakigkoordinar -X- _ O
na -X- _ O
ang -X- _ O
ilang -X- _ O
ahensya -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
Bureau -X- _ B-ORG
of -X- _ I-ORG
Animal -X- _ I-ORG
Industry -X- _ I-ORG
( -X- _ I-ORG
BAI -X- _ I-ORG
) -X- _ I-ORG
aron -X- _ O
pagpangita -X- _ O
og -X- _ O
mga -X- _ O
pamaagi -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
matabangan -X- _ O
ang -X- _ O
mga -X- _ O
hog -X- _ O
raiser -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
makakuha -X- _ O
og -X- _ O
ASF -X- _ B-OTHER
vaccines. -X- _ O
Gisubli -X- _ O
sab -X- _ O
ni -X- _ O
Evangelista -X- _ B-PER
nga -X- _ O
nagpatuman -X- _ O
na -X- _ O
sila -X- _ O
og -X- _ O
dugang -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
mga -X- _ O
lakang -X- _ O
aron -X- _ O
mapunggan -X- _ O
ang -X- _ O
pagkuyanap -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
swine -X- _ O
disease. -X- _ O
Matud -X- _ O
pa -X- _ O
ni -X- _ O
BAI -X- _ B-ORG
assistant -X- _ O
director -X- _ O
Arlene -X- _ B-PER
Vytiaco -X- _ I-PER
, -X- _ O
plano -X- _ O
sab -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
ilang -X- _ O
ahensya -X- _ O
ang -X- _ O
pagpalit -X- _ O
og -X- _ O
600,000 -X- _ O
doses -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
ASF -X- _ B-OTHER
vaccines -X- _ O
karong -X- _ O
tuiga -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
dihang -X- _ O
maka-isyu -X- _ O
na -X- _ O
ang -X- _ O
Food -X- _ B-ORG
and -X- _ I-ORG
Drug -X- _ I-ORG
Administration -X- _ I-ORG
og -X- _ O
certificate -X- _ O
of -X- _ O
product -X- _ O
registration -X- _ O
. -X- _ O

MGA -X- _ O
HAYOP -X- _ O
SA -X- _ O
AMLAN -X- _ B-LOC
ZOO -X- _ I-LOC
, -X- _ O
IBALHIN -X- _ O
SA -X- _ O
AKLAN -X- _ B-LOC
Dal-on -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
usa -X- _ O
ka -X- _ O
private -X- _ O
farm -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
Bukid -X- _ B-LOC
Tigayon -X- _ I-LOC
Kalibo -X- _ I-LOC
, -X- _ I-LOC
Aklan -X- _ I-LOC
ang -X- _ O
mga -X- _ O
hayop -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
Amlan -X- _ B-ORG
Nature -X- _ I-ORG
and -X- _ I-ORG
Adventure -X- _ I-ORG
Park. -X- _ I-ORG
Ang -X- _ O
tag-iya -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
Kalibo -X- _ B-LOC
Ostrich -X- _ I-LOC
Farm -X- _ I-LOC
nga -X- _ O
si -X- _ O
Ramon -X- _ B-PER
Dio -X- _ I-PER
ang -X- _ O
mobalhin -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
kapin -X- _ O
80 -X- _ O
ka -X- _ O
mga -X- _ O
hayop -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
maong -X- _ O
farm -X- _ O
kaabag -X- _ O
ang -X- _ O
Department -X- _ B-ORG
of -X- _ I-ORG
Environment -X- _ I-ORG
and -X- _ I-ORG
Natural -X- _ I-ORG
Resources -X- _ I-ORG
( -X- _ I-ORG
DENR -X- _ I-ORG
) -X- _ I-ORG
. -X- _ O
Nahibaloan -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
ang -X- _ O
maong -X- _ O
farm -X- _ O
nagkulang -X- _ O
og -X- _ O
supply -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
pagkaon -X- _ O
hinungdan -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
ang -X- _ O
maong -X- _ O
mga -X- _ O
hayop -X- _ O
nagniwang -X- _ O
ug -X- _ O
nagkasakit -X- _ O
. -X- _ O

16 -X- _ O
KA -X- _ O
BULAN -X- _ O
NGA -X- _ O
BATA -X- _ O
, -X- _ O
PATAY -X- _ O
HUMAN -X- _ O
GIBIYAAN -X- _ O
OG -X- _ O
8 -X- _ O
KA -X- _ O
ADLAW -X- _ O
SA -X- _ O
INAHAN -X- _ O
ARON -X- _ O
MAGBAKASYON -X- _ O
Patay -X- _ O
na -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
napalgan -X- _ O
ang -X- _ O
usa -X- _ O
ka -X- _ O
16 -X- _ O
ka -X- _ O
bulan -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
batang -X- _ O
babayi -X- _ O
human -X- _ O
giingong -X- _ O
gibiyaan -X- _ O
siya -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
nag-inusara -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
iyang -X- _ O
inahan -X- _ O
sulod -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
walo -X- _ O
ka -X- _ O
adlaw -X- _ O
samtang -X- _ O
kini -X- _ O
nagbakasyon. -X- _ O
Gidakop -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
kapulisan -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
Ohio -X- _ B-LOC
ang -X- _ O
inahan -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
bata -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
si -X- _ O
Kristel -X- _ B-PER
Candelario -X- _ I-PER
, -X- _ O
31 -X- _ O
anyos. -X- _ O
Sumala -X- _ O
pa -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
awtoridad -X- _ O
, -X- _ O
napalgan -X- _ O
ni -X- _ O
Candelario -X- _ B-PER
ang -X- _ O
iyang -X- _ O
anak -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
wala -X- _ O
na'y -X- _ O
kinabuhi -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
dihang -X- _ O
nipauli -X- _ O
siya -X- _ O
gikan -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
Puerto -X- _ B-LOC
Rico. -X- _ I-LOC
Bisan -X- _ O
pa -X- _ O
man -X- _ O
wala -X- _ O
gipagawas -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
medical -X- _ O
examiner -X- _ O
ang -X- _ O
hinungdan -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
kamatayon -X- _ O
, -X- _ O
gisubli -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
imbestigador -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
grabe -X- _ O
ka -X- _ O
dehydrated -X- _ O
ang -X- _ O
bata. -X- _ O
Matud -X- _ O
pa -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
kapulisan -X- _ O
, -X- _ O
gibutyag -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
mga -X- _ O
silingan -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
ang -X- _ O
lola -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
bata -X- _ O
mao'y -X- _ O
kalagmitang -X- _ O
magbantay -X- _ O
niini -X- _ O
tungod -X- _ O
hilig -X- _ O
gyud -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
mogawas -X- _ O
ang -X- _ O
inahan -X- _ O
niini. -X- _ O
Pasakaan -X- _ O
og -X- _ O
kasong -X- _ O
pagpatay -X- _ O
ug -X- _ O
multa -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
$ -X- _ O
1 -X- _ O
milyones -X- _ O
si -X- _ O
Candelario -X- _ B-PER
. -X- _ O

NEGROS -X- _ B-ORG
ORIENTAL -X- _ I-ORG
PROVINCIAL -X- _ I-ORG
HOSPITAL -X- _ I-ORG
, -X- _ O
NASUPLAYAN -X- _ O
OG -X- _ O
P10-M -X- _ O
NGA -X- _ O
DUGANG -X- _ O
TAMBAL -X- _ O
Naabot -X- _ O
na -X- _ O
kagahapong -X- _ O
adlawa -X- _ O
ang -X- _ O
mga -X- _ O
stock -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
medisina -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
nagkantidad -X- _ O
og -X- _ O
P10 -X- _ O
milyones -X- _ O
isip -X- _ O
paghatag -X- _ O
og -X- _ O
pagtagad -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
suplay -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
tambal -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
ospital -X- _ O
ning -X- _ O
probinsya. -X- _ O
Dali -X- _ O
kining -X- _ O
gipapalit -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
kagamhanan -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
probinsya -X- _ O
aron -X- _ O
aduna'y -X- _ O
dugang -X- _ O
suplay -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
tambal -X- _ O
ang -X- _ O
Negros -X- _ B-ORG
Oriental -X- _ I-ORG
Provincial -X- _ I-ORG
Hospital -X- _ I-ORG
ug -X- _ O
mahatag -X- _ O
kini -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
mga -X- _ O
gakinahanglan -X- _ O
niini -X- _ O
. -X- _ O

Wala -X- _ O
pa'y -X- _ O
nakadaog -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
kapin -X- _ O
P292 -X- _ O
milyones -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
jackpot -X- _ O
prize -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
Ultra -X- _ B-OTHER
Lotto -X- _ I-OTHER
6 -X- _ I-OTHER
/ -X- _ I-OTHER
58. -X- _ I-OTHER
Sumala -X- _ O
pa -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
PCSO -X- _ B-ORG
, -X- _ O
wala'y -X- _ O
nakakuha -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
winning -X- _ O
combination -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
draw -X- _ O
niini -X- _ O
niadtong -X- _ O
Martes -X- _ O
, -X- _ O
Hunyo -X- _ O
20 -X- _ O
, -X- _ O
2023 -X- _ O
. -X- _ O

GIINGONG -X- _ O
ILLEGAL -X- _ O
QUARRY -X- _ O
SA -X- _ O
NEGROS -X- _ B-LOC
ORIENTAL -X- _ I-LOC
, -X- _ O
NADAKPAN -X- _ O
Nasikop -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
Criminal -X- _ B-ORG
Investigation -X- _ I-ORG
and -X- _ I-ORG
Detection -X- _ I-ORG
Group -X- _ I-ORG
( -X- _ I-ORG
CIDG-PNP -X- _ I-ORG
) -X- _ I-ORG
ang -X- _ O
giingong -X- _ O
illegal -X- _ O
quarry -X- _ O
operation -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
gikatahong -X- _ O
doul -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
dakbayan -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
Dumaguete. -X- _ B-LOC
Kini -X- _ O
human -X- _ O
gimandoan -X- _ O
ni -X- _ O
Negros -X- _ B-LOC
Oriental -X- _ I-LOC
Gov. -X- _ O
Manuel -X- _ B-PER
" -X- _ I-PER
Chaco -X- _ I-PER
" -X- _ I-PER
Sagarbarria -X- _ I-PER
ang -X- _ O
kapulisan -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
paglanat -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
mga -X- _ O
illegal -X- _ O
quarry -X- _ O
operation. -X- _ O
Usa -X- _ O
kini -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
mga -X- _ O
dagkong -X- _ O
polisiya -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
ipatuman -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
probinsya -X- _ O
aron -X- _ O
pagpreserbar -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
kinaiyahan. -X- _ O
Ang -X- _ O
direktiba -X- _ O
pinaagi -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
usa -X- _ O
ka -X- _ O
Memorandum -X- _ O
Order -X- _ O
nag-ingon -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
" -X- _ O
pursuant -X- _ O
to -X- _ O
the -X- _ O
Local -X- _ O
Government -X- _ O
Code -X- _ O
, -X- _ O
the -X- _ O
provincial -X- _ O
Governor -X- _ O
has -X- _ O
the -X- _ O
exclusive -X- _ O
authority -X- _ O
to -X- _ O
issue -X- _ O
permit -X- _ O
to -X- _ O
extract -X- _ O
sand -X- _ O
, -X- _ O
gravel -X- _ O
, -X- _ O
and -X- _ O
other -X- _ O
quarry -X- _ O
resources. -X- _ O
" -X- _ O
Masiguro -X- _ O
niini -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
hugot -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
masunod -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
tanang -X- _ O
quarry -X- _ O
operators -X- _ O
ug -X- _ O
ilang -X- _ O
operasyon -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
probinsya -X- _ O
ang -X- _ O
mga -X- _ O
lagda -X- _ O
ug -X- _ O
regulasyon -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
quarry -X- _ O
permit -X- _ O
. -X- _ O

JOB -X- _ O
ORDER -X- _ O
UG -X- _ O
CONTRACT -X- _ O
OF -X- _ O
SERVICE -X- _ O
WORKERS -X- _ O
SA -X- _ O
DGTE -X- _ B-LOC
, -X- _ O
MAKADAWAT -X- _ O
OG -X- _ O
25KG -X- _ O
NGA -X- _ O
BUGAS -X- _ O
Makadawat -X- _ O
og -X- _ O
25kg -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
ayudang -X- _ O
bugas -X- _ O
ang -X- _ O
matag -X- _ O
usa -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
1,510 -X- _ O
ka -X- _ O
mga -X- _ O
Contract -X- _ B-OTHER
of -X- _ I-OTHER
Service -X- _ I-OTHER
ug -X- _ O
Job -X- _ O
Order -X- _ O
workers -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
LGU-Dumaguete -X- _ B-ORG
karong -X- _ O
Miyerkules -X- _ O
ug -X- _ O
Huwebes -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
City -X- _ O
Hall -X- _ O
Grounds. -X- _ O
Sa -X- _ O
usa -X- _ O
ka -X- _ O
memorandum -X- _ O
, -X- _ O
gisiguro -X- _ O
sab -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
magpadayon -X- _ O
ang -X- _ O
operasyon -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
kagamhanang -X- _ O
syudad -X- _ O
ug -X- _ O
kahapsay -X- _ O
niini -X- _ O
atol -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
naasoy -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
mga -X- _ O
adlaw -X- _ O
. -X- _ O

PLDT -X- _ B-ORG
, -X- _ O
NAGSUGYOT -X- _ O
OG -X- _ O
PAMAAGI -X- _ O
ARON -X- _ O
MAPAKUSGAN -X- _ O
ANG -X- _ O
CCTV -X- _ O
SA -X- _ O
DUMAGUETE -X- _ B-LOC
; -X- _ O
POSIBLENG -X- _ O
MAGTAOD -X- _ O
SAB -X- _ O
OG -X- _ O
PUBLIC -X- _ O
WIFI -X- _ O
UG -X- _ O
TRAFFIC -X- _ O
LIGHTS -X- _ O
Gisugyot -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
Philippine -X- _ B-ORG
Long -X- _ I-ORG
Distance -X- _ I-ORG
Incorporated -X- _ I-ORG
( -X- _ B-ORG
PLDT -X- _ I-ORG
) -X- _ I-ORG
uban -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
Fortinet -X- _ B-ORG
ang -X- _ O
ilang -X- _ O
gi-bundle -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
high -X- _ O
grade -X- _ O
equipment -X- _ O
uban -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
ilang -X- _ O
lig-on -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
network. -X- _ O
Maminusan -X- _ O
niini -X- _ O
ang -X- _ O
pagkawala -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
feed -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
mga -X- _ O
CCTV -X- _ O
camera -X- _ O
kun -X- _ O
ugaling -X- _ O
maputol -X- _ O
ang -X- _ O
mga -X- _ O
fiber -X- _ O
optic -X- _ O
cable -X- _ O
niini -X- _ O
tungod -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
mga -X- _ O
wala -X- _ O
damhang -X- _ O
insidente. -X- _ O
Gipresentar -X- _ O
kini -X- _ O
nila -X- _ O
ngadto -X- _ O
ni -X- _ O
Mayor -X- _ O
Felipe -X- _ B-PER
Remollo -X- _ I-PER
ug -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
ubang -X- _ O
hingtungdan -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
kawani -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
LGU. -X- _ B-ORG
Kung -X- _ O
maaprobahan -X- _ O
ang -X- _ O
gisugyot -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
solusyon -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
Fortiner -X- _ B-ORG
SDWAN -X- _ I-ORG
, -X- _ O
magsilbi -X- _ O
sab -X- _ O
kini -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
pamaagi -X- _ O
aron -X- _ O
pag-install -X- _ O
og -X- _ O
public -X- _ O
wifi -X- _ O
ug -X- _ O
intelligent -X- _ O
traffic -X- _ O
lights -X- _ O
systems -X- _ O
. -X- _ O

BABAYI -X- _ O
SA -X- _ O
ECUADOR -X- _ B-LOC
NGA -X- _ O
NAKAMATA -X- _ O
SULOD -X- _ O
SA -X- _ O
IYANG -X- _ O
LUNGON -X- _ O
, -X- _ O
TINUOD -X- _ O
NA -X- _ O
NGA -X- _ O
PATAY -X- _ O
Tinuod -X- _ O
na -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
namatay -X- _ O
ang -X- _ O
usa -X- _ O
ka -X- _ O
tigulang -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
babayi -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
Ecuador -X- _ B-LOC
kinsa -X- _ O
kaniadto -X- _ O
nakamata -X- _ O
sulod -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
usa -X- _ O
ka -X- _ O
lungon -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
iyang -X- _ O
kaugalingong -X- _ O
haya. -X- _ O
Sa -X- _ O
niaging -X- _ O
semana -X- _ O
, -X- _ O
nag-viral -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
social -X- _ O
media -X- _ O
ang -X- _ O
video -X- _ O
ni -X- _ O
Bella -X- _ B-PER
Montoya -X- _ I-PER
, -X- _ O
76 -X- _ O
anyos -X- _ O
, -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
naglisod -X- _ O
og -X- _ O
ginhawa -X- _ O
sulod -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
iyang -X- _ O
lungon -X- _ O
samtang -X- _ O
gitabang -X- _ O
kini -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
duha -X- _ O
ka -X- _ O
lalaki. -X- _ O
Human -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
maong -X- _ O
panghitabo -X- _ O
, -X- _ O
gidala -X- _ O
si -X- _ O
Montoya -X- _ B-PER
sa -X- _ O
usa -X- _ O
ka -X- _ O
ospital -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
lungsod -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
Babahoyo -X- _ B-LOC
aron -X- _ O
ipadayon -X- _ O
ang -X- _ O
pagtambal. -X- _ O
Nasayop -X- _ O
siya -X- _ O
pagdeklarar -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
patay -X- _ O
na -X- _ O
niadtong -X- _ O
Hunyo -X- _ O
9 -X- _ O
, -X- _ O
apan -X- _ O
tinuod -X- _ O
na -X- _ O
kining -X- _ O
namatay -X- _ O
tungod -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
stroke -X- _ O
niadtong -X- _ O
Hunyo -X- _ O
16 -X- _ O
. -X- _ O

LATO-LATO -X- _ O
NO -X- _ O
MORE -X- _ O
! -X- _ O
Nagpahimangno -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
publiko -X- _ O
ang -X- _ O
Food -X- _ B-ORG
and -X- _ I-ORG
Drug -X- _ I-ORG
Administration -X- _ I-ORG
( -X- _ B-ORG
FDA -X- _ I-ORG
) -X- _ I-ORG
nga -X- _ O
dili -X- _ O
mopalit -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
dulaan -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
lato-lato. -X- _ O
Sumala -X- _ O
pa -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
FDA -X- _ B-ORG
, -X- _ O
dili -X- _ O
sigurado -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
luwas -X- _ O
alang -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
mga -X- _ O
bata -X- _ O
ang -X- _ O
maong -X- _ O
dulaan -X- _ O
tungod -X- _ O
wala -X- _ O
kini -X- _ O
moagi -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
quality -X- _ O
testing. -X- _ O
Gisubli -X- _ O
sab -X- _ O
nila -X- _ O
, -X- _ O
walay -X- _ O
certificate -X- _ O
of -X- _ O
notification -X- _ O
ang -X- _ O
maong -X- _ O
produkto -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
usa -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
kinahanglanon -X- _ O
alang -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
pag-apruba -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
pagbaligya -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
merkado. -X- _ O
Gasugod -X- _ O
na -X- _ O
sab -X- _ O
ang -X- _ O
maong -X- _ O
ahensya -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
pagkumpiskar -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
naasoy -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
dulaan -X- _ O
. -X- _ O

637 -X- _ O
KA -X- _ O
EDUCATIONAL -X- _ O
SCHOLAR -X- _ O
SA -X- _ O
NEGOR -X- _ B-ORG
, -X- _ O
HATAGAN -X- _ O
OG -X- _ O
₱5,000 -X- _ O
NGA -X- _ O
AYUDA -X- _ O
KADA -X- _ O
USA -X- _ O
Gipatuman -X- _ O
ni -X- _ O
Gov. -X- _ O
Manuel -X- _ B-PER
" -X- _ I-PER
Chaco -X- _ I-PER
" -X- _ I-PER
Sagarbarria -X- _ I-PER
ang -X- _ O
Educational -X- _ B-OTHER
and -X- _ I-OTHER
Financial -X- _ I-OTHER
Assistance -X- _ I-OTHER
Program -X- _ I-OTHER
sa -X- _ O
637 -X- _ O
ka -X- _ O
mga -X- _ O
scholars -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
probinsya -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
Negros -X- _ B-LOC
Oriental. -X- _ I-LOC
Tumong -X- _ O
niini -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
mapalig-on -X- _ O
ang -X- _ O
scholarship -X- _ O
program -X- _ O
alang -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
mga -X- _ O
" -X- _ O
poor -X- _ O
, -X- _ O
underprivileged -X- _ O
but -X- _ O
deserving -X- _ O
students -X- _ O
" -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
probinsya. -X- _ O
Makadawat -X- _ O
og -X- _ O
P5,000 -X- _ O
kada -X- _ O
semeter -X- _ O
ang -X- _ O
matag -X- _ O
estudyante -X- _ O
, -X- _ O
basta -X- _ O
ilang -X- _ O
imintinar -X- _ O
ang -X- _ O
80 -X- _ O
% -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
general -X- _ O
passing -X- _ O
average. -X- _ O
Hingpit -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
ipatuman -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
gobernador -X- _ O
ang -X- _ O
P10 -X- _ O
milyones -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
pondo -X- _ O
sunod -X- _ O
tuig -X- _ O
ug -X- _ O
pun-on -X- _ O
ang -X- _ O
363 -X- _ O
na -X- _ O
mga -X- _ O
bakante -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
scholarship -X- _ O
program. -X- _ O
Dugang -X- _ O
pa -X- _ O
, -X- _ O
gitinguha -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
gobernador -X- _ O
ang -X- _ O
pagdungag -X- _ O
og -X- _ O
pondo -X- _ O
alang -X- _ O
maong -X- _ O
scholarship -X- _ O
. -X- _ O

DOLE-7 -X- _ B-ORG
, -X- _ O
GIPANGHINGUSGAN -X- _ O
ANG -X- _ O
PAG-MONITOR -X- _ O
SA -X- _ O
MGA -X- _ O
CHILD -X- _ O
LABORER -X- _ O
SA -X- _ O
NEGOR -X- _ B-LOC
Gipanghingusgan -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
Department -X- _ B-ORG
of -X- _ I-ORG
Labor -X- _ I-ORG
and -X- _ I-ORG
Employment -X- _ I-ORG
sa -X- _ O
Region -X- _ B-LOC
7 -X- _ I-LOC
ang -X- _ O
pag-monitor -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
giila -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
mga -X- _ O
child -X- _ O
laborer -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
probinsya -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
Negros -X- _ B-LOC
Oriental -X- _ I-LOC
ug -X- _ O
Siquijor. -X- _ O
Gitaho -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
DOLE-7 -X- _ B-ORG
nga -X- _ O
ilang -X- _ O
gi-monitor -X- _ O
sugod -X- _ O
niadtong -X- _ O
Mayo -X- _ O
ang -X- _ O
239 -X- _ O
ka -X- _ O
mga -X- _ O
child -X- _ O
laborer -X- _ O
ug -X- _ O
ilang -X- _ O
mga -X- _ O
ginikanan -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
munisipalidad -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
Basay -X- _ B-LOC
ug -X- _ O
La -X- _ B-LOC
Libertad -X- _ I-LOC
ug -X- _ O
syudad -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
Bayawan -X- _ B-LOC
ug -X- _ O
Guihulngan. -X- _ B-LOC
Gisubli -X- _ O
nila -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
kaylap -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
naasoy -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
mga -X- _ O
dapit -X- _ O
ang -X- _ O
mga -X- _ O
child -X- _ O
laborer. -X- _ O
Sa -X- _ O
239 -X- _ O
ka -X- _ O
mga -X- _ O
child -X- _ O
laborers -X- _ O
, -X- _ O
104 -X- _ O
ang -X- _ O
gikan -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
Bayawan -X- _ B-LOC
ug -X- _ O
66 -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
La -X- _ B-LOC
Libertad -X- _ I-LOC
, -X- _ O
samtang -X- _ O
49 -X- _ O
ang -X- _ O
natala -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
Guihulngan -X- _ B-LOC
ug -X- _ O
20 -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
Basay. -X- _ B-LOC
Tumong -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
departamento -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
makatabang -X- _ O
pagwagtang -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
insidente -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
child -X- _ O
labor -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
tibuok -X- _ O
nasud -X- _ O
pag-abot -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
2028 -X- _ O
. -X- _ O

Usa -X- _ O
ka -X- _ O
42 -X- _ O
anyos -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
janitress -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
Tuguegarao -X- _ B-LOC
City -X- _ I-LOC
ang -X- _ O
mapasigarbuhon -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
nag-pose -X- _ O
human -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
iyang -X- _ O
klase -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
kindergarten. -X- _ O
Mogradwar -X- _ O
si -X- _ O
Remilyn -X- _ B-PER
Dimla -X- _ I-PER
sa -X- _ O
kindergarten -X- _ O
karong -X- _ O
Hulyo -X- _ O
14 -X- _ O
, -X- _ O
2023 -X- _ O
. -X- _ O

ANGAY -X- _ O
NGA -X- _ O
POSTURA -X- _ O
SA -X- _ O
KAMOT -X- _ O
ATOL -X- _ O
SA -X- _ O
PAG-AMPO -X- _ O
SA -X- _ O
'OUR -X- _ O
FATHER -X- _ O
' -X- _ O
SA -X- _ O
MISA -X- _ O
Nagpagawas -X- _ O
og -X- _ O
usa -X- _ O
ka -X- _ O
sulat -X- _ O
ang -X- _ O
Diocese -X- _ B-ORG
of -X- _ I-ORG
Dumaguete -X- _ I-ORG
mahitungod -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
angay -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
postura -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
kamot -X- _ O
atol -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
pag-ampo -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
" -X- _ O
Our -X- _ O
Father -X- _ O
" -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
mga -X- _ O
misa. -X- _ O
Gisubli -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
obispo -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
masiguro -X- _ O
niini -X- _ O
ang -X- _ O
klaro -X- _ O
ug -X- _ O
pagkaparehas -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
posisyon -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
kamot -X- _ O
atol -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
misa. -X- _ O
Ang -X- _ O
Circular -X- _ B-OTHER
Letter -X- _ I-OTHER
No. -X- _ I-OTHER
1053-14-2023 -X- _ I-OTHER
, -X- _ O
niepekto -X- _ O
niadtong -X- _ O
Hunyo -X- _ O
16 -X- _ O
, -X- _ O
2023 -X- _ O
. -X- _ O

PULIS -X- _ O
, -X- _ O
GIPADAKOP -X- _ O
ANG -X- _ O
ASAWA -X- _ O
SAMTANG -X- _ O
KAUBAN -X- _ O
ANG -X- _ O
GIINGONG -X- _ O
KABIT -X- _ O
NIINI -X- _ O
SA -X- _ O
BACOLOD -X- _ B-LOC
CITY -X- _ I-LOC
Naabtan -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
mga -X- _ O
awtoridad -X- _ O
ang -X- _ O
asawa -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
usa -X- _ O
ka -X- _ O
pulis -X- _ O
uban -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
giingong -X- _ O
kabit -X- _ O
niini -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
anaa -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
sulod -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
kwarto -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
usa -X- _ O
ka -X- _ O
apartment -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
Barangay -X- _ B-LOC
Singcang-Airport -X- _ I-LOC
sa -X- _ O
Bacolod -X- _ B-LOC
City. -X- _ I-LOC
Sumala -X- _ O
pa -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
report -X- _ O
, -X- _ O
giingong -X- _ O
gisulod -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
mga -X- _ O
awtoridad -X- _ O
ang -X- _ O
maong -X- _ O
apartment -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
dihang -X- _ O
nakompirmar -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
nagreklamong -X- _ O
pulis -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
anaa -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
sulod -X- _ O
ang -X- _ O
iyang -X- _ O
asawa. -X- _ O
Sa -X- _ O
sulod -X- _ O
, -X- _ O
naabtan -X- _ O
ang -X- _ O
asawa -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
pulis -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
nakasuot -X- _ O
og -X- _ O
sinina -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
pangkatulog -X- _ O
samtang -X- _ O
naghubo -X- _ O
ang -X- _ O
lalaki -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
anaa -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
higdaanan. -X- _ O
Matud -X- _ O
pa -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
impormasyon -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
kapulisan -X- _ O
, -X- _ O
giingong -X- _ O
pila -X- _ O
ra -X- _ O
kaadlaw -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
giabangan -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
asawa -X- _ O
ug -X- _ O
maong -X- _ O
lalaki -X- _ O
ang -X- _ O
naasoy -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
apartment. -X- _ O
Gisubli -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
asawa -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
komplikado -X- _ O
ang -X- _ O
relasyon -X- _ O
nila -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
iyang -X- _ O
bana -X- _ O
ug -X- _ O
gipasanginlan -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
aduna -X- _ O
sab -X- _ O
laing -X- _ O
karelasyon -X- _ O
ang -X- _ O
iyang -X- _ O
bana. -X- _ O
Dugang -X- _ O
pa -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
kapulisan -X- _ O
, -X- _ O
pasakaan -X- _ O
gihapon -X- _ O
og -X- _ O
kasong -X- _ O
adultery -X- _ O
ang -X- _ O
duha -X- _ O
bisan -X- _ O
paman -X- _ O
wala -X- _ O
makita -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
akto -X- _ O
ang -X- _ O
pakighilawas -X- _ O
niini -X- _ O
. -X- _ O

LALAKI -X- _ O
, -X- _ O
NAPUSILAN -X- _ O
ANG -X- _ O
KAUGALINGON -X- _ O
SAMTANG -X- _ O
NAGDAMGO -X- _ O
NGA -X- _ O
GIKAWATAN -X- _ O
ANG -X- _ O
BALAY -X- _ O
Aksidenteng -X- _ O
napusilan -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
usa -X- _ O
ka -X- _ O
lalaki -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
Estados -X- _ B-LOC
Unidos -X- _ I-LOC
ang -X- _ O
iyang -X- _ O
kaugalingon -X- _ O
samtang -X- _ O
natulog -X- _ O
niadtong -X- _ O
Abril -X- _ O
10 -X- _ O
, -X- _ O
2023. -X- _ O
Gidamgo -X- _ O
si -X- _ O
Mark -X- _ B-PER
Dicara -X- _ I-PER
, -X- _ O
62 -X- _ O
anyos -X- _ O
, -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
aduna'y -X- _ O
nisulod -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
iyang -X- _ O
balay. -X- _ O
Tungod -X- _ O
niini -X- _ O
, -X- _ O
nikuha -X- _ O
siya -X- _ O
og -X- _ O
pusil -X- _ O
ug -X- _ O
aksidenteng -X- _ O
naunay -X- _ O
niini. -X- _ O
Napusilan -X- _ O
ni -X- _ O
Dicara -X- _ B-PER
ang -X- _ O
iyang -X- _ O
batiis -X- _ O
ug -X- _ O
diha -X- _ O
na -X- _ O
siya -X- _ O
nakamata -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
iyang -X- _ O
damgo. -X- _ O
Dali -X- _ O
sab -X- _ O
siyang -X- _ O
gidala -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
usa -X- _ O
ka -X- _ O
lokal -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
ospital -X- _ O
aron -X- _ O
matambalan. -X- _ O
Human -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
maong -X- _ O
insidente -X- _ O
, -X- _ O
mag-atubang -X- _ O
si -X- _ O
Dicara -X- _ B-PER
og -X- _ O
mga -X- _ O
kaso -X- _ O
bahin -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
ilegal -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
pagkupot -X- _ O
og -X- _ O
pusil -X- _ O
. -X- _ O

BROWNOUT -X- _ O
NA -X- _ O
PUD. -X- _ O
Sa -X- _ O
ikaduhang -X- _ O
higayon -X- _ O
, -X- _ O
walay -X- _ O
kuryente -X- _ O
na -X- _ O
pud -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
tibuok -X- _ O
Dumaguete -X- _ B-LOC
City -X- _ I-LOC
ug -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
mga -X- _ O
kasikbit -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
lungsod -X- _ O
niini -X- _ O
karong -X- _ O
Huwebes -X- _ O
, -X- _ O
June -X- _ O
15 -X- _ O
, -X- _ O
2023. -X- _ O
Matud -X- _ O
pa -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
NORECO -X- _ B-ORG
II -X- _ I-ORG
, -X- _ O
kini -X- _ O
tungod -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
pag-trip -X- _ O
off -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
linya -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
NGCP -X- _ B-ORG
aron -X- _ O
mabalik -X- _ O
ang -X- _ O
suga -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
mga -X- _ O
lungsod -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
Zamboanguita -X- _ B-LOC
ug -X- _ O
Siaton -X- _ B-LOC
. -X- _ O

Walay -X- _ O
kuryente -X- _ O
gihapon -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
pipila -X- _ O
ka -X- _ O
bahin -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
Negros -X- _ B-LOC
Oriental -X- _ I-LOC
taliwala -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
ulan -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
padayong -X- _ O
nasinati -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
probinsya -X- _ O
karong -X- _ O
Huwebes -X- _ O
, -X- _ O
June -X- _ O
15 -X- _ O
, -X- _ O
2023. -X- _ O
Ganinang -X- _ O
kaadlawon -X- _ O
, -X- _ O
pakalit -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
nag-blackout -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
tibuok -X- _ O
Dumaguete -X- _ B-LOC
City -X- _ I-LOC
ug -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
mga -X- _ O
kasikbit -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
lungsod -X- _ O
niini. -X- _ O
Sa -X- _ O
pagkakaron -X- _ O
, -X- _ O
padayong -X- _ O
giayo -X- _ O
ang -X- _ O
linya -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
kuryente -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
Dauin -X- _ B-LOC
ngadto -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
Siaton -X- _ B-LOC
. -X- _ O

Nakadawat -X- _ O
og -X- _ O
standing -X- _ O
ovation -X- _ O
ang -X- _ O
Bisaya -X- _ B-OTHER
singer -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
si -X- _ O
Roland -X- _ B-PER
" -X- _ I-PER
Bunot -X- _ I-PER
" -X- _ I-PER
Abante -X- _ I-PER
human -X- _ O
kini -X- _ O
nitungtong -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
entablado -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
America -X- _ B-ORG
's -X- _ I-ORG
Got -X- _ I-ORG
Talent. -X- _ I-ORG
Nakuha -X- _ O
sab -X- _ O
ni -X- _ O
Bunot -X- _ B-PER
ang -X- _ O
" -X- _ O
yes -X- _ O
" -X- _ O
votes -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
tanang -X- _ O
mga -X- _ O
hurado -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
AGT -X- _ B-ORG
nga -X- _ O
sila -X- _ O
si -X- _ O
Howie -X- _ B-PER
Mandel -X- _ I-PER
, -X- _ I-PER
Simon -X- _ B-PER
Cowell -X- _ I-PER
, -X- _ O
Sofia -X- _ B-PER
Vergara -X- _ I-PER
, -X- _ O
ug -X- _ O
Heidi -X- _ B-PER
Klum. -X- _ I-PER
Kini -X- _ O
human -X- _ O
gikanta -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
lumad -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
taga-Santander -X- _ B-LOC
, -X- _ O
Cebu -X- _ B-LOC
ang -X- _ O
" -X- _ O
When -X- _ B-OTHER
a -X- _ I-OTHER
Man -X- _ I-OTHER
Loves -X- _ I-OTHER
a -X- _ I-OTHER
Woman -X- _ I-OTHER
" -X- _ I-OTHER
ni -X- _ O
Percy -X- _ B-PER
Sledge -X- _ I-PER
Martes -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
gabii -X- _ O
, -X- _ O
June -X- _ O
13 -X- _ O
, -X- _ O
2023. -X- _ O
Sa -X- _ O
pakighinabi -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
mga -X- _ O
hurado -X- _ O
kaniya -X- _ O
, -X- _ O
gibutyag -X- _ O
ni -X- _ O
Bunot -X- _ B-PER
sa -X- _ O
pinulongang -X- _ O
Binisaya -X- _ B-OTHER
nga -X- _ O
siya -X- _ O
usa -X- _ O
ka -X- _ O
mangingisda -X- _ O
ug -X- _ O
driver -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
habal-habal. -X- _ O
Matuman -X- _ O
lang -X- _ O
kuno -X- _ O
niya -X- _ O
ang -X- _ O
iyang -X- _ O
hilig -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
pagkanta -X- _ O
pinaagi -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
mga -X- _ O
videokehan -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
iyang -X- _ O
silingan. -X- _ O
Human -X- _ O
mapa-wow -X- _ O
ang -X- _ O
mga -X- _ O
hurado -X- _ O
ug -X- _ O
audience -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
AGT -X- _ B-ORG
, -X- _ O
gilaomang -X- _ O
mopadayon -X- _ O
si -X- _ O
Bunot -X- _ B-PER
sa -X- _ O
sunod -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
hugna -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
maong -X- _ O
contest -X- _ O
. -X- _ O

Heads -X- _ O
up -X- _ O
, -X- _ O
beshy -X- _ O
! -X- _ O
Walay -X- _ O
kuryente -X- _ O
karong -X- _ O
Dominggo -X- _ O
, -X- _ O
Hunyo -X- _ O
18 -X- _ O
, -X- _ O
2023 -X- _ O
, -X- _ O
gikan -X- _ O
alas-5:30 -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
buntag -X- _ O
hangtud -X- _ O
alas-6 -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
gabii. -X- _ O
Usa -X- _ O
ka -X- _ O
scheduled -X- _ O
power -X- _ O
service -X- _ O
interruption -X- _ O
ang -X- _ O
ipahigayon -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
National -X- _ B-ORG
Grid -X- _ I-ORG
Corporation -X- _ I-ORG
of -X- _ I-ORG
the -X- _ I-ORG
Philippines -X- _ I-ORG
( -X- _ B-ORG
NGCP -X- _ I-ORG
) -X- _ I-ORG
sa -X- _ O
pipila -X- _ O
ka -X- _ O
dapit -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
probinsya. -X- _ O
Matud -X- _ O
pa -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
abiso -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
NORECO -X- _ B-ORG
II -X- _ I-ORG
, -X- _ O
wala'y -X- _ O
suga -X- _ O
gikan -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
Calo -X- _ B-LOC
, -X- _ I-LOC
San -X- _ I-LOC
Jose -X- _ I-LOC
ug -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
tibuok -X- _ O
bahin -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
Amlan -X- _ B-LOC
, -X- _ O
Tanjay -X- _ B-LOC
City -X- _ I-LOC
ug -X- _ O
Pamplona. -X- _ B-LOC
Wala -X- _ O
pu'y -X- _ O
kuryente -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
lugar -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
Dobdob -X- _ B-LOC
ug -X- _ O
Calinawan -X- _ B-LOC
sa -X- _ O
Valencia -X- _ B-LOC
ug -X- _ O
Avocado -X- _ B-LOC
sa -X- _ O
Sta. -X- _ B-LOC
Catalina. -X- _ I-LOC
Nipasalig -X- _ O
sab -X- _ O
ang -X- _ O
NGCP -X- _ B-ORG
nga -X- _ O
dalion -X- _ O
pag-ayo -X- _ O
ang -X- _ O
mga -X- _ O
transmission -X- _ O
lines -X- _ O
alang -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
maong -X- _ O
mga -X- _ O
dapit. -X- _ O
| -X- _ O
via -X- _ O
Reynalyn -X- _ B-PER
Labarda -X- _ I-PER
, -X- _ O
correspondent -X- _ O

Gideklarar -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
Malacañang -X- _ B-ORG
nga -X- _ O
regular -X- _ O
holiday -X- _ O
ang -X- _ O
Miyerkules -X- _ O
, -X- _ O
Hunyo -X- _ O
28 -X- _ O
, -X- _ O
2023 -X- _ O
, -X- _ O
isip -X- _ O
pagsaulog -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
Eid'l -X- _ B-OTHER
Adha -X- _ I-OTHER
kon -X- _ O
Feast -X- _ B-OTHER
of -X- _ I-OTHER
Sacrifice -X- _ I-OTHER
sa -X- _ O
atong -X- _ O
mga -X- _ O
kaigsuonang -X- _ O
Muslim -X- _ B-OTHER
. -X- _ O

Walay -X- _ O
kuryente -X- _ O
karong -X- _ O
Sabado -X- _ O
, -X- _ O
Hunyo -X- _ O
17 -X- _ O
, -X- _ O
2023 -X- _ O
, -X- _ O
gikan -X- _ O
alas-6 -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
buntag -X- _ O
hangtud -X- _ O
alas-6 -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
gabii. -X- _ O
Usa -X- _ O
ka -X- _ O
scheduled -X- _ O
power -X- _ O
service -X- _ O
interruption -X- _ O
ang -X- _ O
himuon -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
National -X- _ B-LOC
Grid -X- _ I-LOC
Corporation -X- _ I-LOC
of -X- _ I-LOC
the -X- _ I-LOC
Philippines -X- _ I-LOC
( -X- _ I-LOC
NGCP -X- _ I-LOC
) -X- _ I-LOC
sa -X- _ O
pipila -X- _ O
ka -X- _ O
bahin -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
Negros -X- _ B-LOC
Oriental. -X- _ I-LOC
Sumala -X- _ O
pa -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
abiso -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
NORECO -X- _ B-ORG
II -X- _ I-ORG
, -X- _ O
wala'y -X- _ O
suga -X- _ O
ang -X- _ O
tibuok -X- _ O
bahin -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
Santa -X- _ B-LOC
Catalina -X- _ I-LOC
, -X- _ O
Bayawan -X- _ B-LOC
City -X- _ I-LOC
ug -X- _ O
Basay. -X- _ B-LOC
Wala -X- _ O
pu'y -X- _ O
kuryente -X- _ O
ang -X- _ O
lugar -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
Calicanan -X- _ B-LOC
ug -X- _ O
Fatima -X- _ B-LOC
sa -X- _ O
Pamplona -X- _ B-LOC
, -X- _ O
ug -X- _ O
Sto. -X- _ B-LOC
Niño -X- _ I-LOC
sa -X- _ O
Tanjay -X- _ B-LOC
City. -X- _ I-LOC
Nipasalig -X- _ O
sab -X- _ O
ang -X- _ O
NGCP -X- _ B-ORG
nga -X- _ O
dalion -X- _ O
niini -X- _ O
pag-ayo -X- _ O
ang -X- _ O
transmission -X- _ O
lines -X- _ O
alang -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
maong -X- _ O
mga -X- _ O
dapit. -X- _ O
| -X- _ O
via -X- _ O
Reynalyn -X- _ B-PER
Labarda -X- _ I-PER
, -X- _ O
correspondent -X- _ O

LA -X- _ B-LOC
LIBERTAD -X- _ I-LOC
, -X- _ O
NAG-APOD-APOD -X- _ O
OG -X- _ O
25KG -X- _ O
NGA -X- _ O
BUGAS -X- _ O
SA -X- _ O
MGA -X- _ O
RESIDENTE -X- _ O
NIINI -X- _ O
NGA -X- _ O
APEKTADO -X- _ O
SA -X- _ O
ASF -X- _ B-OTHER
CRISIS -X- _ O
Nag-apod-apod -X- _ O
ang -X- _ O
LGU -X- _ B-ORG
sa -X- _ O
La -X- _ B-LOC
Libertad -X- _ I-LOC
og -X- _ O
25kg -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
bugas -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
11,000 -X- _ O
ka -X- _ O
mga -X- _ O
panimalay -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
sakop -X- _ O
niini. -X- _ O
Gihimo -X- _ O
kini -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
lakang -X- _ O
aron -X- _ O
mabatukan -X- _ O
ang -X- _ O
dili -X- _ O
maayong -X- _ O
epekto -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
African -X- _ B-OTHER
Swine -X- _ I-OTHER
Fever -X- _ I-OTHER
( -X- _ I-OTHER
ASF -X- _ I-OTHER
) -X- _ I-OTHER
sa -X- _ O
maong -X- _ O
lungsod. -X- _ O
Gisugdan -X- _ O
niadtong -X- _ O
Hunyo -X- _ O
7 -X- _ O
ang -X- _ O
pagpanghatag -X- _ O
og -X- _ O
ayudang -X- _ O
bugas -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
unom -X- _ O
ka -X- _ O
mga -X- _ O
coastal -X- _ O
barangay -X- _ O
ug -X- _ O
mosunod -X- _ O
ang -X- _ O
nahibiling -X- _ O
23 -X- _ O
ka -X- _ O
mga -X- _ O
upper -X- _ O
barangay -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
La -X- _ B-LOC
Libertad. -X- _ I-LOC
Ang -X- _ O
Executive -X- _ B-OTHER
Order -X- _ I-OTHER
No. -X- _ I-OTHER
23 -X- _ I-OTHER
nga -X- _ O
nagdili -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
mga -X- _ O
buhing -X- _ O
baboy -X- _ O
ug -X- _ O
mga -X- _ O
produkto -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
may -X- _ O
kalabotan -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
baboy -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
probinsya -X- _ O
, -X- _ O
nakapasamot -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
kalisdanan -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
panginabuhi. -X- _ O
Ang -X- _ O
ASF -X- _ B-OTHER
aduna'y -X- _ O
dakong -X- _ O
epekto -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
La -X- _ B-LOC
Libertad -X- _ I-LOC
, -X- _ O
ilabina -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
mga -X- _ O
residente -X- _ O
kinsang -X- _ O
panginabuhi -X- _ O
nagsalig -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
industriya -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
baboy -X- _ O
. -X- _ O

PARI -X- _ O
, -X- _ O
PATAY -X- _ O
HUMAN -X- _ O
NIBANGGA -X- _ O
ANG -X- _ O
GIMANEHONG -X- _ O
MOTORSIKLO -X- _ O
SA -X- _ O
DUMP -X- _ O
TRUCK -X- _ O
Patay -X- _ O
ang -X- _ O
usa -X- _ O
ka -X- _ O
pari -X- _ O
human -X- _ O
aksidenteng -X- _ O
nibangga -X- _ O
ang -X- _ O
gimanehong -X- _ O
motorsiklo -X- _ O
niini -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
usa -X- _ O
ka -X- _ O
dump -X- _ O
truck -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
National -X- _ B-LOC
Highway -X- _ I-LOC
sa -X- _ O
Barangay -X- _ B-LOC
Malusay -X- _ I-LOC
sa -X- _ O
Guihulngan -X- _ B-LOC
City -X- _ I-LOC
mga -X- _ O
alas-4:28 -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
kadlawon -X- _ O
niadtong -X- _ O
Hunyo -X- _ O
13 -X- _ O
, -X- _ O
2023. -X- _ O
Giila -X- _ O
ang -X- _ O
pari -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
si -X- _ O
Rev. -X- _ O
Father -X- _ O
Rexijan -X- _ B-PER
Gargoles -X- _ I-PER
Jamito -X- _ I-PER
, -X- _ O
29 -X- _ O
anyos -X- _ O
, -X- _ O
ug -X- _ O
lumolupyo -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
Barangay -X- _ B-LOC
Dawis -X- _ I-LOC
, -X- _ I-LOC
Bayawan -X- _ I-LOC
City. -X- _ I-LOC
Usa -X- _ O
ka -X- _ O
pari -X- _ O
si -X- _ O
Jamito -X- _ B-PER
sa -X- _ O
Iglesia -X- _ B-ORG
Filipina -X- _ I-ORG
Independente -X- _ I-ORG
( -X- _ I-ORG
IFI -X- _ I-ORG
) -X- _ I-ORG
nga -X- _ O
nakadestino -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
Barangay -X- _ B-LOC
Hilaitan -X- _ I-LOC
sa -X- _ O
Guihulngan -X- _ B-LOC
City. -X- _ I-LOC
Matud -X- _ O
pa -X- _ O
report -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
kapulisan -X- _ O
, -X- _ O
nagbiye -X- _ O
ang -X- _ O
pari -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
dihang -X- _ O
aksidenteng -X- _ O
nibangga -X- _ O
ang -X- _ O
motorsiklo -X- _ O
niini -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
nakaparadang -X- _ O
dump -X- _ O
truck. -X- _ O
Gidali -X- _ O
pagdala -X- _ O
ang -X- _ O
pari -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
usa -X- _ O
ka -X- _ O
ospital -X- _ O
apan -X- _ O
gideklarar -X- _ O
kinin -X- _ O
dead -X- _ O
on -X- _ O
arrival -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
nag-atiman -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
doktor -X- _ O
. -X- _ O

BABAYENG -X- _ O
GIDEKLARAR -X- _ O
NA -X- _ O
NGA -X- _ O
PATAY -X- _ O
OG -X- _ O
2 -X- _ O
KA -X- _ O
ADLAW -X- _ O
, -X- _ O
NAPALGANG -X- _ O
BUHI -X- _ O
PA -X- _ O
DIAY -X- _ O
SULOD -X- _ O
SA -X- _ O
LUNGON -X- _ O
Usa -X- _ O
ka -X- _ O
tigulang -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
Ecuador -X- _ B-LOC
ang -X- _ O
nakamata -X- _ O
sulod -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
usa -X- _ O
ka -X- _ O
lungon -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
iyang -X- _ O
kaugalingong -X- _ O
haya. -X- _ O
Sa -X- _ O
usa -X- _ O
ka -X- _ O
video -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
gi-post -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
Twitter -X- _ B-OTHER
, -X- _ O
nakita -X- _ O
si -X- _ O
Bella -X- _ B-PER
Montoya -X- _ I-PER
, -X- _ O
76 -X- _ O
anyos -X- _ O
, -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
naglugos -X- _ O
og -X- _ O
ginhawa -X- _ O
sulod -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
iyang -X- _ O
lungon -X- _ O
samtang -X- _ O
gitabang -X- _ O
kini -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
duha -X- _ O
ka -X- _ O
lalaki. -X- _ O
Sumala -X- _ O
pa -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
iyang -X- _ O
anak -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
si -X- _ O
Gilbert -X- _ B-PER
Balberán -X- _ I-PER
, -X- _ O
duha -X- _ O
ka -X- _ O
adlaw -X- _ O
nang -X- _ O
gideklarar -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
patay -X- _ O
ang -X- _ O
iyang -X- _ O
inahan. -X- _ O
Dugang -X- _ O
pa -X- _ O
niya -X- _ O
, -X- _ O
nahibaloan -X- _ O
nilang -X- _ O
buhi -X- _ O
pa -X- _ O
ang -X- _ O
iyang -X- _ O
inahan -X- _ O
tungod -X- _ O
ginahapak -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
walang -X- _ O
kamot -X- _ O
niini -X- _ O
ang -X- _ O
iyang -X- _ O
lungon -X- _ O
human -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
lima -X- _ O
ka -X- _ O
oras -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
haya -X- _ O
niini -X- _ O
. -X- _ O

NANGITA -X- _ O
OG -X- _ O
TRABAHO -X- _ O
? -X- _ O
JOB -X- _ O
FAIR -X- _ O
, -X- _ O
IPAHIGAYON -X- _ O
SA -X- _ O
DUMAGUETE -X- _ B-LOC
CITY -X- _ I-LOC
KARONG -X- _ O
INDEPENDENCE -X- _ B-OTHER
DAY -X- _ I-OTHER
Aduna'y -X- _ O
ipahigayong -X- _ O
job -X- _ O
fair -X- _ O
karong -X- _ O
Lunes -X- _ O
, -X- _ O
Hunyo -X- _ O
12 -X- _ O
, -X- _ O
2023 -X- _ O
, -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
Main -X- _ B-LOC
Atrium -X- _ I-LOC
, -X- _ I-LOC
Robinsons -X- _ I-LOC
Place -X- _ I-LOC
sa -X- _ O
dakbayan -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
Dumaguete. -X- _ O
Ipahigayon -X- _ O
ang -X- _ O
Kalayaan -X- _ B-OTHER
Job -X- _ I-OTHER
Fair -X- _ I-OTHER
aron -X- _ O
pagsaulog -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
ika-125 -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
anibersaryo -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
Philippine -X- _ B-OTHER
Independence -X- _ I-OTHER
and -X- _ I-OTHER
Nationhood -X- _ I-OTHER
uban -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
tema -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
" -X- _ O
Kalayaan. -X- _ O
Kinabukasan. -X- _ O
Kasaysayan -X- _ O
. -X- _ O
" -X- _ O

MAYON -X- _ B-LOC
VOLCANO -X- _ I-LOC
, -X- _ O
GIISA -X- _ O
NA -X- _ O
SA -X- _ O
ALERT -X- _ O
LEVEL -X- _ O
3 -X- _ O
Giisa -X- _ O
na -X- _ O
karon -X- _ O
ngadto -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
Alert -X- _ O
Level -X- _ O
3 -X- _ O
ang -X- _ O
Mayon -X- _ B-LOC
Volcano -X- _ I-LOC
, -X- _ O
sumala -X- _ O
pa -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
alert -X- _ O
level -X- _ O
bulletin -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
gipagawas -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
DOST-PHIVOLCS. -X- _ B-ORG
Nagpasabot -X- _ O
kini -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
nagpakita -X- _ O
ang -X- _ O
Mayon -X- _ B-LOC
Volcano -X- _ I-LOC
og -X- _ O
dili -X- _ O
maayong -X- _ O
kalihokan -X- _ O
ug -X- _ O
gipasidan-an -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
adunay -X- _ O
" -X- _ O
increased -X- _ O
tendency -X- _ O
towards -X- _ O
a -X- _ O
hazardous -X- _ O
eruption. -X- _ O
" -X- _ O
Girekomendar -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
Phivolcs -X- _ B-ORG
ang -X- _ O
pagbakwit -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
mga -X- _ O
tawo -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
nagpuyo -X- _ O
sulod -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
6-km -X- _ O
radius -X- _ O
Permanent -X- _ O
Danger -X- _ O
Zone -X- _ O
( -X- _ O
PDZ -X- _ O
) -X- _ O
palibot -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
maong -X- _ O
bulkan. -X- _ O
Nihibaloan -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
niadtong -X- _ O
Lunes -X- _ O
, -X- _ O
Hunyo -X- _ O
5 -X- _ O
, -X- _ O
2023 -X- _ O
, -X- _ O
giisa -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
PHIVOLCS -X- _ B-ORG
ang -X- _ O
alert -X- _ O
level -X- _ O
status -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
Mayon -X- _ O
gikan -X- _ O
Alert -X- _ O
Level -X- _ O
1 -X- _ O
ngadto -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
Alert -X- _ O
Level -X- _ O
2. -X- _ O
Napahimangno -X- _ O
sab -X- _ O
ang -X- _ O
CAAP -X- _ B-ORG
sa -X- _ O
mga -X- _ O
flight -X- _ O
operators -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
likayan -X- _ O
ang -X- _ O
pagpalupad -X- _ O
duol -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
bulkan -X- _ O
tungod -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
posibilidad -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
kalit -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
pag-ulbo -X- _ O
o -X- _ O
phreatic -X- _ O
eruptions -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
maong -X- _ O
bulkan -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
maghatag -X- _ O
og -X- _ O
peligro -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
mga -X- _ O
eroplano -X- _ O
na -X- _ O
molupad -X- _ O
. -X- _ O

Makita -X- _ O
na -X- _ O
karon -X- _ O
ang -X- _ O
mata -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
Severe -X- _ O
Tropical -X- _ O
Storm -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
# -X- _ O
ChedengPH -X- _ B-OTHER
( -X- _ O
# -X- _ O
GUCHOL -X- _ B-OTHER
) -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
usa -X- _ O
ka -X- _ O
timailhan -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
mokusog -X- _ O
kini -X- _ O
isip -X- _ O
usa -X- _ O
ka -X- _ O
TYPHOON -X- _ O
Category -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
mga -X- _ O
mosunod -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
oras. -X- _ O
Sa -X- _ O
pagkakaron -X- _ O
, -X- _ O
nagpabiling -X- _ O
maba -X- _ O
ang -X- _ O
tsansa -X- _ O
niini -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
moigo -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
nasud -X- _ O
apan -X- _ O
gilaomang -X- _ O
pakusgon -X- _ O
niini -X- _ O
ang -X- _ O
Southwest -X- _ O
Monsoon -X- _ O
o -X- _ O
Habagat -X- _ O
sugod -X- _ O
ugmang -X- _ O
adlawa -X- _ O
. -X- _ O

MAGTIAYON -X- _ O
SA -X- _ O
MALAYSIA -X- _ B-LOC
NAGBULAG -X- _ O
TUNGOD -X- _ O
SA -X- _ O
TALAGSA-ONG -X- _ O
SAKIT -X- _ O
SA -X- _ O
DUGO -X- _ O
Usa -X- _ O
ka -X- _ O
magtiayon -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
Malaysia -X- _ B-LOC
ang -X- _ O
nagbulag -X- _ O
human -X- _ O
nahibal-an -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
sila -X- _ O
parehong -X- _ O
adunay -X- _ O
thalassemia -X- _ O
, -X- _ O
usa -X- _ O
ka -X- _ O
sakit -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
dugo -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
gipasa -X- _ O
gikan -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
ginikanan -X- _ O
ngadto -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
anak. -X- _ O
Ang -X- _ O
maong -X- _ O
sakit -X- _ O
mahimong -X- _ O
moresulta -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
anemia -X- _ O
ug -X- _ O
nagkinahanglan -X- _ O
kini -X- _ O
og -X- _ O
regular -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
pag-abono -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
dugo -X- _ O
kon -X- _ O
blood -X- _ O
transfusions -X- _ O
ug -X- _ O
ang -X- _ O
bugtong -X- _ O
posible -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
tambal -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
pagkakaron -X- _ O
mao -X- _ O
ang -X- _ O
bone-marrow -X- _ O
transplant. -X- _ O
Ang -X- _ O
magtiayon -X- _ O
parehong -X- _ O
doktor -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
si -X- _ O
Farra -X- _ B-PER
Diana -X- _ I-PER
ug -X- _ O
Ashraff. -X- _ B-PER
Sa -X- _ O
wala -X- _ O
pa -X- _ O
sila -X- _ O
gikasal -X- _ O
, -X- _ O
niining -X- _ O
bagohay -X- _ O
lang -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
mga -X- _ O
bulan -X- _ O
nila -X- _ O
nahibal-an -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
pareha -X- _ O
silang -X- _ O
duha -X- _ O
na -X- _ O
thalassemia -X- _ O
carrier -X- _ O
Sakit -X- _ O
man -X- _ O
para -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
duha -X- _ O
apan -X- _ O
nagdesisyon -X- _ O
sila -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
magbulag -X- _ O
aron -X- _ O
malikayan -X- _ O
ang -X- _ O
mamahimong -X- _ O
peligro -X- _ O
og -X- _ O
mapasa -X- _ O
ang -X- _ O
maong -X- _ O
sakit -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
umaabot -X- _ O
nilang -X- _ O
bata -X- _ O
. -X- _ O

PIPILA -X- _ O
KA -X- _ O
MGA -X- _ O
WALA -X- _ O
NAKABAYAD -X- _ O
OG -X- _ O
UTANG -X- _ O
SA -X- _ O
ONLINE -X- _ O
LENDING -X- _ O
APP -X- _ O
, -X- _ O
GIPADALHAN -X- _ O
OG -X- _ O
BULAK -X- _ O
SA -X- _ O
PATAY -X- _ O
UG -X- _ O
LUNGON -X- _ O
Pipila -X- _ O
ka -X- _ O
indibidwal -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
na-delay -X- _ O
ang -X- _ O
pagbayad -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
online -X- _ O
lending -X- _ O
app -X- _ O
ang -X- _ O
giingong -X- _ O
gipadalhan -X- _ O
og -X- _ O
bulak -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
patay -X- _ O
ug -X- _ O
lungon -X- _ O
aron -X- _ O
hadlukon. -X- _ O
Sumala -X- _ O
pa -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
report -X- _ O
, -X- _ O
giingong -X- _ O
nakahilak -X- _ O
na -X- _ O
lamang -X- _ O
ang -X- _ O
usa -X- _ O
ka -X- _ O
biktima -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
dihang -X- _ O
nakita -X- _ O
niya -X- _ O
ang -X- _ O
bulak -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
patay -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
gipadala -X- _ O
ngadto -X- _ O
niya. -X- _ O
Dugang -X- _ O
pa -X- _ O
, -X- _ O
giingong -X- _ O
tulo -X- _ O
lamang -X- _ O
kaadlaw -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
na-delay -X- _ O
ang -X- _ O
pagbayad -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
utang -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
usa -X- _ O
ka -X- _ O
biktima. -X- _ O
Usa -X- _ O
sab -X- _ O
ka -X- _ O
indibidwal -X- _ O
ang -X- _ O
gipadalhan -X- _ O
og -X- _ O
lungon -X- _ O
tungod -X- _ O
sab -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
pagkalangan -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
pagbayad -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
utang. -X- _ O
Giawhag -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
PNP -X- _ B-ORG
Anti-Cybercrime -X- _ I-ORG
Group -X- _ I-ORG
ang -X- _ O
mga -X- _ O
biktima -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
maong -X- _ O
panghitabo -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
moduol -X- _ O
nila -X- _ O
aron -X- _ O
makapasaka -X- _ O
og -X- _ O
kaso -X- _ O
. -X- _ O

CANADA -X- _ B-LOC
, -X- _ O
NAGTANYAG -X- _ O
OG -X- _ O
VISA-FREE -X- _ O
TRAVEL -X- _ O
SA -X- _ O
MGA -X- _ O
KWALIPIKADONG -X- _ O
PILIPINO -X- _ B-OTHER
Mahimo -X- _ O
ng -X- _ O
mokuha -X- _ O
og -X- _ O
visa-free -X- _ O
air -X- _ O
travel -X- _ O
ang -X- _ O
mga -X- _ O
kwalipikadong -X- _ O
Pilipino -X- _ B-OTHER
, -X- _ O
sumala -X- _ O
pa -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
embahado -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
Canada -X- _ B-LOC
niadtong -X- _ O
Miyerkules. -X- _ O
Kini -X- _ O
human -X- _ O
gidungag -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
nasud -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
North -X- _ B-LOC
America -X- _ I-LOC
ang -X- _ O
Pilipinas -X- _ B-LOC
sa -X- _ O
Electronic -X- _ B-ORG
Travel -X- _ I-ORG
Authorization -X- _ I-ORG
( -X- _ I-ORG
eTA -X- _ I-ORG
) -X- _ I-ORG
program -X- _ O
niini. -X- _ O
Magtugot -X- _ O
kini -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
mga -X- _ O
Pilipino -X- _ B-OTHER
nga -X- _ O
aduna'y -X- _ O
Canadian -X- _ B-OTHER
visa -X- _ O
sulod -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
pulo -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
tuig -X- _ O
ug -X- _ O
kadtong -X- _ O
naa'y -X- _ O
mga -X- _ O
non-immigrant -X- _ O
visas -X- _ O
gikan -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
United -X- _ B-LOC
States -X- _ I-LOC
nga -X- _ O
mo-apply -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
eTA -X- _ O
kung -X- _ O
mobiyahe -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
Canada. -X- _ B-LOC
Aron -X- _ O
mahibal-an -X- _ O
kung -X- _ O
kwalipikado -X- _ O
ang -X- _ O
usa -X- _ O
ka -X- _ O
indibidwal -X- _ O
ug -X- _ O
unsaon -X- _ O
pag-apply -X- _ O
, -X- _ O
mahimong -X- _ O
bisitahon -X- _ O
ang -X- _ O
Canadian -X- _ B-OTHER
government -X- _ O
's -X- _ O
eTA -X- _ O
website -X- _ O
. -X- _ O

PHILIPPINE -X- _ B-ORG
AIRLINES -X- _ I-ORG
, -X- _ O
NAGTANYAG -X- _ O
OG -X- _ O
P125 -X- _ O
NGA -X- _ O
PLITE -X- _ O
HANGTOD -X- _ O
JUNE -X- _ O
25 -X- _ O
Nagtanyag -X- _ O
ang -X- _ O
Philippine -X- _ B-ORG
Airlines -X- _ I-ORG
og -X- _ O
P125 -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
one-way -X- _ O
base -X- _ O
fare -X- _ O
sugod -X- _ O
June -X- _ O
5 -X- _ O
hangtod -X- _ O
June -X- _ O
25 -X- _ O
, -X- _ O
2023. -X- _ O
Aduna -X- _ O
kini -X- _ O
domestic -X- _ O
travel -X- _ O
period -X- _ O
gikan -X- _ O
Feb. -X- _ O
1 -X- _ O
, -X- _ O
2024. -X- _ O
Alang -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
mga -X- _ O
international -X- _ O
travelers -X- _ O
, -X- _ O
lakip -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
travel -X- _ O
period -X- _ O
ang -X- _ O
South -X- _ B-LOC
Korea -X- _ I-LOC
ug -X- _ O
Guam -X- _ B-LOC
gikan -X- _ O
July -X- _ O
; -X- _ O
Hong -X- _ B-LOC
Kong -X- _ I-LOC
, -X- _ O
Macau -X- _ B-LOC
, -X- _ O
China -X- _ B-LOC
, -X- _ O
Taiwan -X- _ B-LOC
, -X- _ O
ug -X- _ O
Southeast -X- _ B-LOC
Asia -X- _ I-LOC
gikan -X- _ O
Sept. -X- _ O
1 -X- _ O
; -X- _ O
Japan -X- _ B-LOC
gikan -X- _ O
Jan. -X- _ O
15 -X- _ O
; -X- _ O
North -X- _ B-LOC
America -X- _ I-LOC
, -X- _ O
Middle -X- _ B-LOC
East -X- _ I-LOC
, -X- _ O
ug -X- _ O
Australia -X- _ B-LOC
gikan -X- _ O
Feb. -X- _ O
1. -X- _ O
Aron -X- _ O
pag-avail -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
maong -X- _ O
promo -X- _ O
, -X- _ O
mahimong -X- _ O
bisitahon -X- _ O
ang -X- _ O
section -X- _ O
on -X- _ O
flight -X- _ O
ticket -X- _ O
deals -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
maong -X- _ O
airline -X- _ O
ug -X- _ O
i-click -X- _ O
ang -X- _ O
" -X- _ O
book -X- _ O
now -X- _ O
" -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
ilalom -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
napiling -X- _ O
destinasyon -X- _ O
. -X- _ O

CAAP -X- _ B-ORG
, -X- _ O
GIDID-AN -X- _ O
ANG -X- _ O
MGA -X- _ O
EROPLANO -X- _ O
PAGLUPAD -X- _ O
DUOL -X- _ O
SA -X- _ O
KANLAON -X- _ B-LOC
VOLCANO -X- _ I-LOC
TUNGOD -X- _ O
SA -X- _ O
ABNORMAL -X- _ O
NGA -X- _ O
KAHIMTANG -X- _ O
NIINI -X- _ O
Gidili -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
Civil -X- _ B-ORG
Aviation -X- _ I-ORG
Authority -X- _ I-ORG
of -X- _ I-ORG
the -X- _ I-ORG
Philippines -X- _ I-ORG
( -X- _ B-ORG
CAAP -X- _ I-ORG
) -X- _ I-ORG
ang -X- _ O
mga -X- _ O
eroplano -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
paglupad -X- _ O
duol -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
Taal -X- _ B-LOC
, -X- _ I-LOC
Mayon -X- _ I-LOC
, -X- _ O
ug -X- _ O
Kanlaon -X- _ B-LOC
volcanoes. -X- _ O
Ang -X- _ O
Kanlaon -X- _ B-LOC
Volcano -X- _ I-LOC
anaa -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
alert -X- _ O
level -X- _ O
1 -X- _ O
( -X- _ O
Abnormal -X- _ O
Condition -X- _ O
) -X- _ O
kon -X- _ O
nagpakita -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
abnormal -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
kahimtang. -X- _ O
Gitambagan -X- _ O
ang -X- _ O
mga -X- _ O
flight -X- _ O
operators -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
likayan -X- _ O
ang -X- _ O
pagpalupad -X- _ O
duol -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
bulkan -X- _ O
tungod -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
posibilidad -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
kalit -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
pag-ulbo -X- _ O
o -X- _ O
phreatic -X- _ O
eruptions -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
maong -X- _ O
bulkan -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
maghatag -X- _ O
og -X- _ O
peligro -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
mga -X- _ O
eroplano -X- _ O
na -X- _ O
molupad. -X- _ O
Dugang -X- _ O
pa -X- _ O
, -X- _ O
gidili -X- _ O
sab -X- _ O
ang -X- _ O
pagsulod -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
4km -X- _ O
radius -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
permanent -X- _ O
danger -X- _ O
zone -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
Kanlaon -X- _ B-LOC
Volcano -X- _ I-LOC
. -X- _ O

Nahimo -X- _ O
nang -X- _ O
usa -X- _ O
ka -X- _ O
tropical -X- _ O
depression -X- _ O
ang -X- _ O
low -X- _ O
pressure -X- _ O
area -X- _ O
( -X- _ O
LPA -X- _ O
) -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
gibantayan -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
silangang -X- _ O
bahin -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
# -X- _ O
Visayas -X- _ B-LOC
, -X- _ O
sumala -X- _ O
pa -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
PAGASA -X- _ B-ORG
. -X- _ O

PLDT -X- _ B-ORG
NITAHO -X- _ O
NGA -X- _ O
DUNAY -X- _ O
PROBLEMA -X- _ O
SA -X- _ O
INTERNET -X- _ O
NIINI -X- _ O
Gikumpirmar -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
PLDT -X- _ B-ORG
nga -X- _ O
nakasinati -X- _ O
ang -X- _ O
mga -X- _ O
subscriber -X- _ O
niini -X- _ O
og -X- _ O
hinay -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
internet -X- _ O
connection -X- _ O
tungod -X- _ O
kay -X- _ O
nawad-an -X- _ O
og -X- _ O
bandwidth -X- _ O
capacity -X- _ O
and -X- _ O
mga -X- _ O
submarine -X- _ O
cable -X- _ O
partners -X- _ O
niini. -X- _ O
" -X- _ O
We -X- _ O
are -X- _ O
now -X- _ O
working -X- _ O
with -X- _ O
our -X- _ O
partners -X- _ O
to -X- _ O
provide -X- _ O
alternate -X- _ O
capacity -X- _ O
that -X- _ O
would -X- _ O
restore -X- _ O
the -X- _ O
browsing -X- _ O
experience -X- _ O
in -X- _ O
the -X- _ O
next -X- _ O
few -X- _ O
hours -X- _ O
, -X- _ O
" -X- _ O
matod -X- _ O
pa -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
PLDT. -X- _ B-ORG
Beshie -X- _ O
, -X- _ O
nagkaproblema -X- _ O
ba -X- _ O
pud -X- _ O
ka -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
imong -X- _ O
internet -X- _ O
? -X- _ O

Nisulod -X- _ O
na -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
Philippine -X- _ B-LOC
Area -X- _ I-LOC
of -X- _ I-LOC
Responsibility -X- _ I-LOC
( -X- _ I-LOC
PAR -X- _ I-LOC
) -X- _ I-LOC
ang -X- _ O
gibantayang -X- _ O
aktibo -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
LPA -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
silangang -X- _ O
bahin -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
# -X- _ O
Visayas. -X- _ B-LOC
Aduna -X- _ O
kini -X- _ O
taas -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
posibilidad -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
mahimong -X- _ O
bagyo -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
mga -X- _ O
mosunod -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
oras. -X- _ O
Kung -X- _ O
mahimo -X- _ O
na -X- _ O
kining -X- _ O
bagyo -X- _ O
samtang -X- _ O
anaa -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
sulod -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
PAR -X- _ B-LOC
, -X- _ O
tawgon -X- _ O
kining -X- _ O
# -X- _ O
Chedeng -X- _ B-OTHER
sa -X- _ O
PAGASA -X- _ B-ORG
. -X- _ O

INDONESIAN -X- _ B-OTHER
BILLIONAIRE -X- _ O
MINGDONAR -X- _ O
OG -X- _ O
P41-M -X- _ O
SA -X- _ O
PILIPINAS -X- _ B-LOC
Nagdonar -X- _ O
ang -X- _ O
usa -X- _ O
ka -X- _ O
Indonesian -X- _ O
businessman -X- _ O
og -X- _ O
kapin -X- _ O
P41 -X- _ O
milyones -X- _ O
ngadto -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
gobyerno -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
Pilipinas -X- _ B-LOC
aron -X- _ O
suportahan -X- _ O
ang -X- _ O
mga -X- _ O
social -X- _ O
programs -X- _ O
ni -X- _ O
President -X- _ O
Ferdinand -X- _ B-PER
Marcos -X- _ I-PER
Jr. -X- _ I-PER
Mao -X- _ O
kini -X- _ O
ang -X- _ O
gibutyag -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
Malacañang -X- _ B-ORG
niadtong -X- _ O
Huwebes -X- _ O
, -X- _ O
Hunyo -X- _ O
1 -X- _ O
, -X- _ O
2023. -X- _ O
Si -X- _ O
Tahir -X- _ B-PER
ang -X- _ O
nagtukod -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
Mayapada -X- _ B-ORG
Group -X- _ I-ORG
diin -X- _ O
aduna -X- _ O
sab -X- _ O
siya'y -X- _ O
negosyo -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
financial -X- _ O
, -X- _ O
healthcare -X- _ O
, -X- _ O
hotels -X- _ O
, -X- _ O
media -X- _ O
, -X- _ O
ug -X- _ O
mining -X- _ O
sectors. -X- _ O
Interesado -X- _ O
sab -X- _ O
si -X- _ O
Tahir -X- _ B-PER
nga -X- _ O
mo-invest -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
Pilipinas -X- _ B-LOC
sama -X- _ O
nalang -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
pagtukod -X- _ O
og -X- _ O
mga -X- _ O
hospitals. -X- _ O
Nahibaloan -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
si -X- _ O
Tahir -X- _ B-PER
nakaila -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
mga -X- _ O
Marcoses -X- _ B-PER
human -X- _ O
sila -X- _ O
nahimamat -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
dihang -X- _ O
naka-exile -X- _ O
kini -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
Hawaii -X- _ B-LOC
. -X- _ O

PAGASA -X- _ B-ORG
, -X- _ O
GIBANTAYAN -X- _ O
ANG -X- _ O
2 -X- _ O
KA -X- _ O
LPA -X- _ O
NGA -X- _ O
ANAA -X- _ O
SA -X- _ O
GAWAS -X- _ O
SA -X- _ O
PAR -X- _ B-LOC
Gibantayan -X- _ O
karon -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
PAGASA -X- _ B-ORG
ang -X- _ O
duha -X- _ O
ka -X- _ O
low -X- _ O
pressure -X- _ O
area -X- _ O
( -X- _ O
LPA -X- _ O
) -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
anaa -X- _ O
pa -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
gawas -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
Philippine -X- _ B-LOC
Area -X- _ I-LOC
of -X- _ I-LOC
Responsibility -X- _ I-LOC
( -X- _ I-LOC
PAR -X- _ I-LOC
) -X- _ I-LOC
. -X- _ O
Ang -X- _ O
duha -X- _ O
ka -X- _ O
LPA -X- _ O
mahimong -X- _ O
makapausbaw -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
southeast -X- _ O
monsoon -X- _ O
o -X- _ O
habagat -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
nasud. -X- _ O
Sumala -X- _ O
pa -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
PAGASA -X- _ B-ORG
, -X- _ O
nahimutang -X- _ O
ang -X- _ O
unang -X- _ O
LPA -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
silangang -X- _ O
bahin -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
Visayas. -X- _ B-LOC
Posible -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
mahimo -X- _ O
kining -X- _ O
usa -X- _ O
ka -X- _ O
tropical -X- _ O
cyclone -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
tunga-tunga -X- _ O
ning -X- _ O
semana -X- _ O
apan -X- _ O
gilaomang -X- _ O
dili -X- _ O
kini -X- _ O
mag-landfall. -X- _ O
Samtang -X- _ O
ang -X- _ O
ikaduhang -X- _ O
LPA -X- _ O
anaa -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
West -X- _ B-LOC
Philippine -X- _ I-LOC
Sea -X- _ I-LOC
ug -X- _ O
mopaingon -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
Southern -X- _ B-LOC
China -X- _ I-LOC
sa -X- _ O
tunga-tunga -X- _ O
ning -X- _ O
semana. -X- _ O
Dugang -X- _ O
pa -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
state -X- _ O
weather -X- _ O
bureau -X- _ O
, -X- _ O
mahimo -X- _ O
sab -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
maporma -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
West -X- _ B-LOC
Philippine -X- _ I-LOC
Sea -X- _ I-LOC
ang -X- _ O
ikatulong -X- _ O
LPA -X- _ O
gikan -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
mga -X- _ O
salin -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
ikaduhang -X- _ O
LPA -X- _ O
. -X- _ O

Mga -X- _ O
eksena -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
pag-abot -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
patayng -X- _ O
lawas -X- _ O
ni -X- _ O
kanhi -X- _ O
Gob. -X- _ O
Guido -X- _ B-PER
Reyes -X- _ I-PER
sa -X- _ O
Negros -X- _ B-LOC
Oriental -X- _ I-LOC
karong -X- _ O
adlawa -X- _ O
, -X- _ O
Hunyo -X- _ O
3 -X- _ O
, -X- _ O
2023 -X- _ O
, -X- _ O
human -X- _ O
siya -X- _ O
nitaliwan -X- _ O
niadtong -X- _ O
Miyerkules -X- _ O
, -X- _ O
Mayo -X- _ O
31. -X- _ O
Gihaya -X- _ O
si -X- _ O
Reyes -X- _ B-PER
sa -X- _ O
Kapitolyo -X- _ B-LOC
Sabado -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
buntag -X- _ O
una -X- _ O
kini -X- _ O
gidala -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
iyang -X- _ O
lungsod -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
natawhan -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
Guihulngan -X- _ B-LOC
City -X- _ I-LOC
. -X- _ O

Anaa -X- _ O
na -X- _ O
karon -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
half-mast -X- _ O
ang -X- _ O
bandila -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
Pilipinas -X- _ B-LOC
sa -X- _ O
Freedom -X- _ B-LOC
Park -X- _ I-LOC
atbang -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
Negros -X- _ B-LOC
Oriental -X- _ I-LOC
Provincial -X- _ I-LOC
Capitol -X- _ I-LOC
isip -X- _ O
pahasubo -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
pagpanaw -X- _ O
ni -X- _ O
Governor -X- _ O
Guido -X- _ B-PER
Reyes -X- _ I-PER
karong -X- _ O
adlawa -X- _ O
, -X- _ O
Mayo -X- _ O
31 -X- _ O
, -X- _ O
2023 -X- _ O
. -X- _ O

Duna -X- _ O
nay -X- _ O
bag-ong -X- _ O
gobernador -X- _ O
ang -X- _ O
Negros -X- _ B-LOC
Oriental. -X- _ I-LOC
Kini -X- _ O
human -X- _ O
nanumpa -X- _ O
si -X- _ O
Vice -X- _ O
Governor -X- _ O
Manuel -X- _ B-PER
" -X- _ I-PER
Chaco -X- _ I-PER
" -X- _ I-PER
Sagarbarria -X- _ I-PER
isip -X- _ O
bag-ong -X- _ O
lider -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
probinsya -X- _ O
human -X- _ O
nipanaw -X- _ O
karong -X- _ O
adlawa -X- _ O
si -X- _ O
Governor -X- _ O
Guido -X- _ B-PER
Reyes. -X- _ I-PER
Si -X- _ O
Sagarbarria -X- _ B-PER
gikan -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
banay -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
mga -X- _ O
politiko. -X- _ O
Ang -X- _ O
iyang -X- _ O
amahan -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
si -X- _ O
Chiquiting -X- _ B-PER
maoy -X- _ O
representante -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
ikaduhang -X- _ O
distrito -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
Negros -X- _ B-LOC
Oriental -X- _ I-LOC
, -X- _ O
samtang -X- _ O
ang -X- _ O
iyang -X- _ O
inahan -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
si -X- _ O
Maisa -X- _ B-PER
maoy -X- _ O
bise -X- _ O
mayor -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
dakbayan -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
Dumaguete -X- _ B-LOC
. -X- _ O

Nipanaw -X- _ O
na -X- _ O
si -X- _ O
Governor -X- _ O
Jorge -X- _ B-PER
Carlo -X- _ I-PER
Joan -X- _ I-PER
" -X- _ I-PER
Guido -X- _ I-PER
" -X- _ I-PER
Reyes -X- _ I-PER
karong -X- _ O
adlawa -X- _ O
, -X- _ O
Mayo -X- _ O
31 -X- _ O
, -X- _ O
2023. -X- _ O
Kini -X- _ O
gikumpirmar -X- _ O
ni -X- _ O
Provincial -X- _ O
Administrator -X- _ O
Karen -X- _ B-PER
Molas -X- _ I-PER
ngadto -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
Yes -X- _ B-ORG
The -X- _ I-ORG
Best -X- _ I-ORG
Dumaguete -X- _ I-ORG
sa -X- _ O
usa -X- _ O
ka -X- _ O
pahinabi -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
telepono. -X- _ O
Namatay -X- _ O
si -X- _ O
Reyes -X- _ O
kapin -X- _ O
2 -X- _ O
ka -X- _ O
bulan -X- _ O
sukad -X- _ O
niya -X- _ O
gipulihan -X- _ O
si -X- _ O
Gov. -X- _ O
Roel -X- _ B-PER
Degamo -X- _ I-PER
kinsa -X- _ O
gipatay -X- _ O
niadtong -X- _ O
Marso -X- _ O
4. -X- _ O
Sumala -X- _ O
pa -X- _ O
ni -X- _ O
Molas -X- _ B-PER
, -X- _ O
namatay -X- _ O
si -X- _ O
Reyes -X- _ B-PER
human -X- _ O
ang -X- _ O
taas -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
panahon -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
nakigbisog -X- _ O
kini -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
sakit -X- _ O
, -X- _ O
apan -X- _ O
wala -X- _ O
kini -X- _ O
naghatag -X- _ O
og -X- _ O
dugang -X- _ O
detalye. -X- _ O
Mao -X- _ O
kini -X- _ O
ang -X- _ O
unang -X- _ O
higayon -X- _ O
human -X- _ O
ang -X- _ O
kapin -X- _ O
usa -X- _ O
ka -X- _ O
dekada -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
nagsagunson -X- _ O
ang -X- _ O
pagkamatay -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
duha -X- _ O
ka -X- _ O
gobernador -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
probinsya. -X- _ O
Niadtong -X- _ O
2010 -X- _ O
, -X- _ O
namatay -X- _ O
si -X- _ O
Gov. -X- _ O
Emilio -X- _ B-PER
" -X- _ I-PER
Dodo -X- _ I-PER
" -X- _ I-PER
Macias -X- _ I-PER
II -X- _ I-PER
pipila -X- _ O
lamang -X- _ O
ka -X- _ O
semana -X- _ O
human -X- _ O
siya -X- _ O
nidaog -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
piniliay -X- _ O
niadtong -X- _ O
tuiga. -X- _ O
Ang -X- _ O
nipuli -X- _ O
niya -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
si -X- _ O
Gov. -X- _ O
Agustin -X- _ B-PER
Perdices -X- _ I-PER
, -X- _ O
namatay -X- _ O
sab -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
sakit -X- _ O
niadtong -X- _ O
Enero -X- _ O
2011 -X- _ O
, -X- _ O
pipila -X- _ O
ka -X- _ O
bulan -X- _ O
lang -X- _ O
human -X- _ O
niya -X- _ O
gipulihan -X- _ O
si -X- _ O
Macias -X- _ B-PER
. -X- _ O

DUMAGUETE-CVIRAA -X- _ B-ORG
MEDALISTS -X- _ O
, -X- _ O
MAKADAWAT -X- _ O
OG -X- _ O
CASH -X- _ O
INCENTIVES -X- _ O
GIKAN -X- _ O
SA -X- _ O
SYUDAD -X- _ O
Nihatag -X- _ O
ang -X- _ O
City -X- _ O
Government -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
Dumaguete -X- _ B-LOC
City -X- _ I-LOC
og -X- _ O
cash -X- _ O
incentives -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
tanang -X- _ O
medalists -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
bag-ohay -X- _ O
lang -X- _ O
nahuman -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
Central -X- _ B-ORG
Visayas -X- _ I-ORG
Athletics -X- _ I-ORG
Associations -X- _ I-ORG
Meet -X- _ I-ORG
( -X- _ I-ORG
CVIRAA -X- _ I-ORG
) -X- _ I-ORG
nga -X- _ O
gipahigayon -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
syudad -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
Carcar -X- _ B-LOC
, -X- _ I-LOC
Cebu. -X- _ I-LOC
Makadawat -X- _ O
og -X- _ O
P2,500 -X- _ O
ang -X- _ O
mga -X- _ O
gold -X- _ O
medalists -X- _ O
, -X- _ O
P2,000 -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
mga -X- _ O
silver -X- _ O
medalist -X- _ O
, -X- _ O
ug -X- _ O
P1,500 -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
mga -X- _ O
bronze -X- _ O
medalist. -X- _ O
Makadawat -X- _ O
sab -X- _ O
ang -X- _ O
mga -X- _ O
coach -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
mga -X- _ O
nidaog -X- _ O
og -X- _ O
cash -X- _ O
incentives -X- _ O
. -X- _ O

Taas-taas -X- _ O
ang -X- _ O
atong -X- _ O
weekend -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
ikaduhang -X- _ O
semana -X- _ O
sunod -X- _ O
bulan -X- _ O
tungod -X- _ O
aduna'y -X- _ O
usa -X- _ O
ka -X- _ O
regular -X- _ O
holiday -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
June -X- _ O
12 -X- _ O
, -X- _ O
isip -X- _ O
pagsaulog -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
Independence -X- _ B-OTHER
Day -X- _ I-OTHER
sa -X- _ O
Pilipinas -X- _ B-LOC
. -X- _ O

BASKETBOL -X- _ O
, -X- _ O
NISANGKO -X- _ O
SA -X- _ O
RAMBOL -X- _ O
Usa -X- _ O
ka -X- _ O
kagubot -X- _ O
ang -X- _ O
nahitabo -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
gipahigayong -X- _ O
basketball -X- _ O
game -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
Tanjay -X- _ B-LOC
City -X- _ I-LOC
niadtong -X- _ O
Lunes -X- _ O
, -X- _ O
May -X- _ O
29 -X- _ O
, -X- _ O
2023. -X- _ O
Sa -X- _ O
video -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
gi-post -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
netizen -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
si -X- _ O
Von -X- _ B-PER
Anjielo -X- _ I-PER
Ferolino -X- _ I-PER
, -X- _ O
makita -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
nagsumbagay -X- _ O
ang -X- _ O
referee -X- _ O
ug -X- _ O
usa -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
mga -X- _ O
giingong -X- _ O
audience. -X- _ O
Makita -X- _ O
sab -X- _ O
ang -X- _ O
pipila -X- _ O
ka -X- _ O
mga -X- _ O
indibidwal -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
nitabang -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
pagbulag -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
mga -X- _ O
nagsumbagay. -X- _ O
Sumala -X- _ O
pa -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
taho -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
kapulisan -X- _ O
, -X- _ O
giingong -X- _ O
nagsugod -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
trashtalk -X- _ O
ang -X- _ O
maong -X- _ O
sumbagay -X- _ O
human -X- _ O
gibugalbugalan -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
usa -X- _ O
ka -X- _ O
audience -X- _ O
member -X- _ O
ang -X- _ O
referee -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
dula -X- _ O
. -X- _ O

Pipila -X- _ O
ka -X- _ O
lugar -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
Negros -X- _ B-LOC
Oriental -X- _ I-LOC
ang -X- _ O
nagsuspenso -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
klase -X- _ O
karong -X- _ O
Martes -X- _ O
, -X- _ O
Mayo -X- _ O
30 -X- _ O
, -X- _ O
2023 -X- _ O
, -X- _ O
tungod -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
pag-ulan -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
dala -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
habagat -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
gipakusgan -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
Bagyong -X- _ O
# -X- _ O
BettyPH -X- _ B-OTHER
. -X- _ O

Gatusan -X- _ O
ka -X- _ O
aplikante -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
ganahang -X- _ O
moskuwela -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
Negros -X- _ B-LOC
Oriental -X- _ I-LOC
State -X- _ I-LOC
University -X- _ I-LOC
( -X- _ I-LOC
NORSU -X- _ I-LOC
) -X- _ I-LOC
ang -X- _ O
padayong -X- _ O
nagtalay -X- _ O
karon -X- _ O
gawas -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
campus -X- _ O
niini -X- _ O
karong -X- _ O
alas-9 -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
buntag -X- _ O
, -X- _ O
Mayo -X- _ O
30 -X- _ O
, -X- _ O
2023. -X- _ O
Kini -X- _ O
aron -X- _ O
pagkuha -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
NORSU -X- _ B-OTHER
Online -X- _ I-OTHER
Admission -X- _ I-OTHER
Test -X- _ I-OTHER
( -X- _ I-OTHER
NOAT -X- _ I-OTHER
) -X- _ I-OTHER
nga -X- _ O
nagsugod -X- _ O
niadtong -X- _ O
Lunes -X- _ O
, -X- _ O
Mayo -X- _ O
29 -X- _ O
, -X- _ O
ug -X- _ O
molungtad -X- _ O
hangtud -X- _ O
Hunyo -X- _ O
30 -X- _ O
. -X- _ O

GATOSAN -X- _ O
KA -X- _ O
APLIKANTE -X- _ O
SA -X- _ O
NORSU -X- _ B-LOC
, -X- _ O
NAGTALAY -X- _ O
GIHAPON -X- _ O
BISA’G -X- _ O
GABIING -X- _ O
DAKO -X- _ O
Tungang -X- _ O
gabii -X- _ O
na -X- _ O
apan -X- _ O
gatosan -X- _ O
gihapon -X- _ O
ka -X- _ O
estudyante -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
ganahang -X- _ O
moskuwela -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
Negros -X- _ B-LOC
Oriental -X- _ I-LOC
State -X- _ I-LOC
University -X- _ I-LOC
ang -X- _ O
naglinya -X- _ O
aron -X- _ O
pagkuha -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
NORSU -X- _ B-OTHER
Online -X- _ I-OTHER
Admission -X- _ I-OTHER
Test -X- _ I-OTHER
( -X- _ I-OTHER
NOAT -X- _ I-OTHER
) -X- _ I-OTHER
. -X- _ O
Gikan -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
Gate -X- _ O
3 -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
NORSU -X- _ B-LOC
Dumaguete -X- _ I-LOC
Campus -X- _ I-LOC
, -X- _ O
niabot -X- _ O
na -X- _ O
ang -X- _ O
linya -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
mga -X- _ O
aplikante -X- _ O
hangtud -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
Dumaguete -X- _ B-LOC
Perpetual -X- _ I-LOC
Church. -X- _ I-LOC
Una -X- _ O
nang -X- _ O
gipasidaan -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
tunghaan -X- _ O
ang -X- _ O
mga -X- _ O
aplikante -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
layo -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
Dumaguete -X- _ B-LOC
nga -X- _ O
kuhaon -X- _ O
ang -X- _ O
NOAT -X- _ B-OTHER
online -X- _ O
gikan -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
ilang -X- _ O
mga -X- _ O
balay. -X- _ O
Apan -X- _ O
duna -X- _ O
gihapoy -X- _ O
mga -X- _ O
estudyante -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
nisugal -X- _ O
pagbiyahe -X- _ O
nganhi -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
dakbayan -X- _ O
aron -X- _ O
madawat -X- _ O
unta -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
NORSU -X- _ B-LOC
alang -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
kolehiyo. -X- _ O
Ipahigayon -X- _ O
ang -X- _ O
NOAT -X- _ B-OTHER
gikan -X- _ O
Mayo -X- _ O
29 -X- _ O
hangtud -X- _ O
Hunyo -X- _ O
30 -X- _ O
. -X- _ O

DGTE -X- _ B-LOC
, -X- _ O
GIPANGHINGUSGAN -X- _ O
ANG -X- _ O
PAGBAKUNA -X- _ O
SA -X- _ O
MGA -X- _ O
BATA -X- _ O
BATOK -X- _ O
MEASLES -X- _ O
UG -X- _ O
RUBELLA -X- _ O
Gipanghingusgan -X- _ O
pa -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
City -X- _ O
Governement -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
dakbayan -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
Dumaguete -X- _ B-LOC
ang -X- _ O
pagbakuna -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
mga -X- _ O
kwalipikadong -X- _ O
bata -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
nag-edad -X- _ O
og -X- _ O
9 -X- _ O
months -X- _ O
hangtod -X- _ O
5 -X- _ O
years -X- _ O
old -X- _ O
batok -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
measles -X- _ O
ug -X- _ O
rebella. -X- _ O
Gipatuman -X- _ O
karon -X- _ O
ang -X- _ O
supplemental -X- _ O
immunization -X- _ O
activity -X- _ O
City -X- _ O
Health -X- _ O
Office -X- _ O
, -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
DOH -X- _ B-ORG
sa -X- _ O
Negros -X- _ B-LOC
Oriental -X- _ I-LOC
ug -X- _ O
Provincial -X- _ B-LOC
Health -X- _ I-LOC
Office. -X- _ I-LOC
Tumong -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
maong -X- _ O
aktibidad -X- _ O
ang -X- _ O
pagbakuna -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
mga -X- _ O
kwalipikadong -X- _ O
bata -X- _ O
batok -X- _ O
measles -X- _ O
ug -X- _ O
rubella -X- _ O
aron -X- _ O
modako -X- _ O
sila -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
biskog -X- _ O
ang -X- _ O
panglawas -X- _ O
ug -X- _ O
malikayan -X- _ O
ang -X- _ O
mga -X- _ O
serious -X- _ O
disabilities. -X- _ O
Alang -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
schedules -X- _ O
, -X- _ O
mahimong -X- _ O
makig-coordinate -X- _ O
ang -X- _ O
mga -X- _ O
ginikanan -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
ilang -X- _ O
tagsa-tagsa -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
mga -X- _ O
barangay -X- _ O
health -X- _ O
centers -X- _ O
o -X- _ O
maghulat -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
mga -X- _ O
health -X- _ O
workers -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
house-to-house -X- _ O
immunization -X- _ O
. -X- _ O

Mas -X- _ O
nikusog -X- _ O
pa -X- _ O
ang -X- _ O
Super -X- _ O
Typhoon -X- _ O
# -X- _ O
Mawar -X- _ B-OTHER
samtang -X- _ O
gipuntirya -X- _ O
niini -X- _ O
ang -X- _ O
kadagatan -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
Pilipinas. -X- _ B-LOC
Dala -X- _ O
karon -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
maong -X- _ O
bagyo -X- _ O
ang -X- _ O
kakusgon -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
hangin -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
moabot -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
205 -X- _ O
kph -X- _ O
ug -X- _ O
paghuros -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
moabot -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
290 -X- _ O
kph. -X- _ O
Naglihok -X- _ O
kini -X- _ O
paingon -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
amihanan-kasadpang -X- _ O
direksyon -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
aduna'y -X- _ O
kapaspason -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
15 -X- _ O
kph. -X- _ O
Gilaomang -X- _ O
mokusog -X- _ O
pa -X- _ O
kini -X- _ O
samtang -X- _ O
pasulod -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
Philippine -X- _ B-OTHER
Area -X- _ I-OTHER
of -X- _ I-OTHER
Responsibility -X- _ I-OTHER
( -X- _ I-OTHER
PAR -X- _ I-OTHER
) -X- _ I-OTHER
tungod -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
" -X- _ O
very -X- _ O
favorable -X- _ O
" -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
kadagatan -X- _ O
. -X- _ O

CEBU -X- _ B-ORG
PACIFIC -X- _ I-ORG
, -X- _ O
NAGTANYAG -X- _ O
OG -X- _ O
P88 -X- _ O
NGA -X- _ O
PLITE -X- _ O
HANGTOD -X- _ O
MAY -X- _ O
27 -X- _ O
Nagtanyag -X- _ O
ang -X- _ O
Cebu -X- _ B-ORG
Pacific -X- _ I-ORG
og -X- _ O
P88 -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
one-way -X- _ O
base -X- _ O
fare -X- _ O
alang -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
ilang -X- _ O
bag-ong -X- _ O
seat -X- _ O
sale -X- _ O
paingon -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
local -X- _ O
ug -X- _ O
international -X- _ O
destinations. -X- _ O
Lakip -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
international -X- _ O
destinations -X- _ O
ang -X- _ O
Taipei -X- _ B-LOC
, -X- _ O
Tokyo -X- _ B-LOC
, -X- _ O
Macau -X- _ B-LOC
, -X- _ O
ug -X- _ O
Ho -X- _ B-LOC
Chi -X- _ I-LOC
Minh -X- _ I-LOC
, -X- _ O
samtang -X- _ O
apil -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
local -X- _ O
destinations -X- _ O
ang -X- _ O
Laoag -X- _ B-LOC
, -X- _ O
Puerto -X- _ B-LOC
Princesa -X- _ I-LOC
, -X- _ O
Bacolod -X- _ B-LOC
, -X- _ O
ug -X- _ O
Davao. -X- _ B-LOC
Hangtod -X- _ O
lamang -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
May -X- _ O
27 -X- _ O
ang -X- _ O
P88 -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
promo -X- _ O
ug -X- _ O
aduna'y -X- _ O
travel -X- _ O
period -X- _ O
gikan -X- _ O
June -X- _ O
1 -X- _ O
hangtod -X- _ O
Nov. -X- _ O
30 -X- _ O
, -X- _ O
2023 -X- _ O
. -X- _ O

Makita -X- _ O
na -X- _ O
sab -X- _ O
ang -X- _ O
mata -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
Super -X- _ O
Typhoon -X- _ O
# -X- _ O
Mawar -X- _ B-OTHER
human -X- _ O
niini -X- _ O
gikusokuso -X- _ O
ang -X- _ O
# -X- _ O
Guam -X- _ B-ORG
kagahapong -X- _ O
adlawa. -X- _ O
Gikabalak-ang -X- _ O
mosulod -X- _ O
kini -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
Philippine -X- _ B-OTHER
Area -X- _ I-OTHER
of -X- _ I-OTHER
Responsibility -X- _ I-OTHER
( -X- _ I-OTHER
PAR -X- _ I-OTHER
) -X- _ I-OTHER
ugma -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
gabii -X- _ O
o -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
kadlawon -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
Sabado. -X- _ O
Sa -X- _ O
oras -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
mosulod -X- _ O
kini -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
PAR -X- _ B-OTHER
, -X- _ O
tawgon -X- _ O
kini -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
PAGASA -X- _ B-ORG
og -X- _ O
# -X- _ O
BettyPH. -X- _ B-OTHER
Sa -X- _ O
pagkakaron -X- _ O
, -X- _ O
nagpabiling -X- _ O
maba -X- _ O
ang -X- _ O
posibilidad -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
mo-landfall -X- _ O
kini -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
nasud. -X- _ O
Apan -X- _ O
, -X- _ O
gilaoman -X- _ O
karon -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
mas -X- _ O
magkaduol -X- _ O
kini -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
# -X- _ O
ExtremeNorthernLuzon -X- _ B-LOC
sa -X- _ O
Lunes-Miyerkules -X- _ O
( -X- _ O
May -X- _ O
29-31 -X- _ O
) -X- _ O
, -X- _ O
isip -X- _ O
usa -X- _ O
ka -X- _ O
makadaot -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
bagyo. -X- _ O
Sumala -X- _ O
pa -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
Japan -X- _ B-ORG
Meteorological -X- _ I-ORG
Agency -X- _ I-ORG
( -X- _ I-ORG
JMA -X- _ I-ORG
) -X- _ I-ORG
, -X- _ O
posibleng -X- _ O
moabot -X- _ O
ang -X- _ O
bagyo -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
" -X- _ O
VIOLENT -X- _ O
" -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
kategorya -X- _ O
pagsulod -X- _ O
niini -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
PAR -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
adunay -X- _ O
kakusgon -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
moabot -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
205 -X- _ O
kph -X- _ O
ug -X- _ O
paghuros -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
290 -X- _ O
kph. -X- _ O
Kinahanglang -X- _ O
kining -X- _ O
pangandaman -X- _ O
ilabi -X- _ O
na -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
mga -X- _ O
nagpuyo -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
Hilagang -X- _ B-LOC
Luzon -X- _ I-LOC
. -X- _ O

TEENAGER -X- _ O
SA -X- _ O
TAIWAN -X- _ B-LOC
, -X- _ O
NAPALGANG -X- _ O
PATAY -X- _ O
HUMAN -X- _ O
NAGPAKASAL -X- _ O
SA -X- _ O
LALAKI -X- _ O
NGA -X- _ O
BAG-O -X- _ O
RA -X- _ O
NIYANG -X- _ O
NAKAILA -X- _ O
Usa -X- _ O
ka -X- _ O
18-anyos -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
high -X- _ O
school -X- _ O
student -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
Taiwan -X- _ B-LOC
ang -X- _ O
napalgang -X- _ O
patay -X- _ O
duha -X- _ O
lamang -X- _ O
ka -X- _ O
oras -X- _ O
human -X- _ O
giingong -X- _ O
naminyo -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
usa -X- _ O
ka -X- _ O
lalaki -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
kaduha -X- _ O
pa -X- _ O
lang -X- _ O
niya -X- _ O
nahimamat -X- _ O
, -X- _ O
sumala -X- _ O
pa -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
inahan -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
biktima. -X- _ O
Giila -X- _ O
ang -X- _ O
estudyante -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
pangalang -X- _ O
Lai -X- _ B-PER
, -X- _ O
usa -X- _ O
ka -X- _ O
lalaki -X- _ O
, -X- _ O
18 -X- _ O
anyos -X- _ O
, -X- _ O
ug -X- _ O
residente -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
Taichung -X- _ B-LOC
sa -X- _ O
naasoy -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
nasud. -X- _ O
Si -X- _ O
Lain -X- _ B-PER
unta -X- _ O
ang -X- _ O
mo-inherit -X- _ O
kon -X- _ O
makapanunod -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
mga -X- _ O
kabtangan -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
nagkantidad -X- _ O
og -X- _ O
$ -X- _ O
500m -X- _ O
gikan -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
iyang -X- _ O
amahan. -X- _ O
Nadiskobrehan -X- _ O
ang -X- _ O
iyang -X- _ O
patayng -X- _ O
lawas -X- _ O
niadtong -X- _ O
May -X- _ O
4 -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
nagbuy-od -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
yuta -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
gawas -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
usa -X- _ O
ka -X- _ O
apartment -X- _ O
building -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
Beitun -X- _ B-LOC
district. -X- _ O
Giila -X- _ O
sab -X- _ O
ang -X- _ O
iyang -X- _ O
bana -X- _ O
og -X- _ O
duha -X- _ O
ka -X- _ O
oras -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
si -X- _ O
Hsia -X- _ B-PER
, -X- _ O
usa -X- _ O
ka -X- _ O
lalaki -X- _ O
, -X- _ O
26 -X- _ O
anyos -X- _ O
, -X- _ O
kinsa -X- _ O
nagpuyo -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
ika-10th -X- _ O
floor -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
maong -X- _ O
apartment -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
nahisgutang -X- _ O
lugar. -X- _ O
Sa -X- _ O
usa -X- _ O
ka -X- _ O
press -X- _ O
conference -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
gipahigayon -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
inahan -X- _ O
ni -X- _ O
Lai -X- _ B-PER
, -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
si -X- _ O
Chen -X- _ B-PER
, -X- _ O
gipahibalo -X- _ O
niya -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
nag-alegar -X- _ O
sila -X- _ O
og -X- _ O
foul -X- _ O
play -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
kamatayon -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
iyang -X- _ O
anak. -X- _ O
Namatay -X- _ O
si -X- _ O
Lai -X- _ B-PER
usa -X- _ O
lang -X- _ O
ka -X- _ O
adlaw -X- _ O
pagkahuman -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
pagsunog -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
iyang -X- _ O
amahan -X- _ O
, -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
namatay -X- _ O
niadtong -X- _ O
katapusang -X- _ O
semana -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
Abril. -X- _ O
Matod -X- _ O
pa -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
iyang -X- _ O
mga -X- _ O
abogado -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
ang -X- _ O
pamilya -X- _ O
nagtuo -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
si -X- _ O
Lai -X- _ B-PER
, -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
nakapanunod -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
mga -X- _ O
30 -X- _ O
ka -X- _ O
mga -X- _ O
properties -X- _ O
ug -X- _ O
kwarta -X- _ O
maoy -X- _ O
hinungdan -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
pagpatay. -X- _ O
Dugang -X- _ O
pa -X- _ O
, -X- _ O
si -X- _ O
Hsia -X- _ B-PER
nga -X- _ O
primary -X- _ O
suspect -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
pagpatay -X- _ O
ug -X- _ O
gibuhian -X- _ O
kini -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
pyansa -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
nagkantidad -X- _ O
og -X- _ O
$ -X- _ O
300,000 -X- _ O
. -X- _ O

PAGASA -X- _ B-ORG
, -X- _ O
GIBANTAYAN -X- _ O
ANG -X- _ O
POSIBLENG -X- _ O
MAHIMONG -X- _ O
'SUPER -X- _ O
TYPHOON -X- _ O
' -X- _ O
GAWAS -X- _ O
SA -X- _ O
PAR -X- _ B-LOC
Gibantayan -X- _ O
karon -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
PAGASA -X- _ B-ORG
ang -X- _ O
usa -X- _ O
ka -X- _ O
tropical -X- _ O
cyclone -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
aduna'y -X- _ O
posibilidad -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
mahimong -X- _ O
super -X- _ O
typhoon -X- _ O
gawas -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
Philippine -X- _ B-LOC
Area -X- _ I-LOC
of -X- _ I-LOC
Responsibility -X- _ I-LOC
( -X- _ I-LOC
PAR -X- _ I-LOC
) -X- _ I-LOC
. -X- _ O
Mao -X- _ O
kini -X- _ O
ang -X- _ O
gibutyag -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
maong -X- _ O
state -X- _ O
weather -X- _ O
bureau -X- _ O
karong -X- _ O
adlawa -X- _ O
, -X- _ O
May -X- _ O
22 -X- _ O
, -X- _ O
2023. -X- _ O
Sa -X- _ O
ilang -X- _ O
pinakabag-ong -X- _ O
public -X- _ O
weather -X- _ O
forecast -X- _ O
, -X- _ O
ulahing -X- _ O
nakita -X- _ O
ang -X- _ O
bagyo -X- _ O
mga -X- _ O
2,330 -X- _ O
km -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
silangang -X- _ O
bahin -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
Mindanao. -X- _ B-LOC
" -X- _ O
It -X- _ O
has -X- _ O
maximum -X- _ O
sustained -X- _ O
winds -X- _ O
of -X- _ O
130 -X- _ O
kph -X- _ O
near -X- _ O
the -X- _ O
center -X- _ O
and -X- _ O
gusts -X- _ O
of -X- _ O
up -X- _ O
to -X- _ O
160 -X- _ O
kph. -X- _ O
It -X- _ O
is -X- _ O
moving -X- _ O
west -X- _ O
northweatward -X- _ O
at -X- _ O
15 -X- _ O
kph -X- _ O
, -X- _ O
" -X- _ O
matud -X- _ O
pa -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
report. -X- _ O
Apan -X- _ O
gisubli -X- _ O
ni -X- _ O
weather -X- _ O
forecaster -X- _ O
Anna -X- _ B-PER
Clauren-Jorda -X- _ I-PER
nga -X- _ O
aduna'y -X- _ O
low -X- _ O
probability -X- _ O
ang -X- _ O
maong -X- _ O
bagyo -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
mag-landfall -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
Pilipinas -X- _ B-LOC
. -X- _ O

PATAYNG -X- _ O
LAWAS -X- _ O
, -X- _ O
NAPALGAN -X- _ O
SA -X- _ O
BAYBAYON -X- _ O
SA -X- _ O
STA. -X- _ B-ORG
CATALINA -X- _ I-ORG
Usa -X- _ O
ka -X- _ O
patayng -X- _ O
lawas -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
tigulang -X- _ O
ang -X- _ O
nakit-an -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
baybayon -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
Sitio -X- _ B-LOC
Talisay -X- _ I-LOC
, -X- _ I-LOC
Barangay -X- _ I-LOC
Poblacion -X- _ I-LOC
sa -X- _ O
Sta. -X- _ B-LOC
Catalina -X- _ I-LOC
mga -X- _ O
alas-7:10 -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
buntag -X- _ O
niadtong -X- _ O
May -X- _ O
20 -X- _ O
, -X- _ O
2023. -X- _ O
Giila -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
kapulisan -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
Sta. -X- _ B-LOC
Catalina -X- _ I-LOC
ang -X- _ O
biktima -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
si -X- _ O
Veronica -X- _ B-PER
Iligan -X- _ I-PER
Padilla -X- _ I-PER
, -X- _ O
67 -X- _ O
anyos -X- _ O
, -X- _ O
minyo -X- _ O
, -X- _ O
ug -X- _ O
lumolupyo -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
Purok -X- _ B-LOC
3 -X- _ I-LOC
, -X- _ I-LOC
Barangay -X- _ I-LOC
Caranoche -X- _ I-LOC
sa -X- _ O
naasoy -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
lungsod. -X- _ O
Matud -X- _ O
pa -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
inisyal -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
imbestigasyon -X- _ O
, -X- _ O
nitambong -X- _ O
si -X- _ O
Padilla -X- _ B-PER
sa -X- _ O
birthday -X- _ O
celebration -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
iyang -X- _ O
pag-umangkon -X- _ O
ug -X- _ O
nag-inom-inom -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
dagat -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
Villareal -X- _ B-LOC
sa -X- _ O
Bayawan -X- _ B-LOC
City. -X- _ I-LOC
Ulahing -X- _ O
nakit-an -X- _ O
ang -X- _ O
biktima -X- _ O
mga -X- _ O
alas-3:00 -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
hapon -X- _ O
niadtong -X- _ O
May -X- _ O
19 -X- _ O
, -X- _ O
2023. -X- _ O
Sumala -X- _ O
pa -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
mga -X- _ O
kabanay -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
biktima -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
aduna -X- _ O
kini -X- _ O
kanhing -X- _ O
record -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
Alzheimer's. -X- _ B-OTHER
Dugang -X- _ O
pa -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
kapulisan -X- _ O
, -X- _ O
wala'y -X- _ O
timailhan -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
physical -X- _ O
injury -X- _ O
ang -X- _ O
nakita -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
lawas -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
biktima. -X- _ O
Gitambagan -X- _ O
sab -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
kapulisan -X- _ O
ang -X- _ O
pamilya -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
biktima -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
ipaubos -X- _ O
kini -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
autopsy -X- _ O
aron -X- _ O
masuta -X- _ O
ang -X- _ O
hinungdan -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
kamatayon -X- _ O
niini -X- _ O
, -X- _ O
apan -X- _ O
gibalibaran -X- _ O
kini -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
pamilya -X- _ O
. -X- _ O

MGA -X- _ O
KASO -X- _ O
SA -X- _ O
ASF -X- _ B-OTHER
NAKOMPIRMAR -X- _ O
SA -X- _ O
DAUIN -X- _ B-LOC
, -X- _ O
PIPILA -X- _ O
KA -X- _ O
BABOY -X- _ O
SA -X- _ O
LUNGSOD -X- _ O
GIPAMATAY -X- _ O
Nagpositibo -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
African -X- _ B-OTHER
Swine -X- _ I-OTHER
Fever -X- _ I-OTHER
( -X- _ I-OTHER
ASF -X- _ I-OTHER
) -X- _ I-OTHER
ang -X- _ O
pipila -X- _ O
ka -X- _ O
mga -X- _ O
baboy -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
namatay -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
Purok -X- _ O
1 -X- _ O
ug -X- _ O
2 -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
Barangay -X- _ B-LOC
Maayongtubig -X- _ I-LOC
sa -X- _ O
lungsod -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
Dauin. -X- _ B-LOC
Mao -X- _ O
kini -X- _ O
ang -X- _ O
gikompirmar -X- _ O
ni -X- _ O
Mayor -X- _ O
Galicano -X- _ B-PER
Truita -X- _ I-PER
pinaagi -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
Executive -X- _ B-OTHER
Order -X- _ I-OTHER
No. -X- _ I-OTHER
2023-19.1. -X- _ I-OTHER
Base -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
laboratory -X- _ O
samples -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
gipadala -X- _ O
ngadto -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
Bureau -X- _ B-ORG
of -X- _ I-ORG
Animal -X- _ I-ORG
Industry-Central -X- _ I-ORG
Office -X- _ I-ORG
, -X- _ O
kompirmado -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
nagpositibo -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
ASF -X- _ B-OTHER
virus -X- _ O
ang -X- _ O
mga -X- _ O
namatay -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
baboy -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
naasoy -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
lugar. -X- _ O
Ubos -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
EO -X- _ O
2023-19.1 -X- _ O
, -X- _ O
temporaryo -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
ginadili -X- _ O
ang -X- _ O
pagpasulod -X- _ O
ug -X- _ O
pagpagawas -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
buhi -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
mga -X- _ O
baboy -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
naglakip -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
fresh -X- _ O
and -X- _ O
frozen -X- _ O
products. -X- _ O
Ginadili -X- _ O
sab -X- _ O
ang -X- _ O
pag-ihaw -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
mga -X- _ O
baboy -X- _ O
ug -X- _ O
kinahanglang -X- _ O
patyon -X- _ O
ang -X- _ O
tanang -X- _ O
baboy -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
anaa -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
500-meter -X- _ O
radius -X- _ O
gikan -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
maong -X- _ O
dapit. -X- _ O
Gimandoan -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
LGU -X- _ B-ORG
Dauin -X- _ I-ORG
uban -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
koordinasyon -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
Provincial -X- _ B-ORG
Veterinary -X- _ I-ORG
Office -X- _ I-ORG
nga -X- _ O
ipatuman -X- _ O
dayon -X- _ O
ang -X- _ O
maong -X- _ O
kamanduan -X- _ O
aron -X- _ O
malikayan -X- _ O
ang -X- _ O
pagkuyanap -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
ASF -X- _ B-OTHER
virus -X- _ O
. -X- _ O

TRAHEDYA -X- _ O
SA -X- _ O
PALITON -X- _ B-LOC
BEACH -X- _ I-LOC
: -X- _ O
BATA -X- _ O
PATAY -X- _ O
, -X- _ O
BABAYE -X- _ O
ANGOL -X- _ O
SA -X- _ O
DISGRASYA -X- _ O
SA -X- _ O
BANGKA -X- _ O
SA -X- _ O
SIQUIJOR -X- _ B-LOC
Patay -X- _ O
ang -X- _ O
usa -X- _ O
ka -X- _ O
6 -X- _ O
anyos -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
batang -X- _ O
babaye -X- _ O
atol -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
karera -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
mga -X- _ O
bangka -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
natapos -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
disgrasya -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
inilang -X- _ O
Paliton -X- _ B-LOC
Beach -X- _ I-LOC
sa -X- _ O
lungsod -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
San -X- _ B-LOC
Juan -X- _ I-LOC
, -X- _ I-LOC
Siquijor -X- _ I-LOC
kagahapon -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
buntag -X- _ O
, -X- _ O
Mayo -X- _ O
21 -X- _ O
, -X- _ O
2023. -X- _ O
Usa -X- _ O
pud -X- _ O
ka -X- _ O
24-anyos -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
babaye -X- _ O
ang -X- _ O
naangol -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
maong -X- _ O
trahedya -X- _ O
human -X- _ O
kini -X- _ O
makahiagom -X- _ O
og -X- _ O
samad -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
ulo. -X- _ O
Sumala -X- _ O
pa -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
report -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
kapulisan -X- _ O
, -X- _ O
naglumba -X- _ O
ang -X- _ O
pipila -X- _ O
ka -X- _ O
bangka -X- _ O
atol -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
usa -X- _ O
ka -X- _ O
" -X- _ O
Bangkarera -X- _ O
" -X- _ O
kagahapon -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
naasoy -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
baybayon. -X- _ O
Giklaro -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
San -X- _ B-ORG
Juan -X- _ I-ORG
PNP -X- _ I-ORG
nga -X- _ O
dunay -X- _ O
permit -X- _ O
ang -X- _ O
maong -X- _ O
lumba. -X- _ O
Atol -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
maong -X- _ O
lumba -X- _ O
, -X- _ O
nawad-an -X- _ O
og -X- _ O
kontrol -X- _ O
ang -X- _ O
usa -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
mga -X- _ O
nisalmot -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
bangka -X- _ O
ug -X- _ O
nilahos -X- _ O
kini -X- _ O
pabalik -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
baybayon. -X- _ O
Tungod -X- _ O
niini -X- _ O
, -X- _ O
naligsan -X- _ O
ang -X- _ O
usa -X- _ O
ka -X- _ O
batang -X- _ O
babaye -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
maoy -X- _ O
hinungdan -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
kamatayon -X- _ O
niini. -X- _ O
Anaa -X- _ O
na -X- _ O
karon -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
kustodiya -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
kapulisan -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
San -X- _ B-LOC
Juan -X- _ I-LOC
ang -X- _ O
driver -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
nakaligis -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
bangka. -X- _ O
Gikatahong -X- _ O
pasakaan -X- _ O
kini -X- _ O
og -X- _ O
mga -X- _ O
tukmang -X- _ O
kaso -X- _ O
. -X- _ O

4 -X- _ O
KA -X- _ O
GIINGONG -X- _ O
NPA -X- _ O
PATAY -X- _ O
SA -X- _ O
PINUSILAY -X- _ O
SA -X- _ O
GUIHULNGAN -X- _ B-LOC
CITY -X- _ I-LOC
Upat -X- _ O
ka -X- _ O
giingong -X- _ O
sakop -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
rebeldeng -X- _ O
New -X- _ B-ORG
People’s -X- _ I-ORG
Army -X- _ I-ORG
( -X- _ I-ORG
NPA -X- _ I-ORG
) -X- _ I-ORG
ang -X- _ O
napatay -X- _ O
atol -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
pinusilay -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
maong -X- _ O
grupo -X- _ O
ug -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
militar -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
bukirang -X- _ O
bahin -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
Guihulngan -X- _ B-LOC
City -X- _ I-LOC
ganinang -X- _ O
buntag -X- _ O
, -X- _ O
Mayo -X- _ O
21 -X- _ O
, -X- _ O
2023. -X- _ O
Kini -X- _ O
sumala -X- _ O
pa -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
pamahayag -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
Philippine -X- _ B-ORG
Army. -X- _ I-ORG
Gibutyag -X- _ O
sab -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
militar -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
dunay -X- _ O
mga -X- _ O
armas -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
nasakmit -X- _ O
gikan -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
giingong -X- _ O
rebelde. -X- _ O
Walo -X- _ O
ka -X- _ O
armado -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
gidudahang -X- _ O
sakop -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
NPA -X- _ B-ORG
ang -X- _ O
nakigsukliay -X- _ O
og -X- _ O
bala -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
mga -X- _ O
sakop -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
62nd -X- _ B-LOC
Infantry -X- _ I-LOC
Battalion -X- _ I-LOC
sa -X- _ O
Philippine -X- _ B-LOC
Army. -X- _ I-LOC
Nilungtad -X- _ O
og -X- _ O
20 -X- _ O
minutos -X- _ O
ang -X- _ O
maong -X- _ O
pinusilay -X- _ O
. -X- _ O

PINAKAGULANG -X- _ O
NGA -X- _ O
IRO -X- _ O
SA -X- _ O
KALIBUTAN -X- _ O
, -X- _ O
GISAULOG -X- _ O
ANG -X- _ O
IYANG -X- _ O
IKA-31 -X- _ O
KA -X- _ O
BIRTHDAY -X- _ O
Bag-ohay -X- _ O
lang -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
nagsaulog -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
iyang -X- _ O
ika-31 -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
birthday -X- _ O
ang -X- _ O
pinakagulang -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
iro -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
kalibutan -X- _ O
, -X- _ O
matud -X- _ O
pa -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
Guinness -X- _ B-OTHER
Book -X- _ I-OTHER
of -X- _ I-OTHER
World -X- _ I-OTHER
Records. -X- _ I-OTHER
Gisaulog -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
irong -X- _ O
si -X- _ O
Bobi -X- _ O
ang -X- _ O
iyang -X- _ O
birthday -X- _ O
niadtong -X- _ O
Sabado -X- _ O
atol -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
usa -X- _ O
ka -X- _ O
party -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
iyang -X- _ O
balay -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
Conqueiros -X- _ B-LOC
, -X- _ I-LOC
Portugal. -X- _ I-LOC
Usa -X- _ O
ka -X- _ O
purebred -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
Rafeiro -X- _ B-PER
do -X- _ I-PER
Alentejo -X- _ I-PER
ang -X- _ O
irong -X- _ O
si -X- _ O
Bobi -X- _ O
, -X- _ O
usa -X- _ O
ka -X- _ O
lahi -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
Portuguese -X- _ B-OTHER
nga -X- _ O
iro. -X- _ O
Sumala -X- _ O
pa -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
tag-iyang -X- _ O
si -X- _ O
Leonel -X- _ B-PER
Costa -X- _ I-PER
, -X- _ O
gitambongan -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
kapin -X- _ O
100 -X- _ O
ka -X- _ O
mga -X- _ O
bisita -X- _ O
ang -X- _ O
usa -X- _ O
ka -X- _ O
" -X- _ O
very -X- _ O
traditional -X- _ O
" -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
party. -X- _ O
Dugang -X- _ O
pa -X- _ O
niya -X- _ O
, -X- _ O
ang -X- _ O
hinungdan -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
taas -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
kinabuhi -X- _ O
ni -X- _ O
Bobi -X- _ O
mao -X- _ O
ang -X- _ O
" -X- _ O
calm -X- _ O
, -X- _ O
peaceful -X- _ O
environment -X- _ O
. -X- _ O
" -X- _ O

KAPIN -X- _ O
7-M -X- _ O
KA -X- _ O
MGA -X- _ O
PINOY -X- _ O
, -X- _ O
MAKADAWAT -X- _ O
SA -X- _ O
INFLATION -X- _ O
AYUDA -X- _ O
Kapin -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
pito -X- _ O
ka -X- _ O
milyon -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
mga -X- _ O
Pilipino -X- _ B-OTHER
ang -X- _ O
makabenepisyo -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
programa -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
Department -X- _ B-ORG
of -X- _ I-ORG
Social -X- _ I-ORG
Welfare -X- _ I-ORG
and -X- _ I-ORG
Development -X- _ I-ORG
( -X- _ I-ORG
DSWD -X- _ I-ORG
) -X- _ I-ORG
nga -X- _ O
Targeted -X- _ B-ORG
Cash -X- _ I-ORG
Transfer -X- _ I-ORG
( -X- _ I-ORG
TCT -X- _ I-ORG
) -X- _ I-ORG
. -X- _ O
Sumala -X- _ O
pa -X- _ O
ni -X- _ O
DSWD -X- _ B-ORG
Assistant -X- _ O
Secretary -X- _ O
Romel -X- _ B-PER
Lopez -X- _ I-PER
, -X- _ O
motabang -X- _ O
ang -X- _ O
ilang -X- _ O
departamento -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
paghatag -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
P500 -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
cash -X- _ O
assistance -X- _ O
matag -X- _ O
bulan -X- _ O
aron -X- _ O
pagtabang -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
mga -X- _ O
benepisyaryo -X- _ O
niini -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
makabawi -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
pagsaka -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
mga -X- _ O
presyo -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
palaliton. -X- _ O
Bag-ohay -X- _ O
lang -X- _ O
, -X- _ O
giaprobahan -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
Department -X- _ B-ORG
of -X- _ I-ORG
Budget -X- _ I-ORG
and -X- _ I-ORG
Management -X- _ I-ORG
( -X- _ I-ORG
DBM -X- _ I-ORG
) -X- _ I-ORG
ang -X- _ O
Special -X- _ B-OTHER
Allotment -X- _ I-OTHER
Release -X- _ I-OTHER
Order -X- _ I-OTHER
sa -X- _ O
P7.68 -X- _ O
bilyones -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
pondo -X- _ O
alang -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
TCT -X- _ B-ORG
program -X- _ O
. -X- _ O

Usa -X- _ O
ka -X- _ O
nigradwar -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
Negros -X- _ B-LOC
Oriental -X- _ I-LOC
State -X- _ I-LOC
University -X- _ I-LOC
( -X- _ I-LOC
NORSU -X- _ I-LOC
) -X- _ I-LOC
ang -X- _ O
nabutang -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
Rank -X- _ O
6 -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
March -X- _ O
2023 -X- _ O
Licensure -X- _ O
Exam -X- _ O
for -X- _ O
Professional -X- _ O
Teachers. -X- _ O
Matud -X- _ O
pa -X- _ O
kini -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
gipagawas -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
resulta -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
Professional -X- _ B-OTHER
Regulation -X- _ I-OTHER
Commission -X- _ I-OTHER
( -X- _ I-OTHER
PRC -X- _ I-OTHER
) -X- _ I-OTHER
karong -X- _ O
adlawa -X- _ O
, -X- _ O
May -X- _ O
19 -X- _ O
, -X- _ O
2023. -X- _ O
Nakuha -X- _ O
ni -X- _ O
Alvord -X- _ B-PER
Van -X- _ I-PER
Patten -X- _ I-PER
Valencia -X- _ I-PER
ang -X- _ O
91.80 -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
passing -X- _ O
rate -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
Secondary -X- _ O
Level -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
naasoy -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
exam -X- _ O
. -X- _ O

Hustisya -X- _ O
ang -X- _ O
gipanawagan -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
mga -X- _ O
animal -X- _ O
lovers -X- _ O
alang -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
duha -X- _ O
ka -X- _ O
iro -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
gipusil -X- _ O
patay -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
Metropolitan -X- _ B-LOC
police -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
London -X- _ B-LOC
, -X- _ I-LOC
United -X- _ I-LOC
Kingdom. -X- _ I-LOC
Ang -X- _ O
duha -X- _ O
ka -X- _ O
Staffordshire -X- _ B-OTHER
bull -X- _ O
terrier -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
sila -X- _ O
si -X- _ O
Marshall -X- _ O
ug -X- _ O
Millions -X- _ O
, -X- _ O
gipanag-iya -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
usa -X- _ O
ka -X- _ O
46-anyos -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
homeless -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
si -X- _ O
Louie -X- _ B-PER
Turnbull. -X- _ I-PER
Sumala -X- _ O
pa -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
report -X- _ O
, -X- _ O
gipusil -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
mga -X- _ O
pulis -X- _ O
ang -X- _ O
mga -X- _ O
iro -X- _ O
tungod -X- _ O
gapamaghot -X- _ O
kini -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
usa -X- _ O
ka -X- _ O
babayi. -X- _ O
Samtang -X- _ O
si -X- _ O
Turnbull -X- _ B-PER
, -X- _ O
gidakop -X- _ O
sab -X- _ O
tungod -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
kasong -X- _ O
pagpanag-iya -X- _ O
og -X- _ O
delikado -X- _ O
ug -X- _ O
'out -X- _ O
of -X- _ O
control -X- _ O
' -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
mga -X- _ O
iro. -X- _ O
Sa -X- _ O
pahayag -X- _ O
ni -X- _ O
Turnbull -X- _ B-PER
, -X- _ O
giprotektahan -X- _ O
lamang -X- _ O
siya -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
mga -X- _ O
iro -X- _ O
tungod -X- _ O
nihulbot -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
ilang -X- _ O
pusil -X- _ O
ang -X- _ O
mga -X- _ O
pulis. -X- _ O
Ang -X- _ O
mga -X- _ O
dog -X- _ O
lovers -X- _ O
naghimo -X- _ O
og -X- _ O
petisyon -X- _ O
online -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
moabot -X- _ O
na -X- _ O
ngadto -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
64,000 -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
pirma -X- _ O
alang -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
pagpangayo -X- _ O
og -X- _ O
hustisya -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
kamatayon -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
maong -X- _ O
mga -X- _ O
iro -X- _ O
. -X- _ O

5 -X- _ O
KA -X- _ O
IRO -X- _ O
, -X- _ O
PATAY -X- _ O
HUMAN -X- _ O
GIPANGHILOAN -X- _ O
Hustisya -X- _ O
ang -X- _ O
gisinggit -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
pamilyang -X- _ O
Go -X- _ B-PER
human -X- _ O
gihiloan -X- _ O
ang -X- _ O
ilang -X- _ O
lima -X- _ O
ka -X- _ O
iro -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
wala -X- _ O
pa -X- _ O
mailhing -X- _ O
suspek. -X- _ O
Gisagop -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
maong -X- _ O
pamilya -X- _ O
ang -X- _ O
mga -X- _ O
iro -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
sila -X- _ O
si -X- _ O
Kobe -X- _ O
, -X- _ O
Batman -X- _ O
, -X- _ O
Bruce -X- _ O
, -X- _ O
Kikay -X- _ O
, -X- _ O
ug -X- _ O
Daya -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
Guadalupe -X- _ B-LOC
, -X- _ I-LOC
Cebu -X- _ I-LOC
City. -X- _ I-LOC
Apan -X- _ O
usa -X- _ O
ka -X- _ O
adlaw -X- _ O
, -X- _ O
nakita -X- _ O
nalang -X- _ O
kini -X- _ O
nilang -X- _ O
wala -X- _ O
na'y -X- _ O
kinabuhi -X- _ O
ug -X- _ O
nagdugo -X- _ O
ang -X- _ O
baba -X- _ O
. -X- _ O

LALAKING -X- _ O
HUBOG -X- _ O
, -X- _ O
GIPUSIL -X- _ O
PATAY -X- _ O
SA -X- _ O
SAN -X- _ B-LOC
JOSE -X- _ I-LOC
Usa -X- _ O
ka -X- _ O
lalaking -X- _ O
gituohang -X- _ O
lango -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
ilimnong -X- _ O
makahubog -X- _ O
ang -X- _ O
gipusil -X- _ O
patay -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
Barangay -X- _ B-LOC
Basak -X- _ I-LOC
sa -X- _ O
San -X- _ B-LOC
Jose -X- _ I-LOC
mga -X- _ O
alas-6:10 -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
gabii -X- _ O
niadtong -X- _ O
Martes -X- _ O
, -X- _ O
May -X- _ O
16 -X- _ O
, -X- _ O
2023. -X- _ O
Giila -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
kapulisan -X- _ O
ang -X- _ O
biktima -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
si -X- _ O
Roberto -X- _ B-PER
Quilpo -X- _ I-PER
, -X- _ O
55 -X- _ O
anyos -X- _ O
, -X- _ O
minyo -X- _ O
, -X- _ O
ug -X- _ O
lumolupyo -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
naasoy -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
lugar. -X- _ O
Samtang -X- _ O
ang -X- _ O
suspek -X- _ O
giila -X- _ O
nga -X- _ O
si -X- _ O
Joseph -X- _ B-PER
Quisel -X- _ I-PER
Salapayni -X- _ I-PER
, -X- _ O
27 -X- _ O
anyos -X- _ O
, -X- _ O
ulitawo -X- _ O
, -X- _ O
ug -X- _ O
residente -X- _ O
sab -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
maong -X- _ O
dapit. -X- _ O
Sumala -X- _ O
pa -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
imbestigasyon -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
kapulisan -X- _ O
, -X- _ O
gituohang -X- _ O
hubog -X- _ O
ug -X- _ O
nag-amok -X- _ O
ang -X- _ O
biktima -X- _ O
ngadto -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
panimalay -X- _ O
ni -X- _ O
Salapayni. -X- _ B-PER
Giingong -X- _ O
gihulga -X- _ O
sab -X- _ O
niini -X- _ O
ang -X- _ O
pamilya -X- _ O
ni -X- _ O
Salapayni -X- _ B-PER
gamit -X- _ O
ang -X- _ O
sundang. -X- _ O
Tungod -X- _ O
niini -X- _ O
, -X- _ O
giingong -X- _ O
nibalos -X- _ O
si -X- _ O
Salapayni -X- _ B-PER
pinaagi -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
pagpusil -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
biktima -X- _ O
gamit -X- _ O
ang -X- _ O
improvised -X- _ O
shotgun -X- _ O
kon -X- _ O
'sulpak -X- _ O
' -X- _ O
aron -X- _ O
depensahan -X- _ O
ang -X- _ O
iyang -X- _ O
kaugalingon -X- _ O
ug -X- _ O
ang -X- _ O
iyang -X- _ O
pamilya. -X- _ O
Human -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
insidente -X- _ O
, -X- _ O
gidakop -X- _ O
ang -X- _ O
suspek -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
mga -X- _ O
nirespondeng -X- _ O
kapulisan -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
San -X- _ B-LOC
Jose -X- _ I-LOC
ug -X- _ O
gidala -X- _ O
siya -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
estasyon -X- _ O
alang -X- _ O
sa -X- _ O
tukmang -X- _ O
disposisyon -X- _ O
. -X- _ O
